<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Deuteronomy 11</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Deuteronomy 11</title><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="1"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And you shall love the Lord your God and keep his charge and his statutes<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and his judgments and his commandments every day.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="2">And you shall know today that it is not with your children who<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>did not know and did not see the reprimand of the Lord your God,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>his greatness, his strong hand and<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>his outstretched arm,</l><l n="3">And his miracles,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and his deeds which he did in the midst of Egypt to Pharaoh,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>king of Egypt, and to all his land,</l><l n="4">And what he did<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to the army of Egypt: to their horses and to their chariots, how<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>he flowed the waters of the Red Sea over their faces<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>when they pursued you, and how the Lord has destroyed them to<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>this day,</l><l n="5">And what he did to you in the wilderness<milestone unit="page" n="299v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>until you came to this place,</l><l n="6">And what he did<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to Dathan and Abiram, sons of Eliab, son of Reuben,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>how the earth opened its mouth and swallowed them up and<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>their households and their tents and all<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the prey that was at their side, in the midst of all Israel,</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Because it is your eyes that saw all the great deeds of the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>which he did.</l><l n="8">And you shall keep all the<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>commandments which I command you this day, so that you may get strong<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and come and inherit the land that you are crossing<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>there to inherit it,</l><l n="9">And so that you may prolong<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>your days in the land, which the Lord swore to your fathers to give<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to them and to their offspring, a land flowing |with| milk and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>honey.</l><l n="10">Because the land, where you are coming to inherit<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>it, is not as the land of Egypt, from where you came out,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>where you sowed your seed, and it was necessary to water<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>it with your foot, as a garden of grass.</l><l n="11">But<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the land to which you are crossing to inherit it is a land of mountains and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>valleys, and it drinks water from the rain of the skies.</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>A land which the Lord your God explores: the eyes<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>of the Lord your God are always on it, from the beginning of the year to the end<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of the year.</l><l n="13">And it shall be, if you will indeed listen to my commandments<milestone unit="page" n="300r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>which I command you today, to love the service of the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>your God and to serve him with all your heart and with all<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>your soul,</l><l n="14">Then I will give you the rain of your land in its due times,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the summer rain and the autumn rain, that you may gather<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in your grain and your must and your olive oil.</l><l n="15">And you will eat<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and be full, and I will also give grass in your fields for your cattle.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="16">Take heed to yourselves, lest your heart be deceived<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and you turn aside from the good way and serve other<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>gods and worship them,</l><l n="17">And<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>the Lord’s anger will be kindled against you, and he will shut up the heaven,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and there will be no rain, and that the land will not give its fruit,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and <supplied reason="lost">you</supplied> will perish quickly from off the good land which the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>your God is giving you.</l><l n="18">And you shall lay up these my words<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>in your heart and in your soul, and bind<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>them for a sign on your hand that they may be as frontlets<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>between your eyes,</l><l n="19">And you shall teach<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>them to your children, to speak about them when you sit in your house<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and when you walk by the way and before you lie down and<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>after you rise,</l><l n="20">And you shall write them in a way on the doorposts<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>of your house, and on your gates, <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>so that<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the words of the Law may always be in your mind,<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/></l><l n="21">So that your<milestone unit="page" n="300v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, on the land<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>which the Lord swore to your fathers to give them,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>as the days of the skies and the earth.</l><l n="22"><milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Because, if you will indeed keep all these commandments<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>which I command you, to do it, to love the service<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of Lord your God, to walk in all his ways, and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to cling to his service:</l><l n="23">Then the Lord will destroy<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>all these kingdoms before you, and<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>you shall inherit kingdoms greater and mightier<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>than you.</l><l n="24">Every place on which the <supplied reason="lost">soles</supplied> of your feet<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>shall step will be yours, from the wilderness and Lebanon,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>from the great river, the river Euphrates, to the western<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>sea will be your border.</l><l n="25">Not a man will be able to stand<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>before you. The Lord your God will put your fear of your dread<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>on all the faces of all the land that you shall step<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>on, as he spoke to you.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/><emph>Parashat Reʾeh</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="26">See: I am giving<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>before you today a blessing and a curse.</l><l n="27"><milestone unit="page" n="301r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>The blessing: if you listen to the commandments of the Lord your God<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>which I command you this day.</l><l n="28">And the curse:<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>if you do not listen to the commandments of the Lord your God, but go<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>aside from the way which I command you today, to go after the service<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of other gods, which you have not known.</l><l n="29">And it shall be,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>when the Lord your God will bring you to the land to which you are coming<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to inherit it, that you shall put the blessing on Mount<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Gerizim, and the curse on Mount<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Ebal.</l><l n="30">Lo, they are at the ford of Jordan,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>on the west |side|, by the way where the sun goes down, in the land<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of the Canaanites who dwell in the steppe opposite<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Gilgal, beside the lands of plains of Moreh.</l><l n="31">Because you<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>are passing over Jordan to come to inherit the<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>land which the Lord your God is giving you. And when you inherit<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>it and dwell therein,</l><l n="32">Then you shall be watchful<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to do all the statutes and judgments<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>which I set before you today.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Deu 11:20.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
