<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Exodus 4</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Exodus 4</title><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="1">And Moses answered<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and said, ‘But, lo, they will not believe me and will not listen to my word,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>because they will say, “The divine Presence of Lord has not appeared to you.”’</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="2">And the Lord said to him, ‘What is that in your hand?’<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And he said, ‘A staff.’</l><l n="3">And he said, ‘Throw it<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>on the ground.’ And he threw it on the ground, and it became a serpent, and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Moses fled from before it.</l><l n="4">And the Lord said to Moses,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>‘Reach out your hand and take it by the tail.’ And he reached out<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>his hand and caught it, and it became a staff in his hand.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="5">‘So that they will believe that<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the divine Presence of Lord God of their fathers, the God<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you.’</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>And the Lord said furthermore to him, ‘Put now your hand into your bosom.’ And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>he put his hand into his bosom, and he took it out, lo, his hand became<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>leprous like snow.</l><l n="7">And he said,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>‘Put your hand back into your bosom.’ And he put his hand back into his bosom. And he took it out<milestone unit="page" n="91v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>from his bosom, and, lo, it had gone back like its flesh.</l><l n="8">‘And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>it shall be, if they do not believe you, neither listen to the word of the first<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>sign, that they will believe the word of the latter sign.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="9">And it shall be, if they also do not believe in these two<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>signs and will not listen to your word: and you shall take<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of the water of the Nile, and pour it on the dry ground. And<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>it will be the water which you take from the Nile, and it will become blood on the dry<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>ground.’</l><l n="10">And Moses said to the Lord, ‘I pray you, oh<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Lord, I am not a man of words. Neither formerly nor<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>the day before nor since the time you spoke to Your servant. Because I am heavy of speech and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of a heavy of tongue.’</l><l n="11">And the Lord said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>‘Who set a mouth for man? Or who set the dumb,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>or who set the deaf, <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><supplied reason="lost"><emph>or</emph></supplied>
							<emph>the seeing,</emph>
							<supplied reason="lost"><emph>or</emph></supplied>
							<emph>the blind</emph>?<anchor xml:id="add001"/> Lo, have not I the Lord?</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="12">And now go, and I will be with be with your mouth,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and I will teach you what you shall say.’</l><l n="13"><milestone unit="line" n="16"/>And he said, ‘Oh my Lord, I pray you, send now by the hand<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of whom you will send.’</l><l n="14">And the anger of the Lord was kindled against Moses,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and he said, ‘Lo, there is Aaron, the Levite, your brother. I know that he surely<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>speaks well. And also, lo, he comes forth to meet you, and he will see<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>you, and he will be glad in his heart.</l><l n="15">And you shall speak to him, and<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>put the words in his mouth, and I will be with your mouth,<milestone unit="page" n="92r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and with his mouth, and I will teach you what<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>you shall do.</l><l n="16">And he shall speak for you<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to the people. And it shall be that he will be for you instead of a mouth, and you<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>will be for him instead of an angel.</l><l n="17">And you shall take <addSpan spanTo="#add002"/><emph>this</emph><anchor xml:id="add002"/> staff<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in your hand, with which you will do the signs.’</l><l n="18">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Moses went. And he returned to Jethro, his father-in-law, and said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>‘Let me go now, and let me return to my brothers who are in Egypt and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>see whether they are still alive.’ And Jethro said to Moses, ‘Go<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>in health.’</l><l n="19">And the LORD said to Moses in Midian,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>‘Go, return to Egypt, because all the men<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>who sought to take your life have died.’</l><l n="20">And Moses took<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>his wife and his children, and set them<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>on a donkey, and he returned to the land of Egypt. And Moses took<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the staff of God in his hand.</l><l n="21">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the Lord said to Moses, ‘When you go to return to Egypt, see<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>all those signs that I have put in your hand and do them<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>before Pharaoh. But I will harden his heart,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and he will not let the people go.</l><l n="22">And you shall say<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to Pharaoh, “<addSpan spanTo="#add003"/><emph>Thus said the LORD</emph><anchor xml:id="add003"/>, “Israel is my firstborn son.</l><l n="23">And<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>I said to you, “Let my son go, and he may serve me.<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And if you are not willing to let him go, lo, I will kill<milestone unit="page" n="92v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>your firstborn son.”””’</l><l n="24">And it was on the way at the place of overnight stay, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the Lord made him ill, and wanted to kill him.</l><l n="25"><milestone unit="line" n="3"/>And Zipporah took a razor and cut off her son’s foreskin<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and touched his feet, and she said, ‘Because you are a renewal of blood<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>to me.’</l><l n="26">And he recovered thanks to that. Then<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>she said, ‘A renewal of blood for those circumcised.’</l><l n="27"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the Lord said to Aaron, ‘Go to meet Moses to the<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>wilderness.’ And he went and met him in the Mountain of God,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and he kissed him.</l><l n="28">And Moses told Aaron<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>all the words of the Lord that he had sent him and all the<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>signs which he had commanded him.</l><l n="29">And Moses and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Aaron went and gathered all the elders of the children of Israel.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="30">And Aaron spoke all the words which<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the Lord had spoken to Moses, and did the signs in the sight<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of the people.</l><l n="31">And the people believed, and they heard<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>that the Lord remembered the children of Israel, and that he had seen<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>their affliction, and they bowed down and worshiped.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
