<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 13</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Genesis 13</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="1"><milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And Abram went from Egypt, he, and his wife, and all that<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he had, and Lot with him, southward.</l><l n="2">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Abram was very rich in livestock, in silver, and in gold.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="3">And he went on his journeys from the south even as far as to Bethel<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>to the place where his tent had been at the beginning,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>between Bethel and Ai,</l><l n="4">To the place<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of the altar, which he had made there at the beginning: and there Abram called<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>upon the name of the Lord.</l><l n="5">And Lot, who was going<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>with Abram, also had sheep, and cattle, and tents.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And the land was not able to give place to them, that they might dwell together, because<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>their property were great, so that they could not dwell together.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="7">And there was a strife between the herdsmen of Abram’s cattle<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and the herdsmen of Lot’s cattle:<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and the Canaanites and the Perizzites dwelt then<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>in the land.</l><l n="8">And Abram said to Lot, ‘I pray you,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>let there be no strife between you and me, and between my herdsmen<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and your herdsmen, because we are kinsmen.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="9">Lo, the whole land is before you, separate<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>now yourself from me, if you go to the left, then let me go to the right,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and if you go to the right, then let me go to the left.’</l><l n="10"><milestone unit="page" n="18r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And Lot raised his eyes and saw all the valley of Jordan<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>that it was all |well-|watered, before the Lord destroyed<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Sodom and Gomorrah, like the garden of the Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>like the land of Egypt, in the direction as you came to Zoar.</l><l n="11">So<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Lot chose for himself all the valley of Jordan, and Lot journeyed<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>east. And they separated, the one from his brother.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="12">Abram settled in the land of Canaan, and Lot<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>in the cities of the valley. And he pitched his tent as far as Sodom.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="13">But the men of Sodom were evil and sinned greatly<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>before the Lord.</l><l n="14">And the Lord said to Abram,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>after Lot was separated from him, ‘Lift up now your eyes,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and look from the place where you are northward, and southward,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and eastward, and westward.</l><l n="15">For all the land<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>that you see, I will give to you and to your offspring forever.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="16">And I will set your offspring like the dust<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of the earth, so that if a man could count the dust of the earth,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>your offspring also could be counted.</l><l n="17">Arise, walk through the land<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to its length and to its width, because I will give it to you.’</l><l n="18">So<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Abram pitched his tent and lived in the plain lands of Mamre,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>which is in Hebron, and built there an altar before the Lord.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
