<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 31</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Deuteronomy 31</supplied></title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l><emph>Parashat Vayelech</emph></l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="1">And Moses went
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and spoke these words to all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            Israel.</l>
                        <l n="2">And he said to them, ‘I am a hundred
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            twenty years old today. I will not be able to go out and come in anymore.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            And the Lord has said to me, “You will not cross this Jordan.”</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="3">The divine Presence of the Lord your God: he is crossing
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            before you. He will destroy these nations
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            from before you, and you shall inherit them. Joshua: he is crossing
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            before you, as the Lord has spoken.</l>
                        <l n="4">And the Lord will do
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            to them as he did to Sihon and to Og, kings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            of the Amorites, and to their land, that he destroyed them.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="334r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="5">And the Lord will give them up before you, and you shall do to them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            according to all the commandments which I have commanded you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="6">Grow stronger and strengthen yourselves. Do not fear and do not be
                            broken down
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            before them, because the help of the Lord your God: he is
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            the one who goes with you. He will not emaciate you and will not leave
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            you.’</l>
                        <l n="7">And Moses called Joshua and said
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            to him in the sight of all Israel, ‘Grow stronger and strengthen
                            yourself, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            you will go with this people to the land which the Lord has sworn
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            to them to give them, and you will put them in possession of it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="8">And the divine Presence of the Lord: he is the one who goes before you.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            His help will be with you, he will not emaciate you and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            will not leave you. You shall not fear and be broken down.’</l>
                        <l n="9">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            And Moses wrote this Law and gave
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            it to the priests, sons of Levi, who were carrying
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and to all the elders of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            Israel.</l>
                        <l n="10">And Moses commanded them, saying,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            ‘At the beginning of every seven years, in the set time of the year of remission,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            at the feast of Sukkot,</l>
                        <l n="11">When all Israel has come to appear
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            before the directions of Lord your God in the place which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            he will choose, you shall read this Law in front of all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            Israel in their ears.</l>
                        <l n="12">Gather the
                            <milestone unit="page" n="334v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            people together — the men and the women and the infants and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            your stranger who is in your cities — that they may hear and that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            they may learn and fear the Lord your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            and be watchful to do all the words of this Law.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="13">And their children who have not known
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            may hear and learn to fear the Lord your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            all the days you are living on the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            to which you are crossing the Jordan to inherit
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            it.’</l>
                        <l n="14">And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Lo,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            your days to die have come close. Call Joshua
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and stand up in the tent of meeting, that I may command him.’
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            And Moses and Joshua went and stood up in the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="15">And the divine Presence of the Lord appeared in the tent
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            in a pillar of cloud, and the pillar of cloud stood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            over the door of the tent.</l>
                        <l n="16">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            the Lord said to Moses, ‘Lo, you will lie down with your fathers,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and this people will rise up and go astray after the service
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of foreign gods of the land into the midst of which it is coming,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            and it will leave my service and break my covenant
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            which I have made with them.</l>
                        <l n="17">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            my anger will be kindled at it on that day, and I will resign
                            <milestone unit="page" n="335r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            from being gracious, and I will hide my directions from them, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            they will be |left| for being devoured, and many evils and troubles
                            shall befall it.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            And it will say on that day, “Lo, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the divine Presence of my God is not present among me,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            all these evils have befallen me.”</l>
                        <l n="18">And I
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            will surely hide my directions in that day because of all the evils
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            which it has done, because it turned to the service of other gods.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="19">So now write this song for yourselves
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and teach it to the children of Israel.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            Put it in their mouths, that this song may be a witness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            for me against the children of Israel.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="20">When I will bring it to the land which I swore
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            to their fathers, a land flowing |with| milk and honey, and it will eat and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            be full and quench, and it will turn to the service of other
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            gods, and they will serve them, and they will annoy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            me, and it will break my covenant,</l>
                        <l n="21">Then
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            it shall be, when many evils and troubles will befall it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            this song shall testify before them as a witness, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            it shall not be forgotten from the mouths of their offspring. Because I know
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            its inclination that <supplied reason="lost">it is doing</supplied>
                            today, before I bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            it to the land which I swore.’</l>
                        <l n="22">And Moses wrote
                            <milestone unit="page" n="335v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            this song the same day and taught it
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            to the children of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="23">And he commanded Joshua, son
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            of Nun, and said, ‘Grow stronger and strengthen yourself, because you
                            will bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the children of Israel to the land which I swore to them.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            And my hep will be with you.’</l>
                        <l n="24">And it was
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            when Moses had finished writing the words of this Law
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            on a scroll until they were finished,</l>
                        <l n="25">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            Moses commanded the Levites, who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="26">to ‘Take this book of the Law,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and put it by the side of the ark of the covenant of the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            your God, that it may be there for you as a witness.</l>
                        <l n="27">Because I know
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            your rebellion and your hard neck. Lo, while I am yet
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            alive with you today, you have been rebellious before the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and |you will be| all the more |so| after my death.</l>
                        <l n="28">Gather
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            to me all the elders of your tribes and your overseers,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            so I may speak these words in their ears
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and call the skies and earth as witness regarding them.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="29">Because I know that after my death you will utterly destroy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            your ways and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            And evil will befall you in the latter days, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            you will do things that seem bad in the eyes of the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="336r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            to annoy him with the work of your hands.’</l>
                        <l n="30">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            Moses spoke in the ears of all the community of Israel the words
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            of this song until they were ended. </l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
