<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Exodus 27</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Exodus 27</title><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="1">And you shall make<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>an altar of acacia wood. Five cubits long,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and five cubits broad, the altar shall be foursquare,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and the height of it shall be three cubits.</l><l n="2">And you shall make<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the horns of it on its four corners.<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Its horns shall be one with it. And you shall overlay it with bronze.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="3">And you shall make its cauldrons to remove its ashes,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and its brushes and its cups and forks<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and its censers. You shall make all its equipment of bronze.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="4">And you shall make for it a grate, a network of bronze,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and on the net you shall make four bronze rings<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>on its four corners.</l><l n="5">And<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>you shall put it under the ledge<ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> of the altar beneath<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>so that the net may be halfway up the altar.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And you shall make poles of acacia wood for the altar and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>overlay them with bronze.</l><l n="7">And the poles shall be put<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>into the rings, and the poles shall be<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>on <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>both</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> sides of the altar when it is carried.</l><l n="8"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>You shall make it of hollow boards as <supplied reason="lost">you were</supplied> shown<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>in the mountain. They shall do it so.</l><l n="9">And you shall make the court<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of the tabernacle: for the south side, southward,<milestone unit="page" n="131r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>curtains for the court of twined linen of a hundred cubits long<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>for one side,</l><l n="10">And its twenty pillars and its twenty bases<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>of bronze, their hooks and their bands<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of silver.</l><l n="11">And so for the north side:<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in length, curtains of a hundred cubits long and its<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>twenty pillars and their twenty bases of bronze, the hooks<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of the pillars and their bands of silver.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="12">And the breadth of the court on the west side:<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>curtains of fifty cubits, their pillars ten and their bases<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>ten.</l><l n="13">And the breadth of the court on the east side,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>eastward, fifty cubits.</l><l n="14">And curtains of fifteen<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>cubits for one side, their pillars three, and their bases<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>three.</l><l n="15">And on the second side:<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>curtains of fifteen <supplied reason="lost">cubits</supplied>, their pillars three and their bases three.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="16">And for the gate of the court: a cover of twenty cubits,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of blue and purple and scarlet silk and twined<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>linen of embroiderer’s work, their pillars four and their<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>bases four.</l><l n="17">All the pillars all around the court:<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>banded with silver, their hooks of silver<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and their bases of bronze.</l><l n="18">The length of the court:<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>a hundred cubits, and the breadth of it fifty cubits, fifty cubits,<milestone unit="page" n="131v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and the height five cubits of twined linen, and their bases<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of bronze.</l><l n="19">All the equipment of the tabernacle for all<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>its service, and all its pegs, and all the pegs of the<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>court: of bronze.<milestone unit="line" n="5"/><emph>Parashat Tetzaveh</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="20">And you shall command the children<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of Israel that they shall bring you<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>pure beaten olive oil for the light, to kindle the lamp continually.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="21"><supplied reason="lost">In</supplied> the tent of meeting, outside the veil which<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>is above the Law, Aaron and his sons shall arrange<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>it from evening until morning before the Lord. It shall be a statute forever<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>throughout their generations from the children of Israel.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Lit. ‘rim’.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
