<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 23</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Deuteronomy <supplied reason="lost">23</supplied></title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Deut023-P318r-L21_trl" n="21" prev="ADub.III.73.005.022.trl.xml#Deut022-P318r-L21_trl" />
                        <l n="1">A man shall not take
                        <milestone unit="page" n="318v" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        his father’s wife, and he shall not uncover his father’s nakedness.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="2">One who has crushed nakedness or spilled by being cut off
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            shall not come into the community of the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="3">A bastard shall not come into the community of the Lord;
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            even his tenth generation shall not come into the community of the
                            Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="4">An Ammonite or Moabite shall not come into the community of the
                            Lord; even
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            their tenth generation shall not come into the community of the Lord
                            forever,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="5">Because they did not meet you with bread
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and with water in the way, when you came out from Egypt, and because
                            they hired
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            Balaam, son of Beor, of Pethor
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            of Aram Naharaim against you to curse you.</l>
                        <l n="6">But the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            your God was not willing to listen to Balaam, and the Lord your God turned
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            the curse into a blessing for you, because the Lord your God loved
                            you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="7">You shall not seek their health or their well-being
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            all your days forever.</l>
                        <l n="8">You shall not despise an Edomite,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            because he is your brother. You shall not despise an Egyptian, because
                            you were a stranger
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            in his land.</l>
                        <l n="9">The children that <delSpan spanTo="#del001" />they have<anchor
                                xml:id="del001" />
                            <addSpan spanTo="#add001" /><emph>are born</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"
                             /> to them:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            the third generation shall come into the community of the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="10">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            When you go out encamped against your enemies, then you shall keep
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            yourself from every evil thing.</l>
                        <l n="11">If there is among you a man who
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            is not clean by reason of some event in the night, then he shall go outside
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            the camp, he shall not come inside the camp.</l>
                        <l n="12">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="319r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            And it shall be: in the evening he shall wash his body with water, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            when the sun sets he shall come inside the camp.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="13">You shall have a place also outside the camp, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            you shall go out there, outside.</l>
                        <l n="14">And you shall have a peg
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            with your weapons of war, and it shall be, when you will sit outside,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            you shall dig with it and shall go back and cover what comes out of
                            you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="15">Because the Lord your God walks in the midst
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            of your camp, to deliver you and to give up your enemies before you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            so your camp shall be holy, so he shall not see in you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            any shameful thing and turn aside from you.</l>
                        <l n="16">You shall not take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and give |back| to his master a servant who escapes<ref target="#fn1"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> to you from his master.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="17">He shall dwell with you, in your midst, in that place which he
                            shall choose
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            in one of your cities, where it seems good for him.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            You shall not torment him.</l>
                        <l n="18">There shall be no temple prostitute of the daughters
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            of Israel, and there shall be no temple prostitute of the sons of
                            Israel.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="19">You shall not bring the endowment of a harlot or the price of a dog
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            into the house of the Lord your God for any vow, because these are an abomination
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to the Lord your God, even the two of them.</l>
                        <l n="20">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            You shall not give for profit to your brother: profit on silver, profit on
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            grain, profit on anything that is given for profit.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="21">You may give for profit to a foreigner, but to your brother
                            <milestone unit="page" n="319v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            you shall not give for profit, so that the Lord your God may bless you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            in all that you reach out your hand to in the land where you are coming
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            to inherit it.</l>
                        <l n="22">If you make a vow to the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            <addSpan spanTo="#add002" /><emph>your God</emph><anchor xml:id="add002"
                             />, you shall not delay to pay it, because the Lord your God will
                            surely require
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            it of you, and it would be sin to you.</l>
                        <l n="23">But if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            you refrain from vowing, there will be no sin in you.</l>
                        <l n="24">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            You shall keep that which has passed from your lips and do as you vowed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            to the Lord your God: the freewill offering that you spoke with your
                            mouth.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="25">If you come into your neighbour’s vineyard, then you may eat grapes
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            as you wish, until you are full, but you shall not put any into your
                            vessel.</l>
                        <l n="26">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            If you come into your neighbour’s the standing grain, then you may pluck
                            the ears with your hand,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            but you shall not elevate a sickle over your neighbour’s standing
                            grain.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Lit. ‘saves himself’.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
