<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 12</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Numbers 12</title><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="1"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And Miriam and Aaron spoke about Moses, about the matter of<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>the Cushite woman whom he had taken — because he had taken an Cushite woman.</l><l n="2"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And they said, ‘Has the Lord only just spoken by Moses?<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Lo, he has spoken also by us.’ And the Lord heard it.</l><l n="3"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And Moses, the prophet, was much more humble than all the men<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>who were on the face of the earth.</l><l n="4">And<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the Lord spoke suddenly to Moses and to Aaron and to Miriam, ‘Come out,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>even the three of you, to the tent of meeting.’ And the three of them came out.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="5">And the divine Presence of the Lord came down in the pillar of the cloud<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and stood in the door of the tent and called Aaron<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and Miriam, and they both went out.</l><l n="6">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>he said, ‘Hear now my words: If there is a prophet among you,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>I, the Lord, will be known to him in a vision, I will speak with him through a dream.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="7">Not so is my servant Moses; in all my house<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>he is faithful.</l><l n="8">Mind to mind I will speak with him and<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>through vision and not through riddles, and he sees the divine Presence of the Lord.<milestone unit="page" n="232v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And why did you not fear to speak about my servant Moses?’</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="9">And the anger of the Lord was kindled against them, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>his divine Presence went.</l><l n="10">And the cloud departed<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>from over the tent. And, lo, Miriam became leprous, like snow. And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Aaron turned to Miriam, and, lo, she was leprous.</l><l n="11">And Aaron said<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>to Moses, ‘I pray you, my lord, do not set the punishment<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of a sin on us which we did foolishly, and which we sinned.</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>I pray you, let her not be like the dead who, when he comes out of<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>his mother’s womb, half of his flesh is eaten up.’</l><l n="13">And<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Moses prayed to the Lord, saying, ‘I pray you, oh God,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>heal her though, now.’</l><l n="14">And the Lord said<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to Moses, ‘And if her father had but spit<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>in her face, should she not be ashamed seven days? She shall be shut up<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>outside the camp seven days, and after that let her be gathered back.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="15">And Miriam was shut up outside the camp seven<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>days. And the people did not travel until Miriam was gathered back.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="16">And afterward the people set out from Hazeroth,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and they camped in the wilderness of Paran.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
