<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 35</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 35</title><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="1">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>God said to Jacob, ‘Arise, go up to Bethel, and dwell<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>there. And make there an altar to God, who appeared<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>to you when you fled from before Esau your brother.’</l><l n="2"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>So Jacob said to his household, and to all that were with him,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>‘Put away the foreign gods that are among you, and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>purify yourselves, and change your garments.</l><l n="3">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>let us arise, and go up to Bethel, and let me make there an altar to God,<milestone unit="page" n="57r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>who answered me in the day of my distress, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>his help was with me in the way that I went.’</l><l n="4">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>they gave to Jacob all the foreign gods which were in their hand,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and all their earrings which were in their ears.<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And Jacob buried them under the linden which was by Shechem.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="5">And they journeyed, and the terror of God<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>was on the people of the cities that were around them,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and they did not pursue after the sons of Jacob.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And Jacob came to Luz, which is in the land of Canaan, that is, Bethel,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>he and all the people that were with him.</l><l n="7">And he built<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>there an altar, and he called the place El-bethel because<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the angels appeared to him there, when he fled from before<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>his brother.</l><l n="8">But Deborah, Rebekah’s nurse, died,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and she was buried beneath Bethel,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>under an oak. And he called its name Allon-Bacuth.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="9">And God’s divine Presence appeared to Jacob<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>again, when he came out of Paddan-Aram, and blessed him.</l><l n="10"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>And God said to him, ‘Your name is Jacob. Your name will not be called Jacob, only, anymore,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>but also Israel will be your name.’<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And he called his name Israel.</l><l n="11">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>God said to him, ‘I am the mighty God. Spread and multiply. A kingdom<milestone unit="page" n="57v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and a multitude of kingdoms will be of you, and kings will come out from your hips.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="12">And the land that I gave to Abraham and to Isaac:<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>I will give it to you, and I will give the land to your offspring after you.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="13">And the divine Presence of God went up from on Jacob<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in the place where he had spoken with him.</l><l n="14">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Jacob set up a pillar in the place where he had spoken with him,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>a pillar of stone. And he <supplied reason="lost">poured</supplied> a drink offering on it, and he <supplied reason="lost">poured</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>oil on it.</l><l n="15">And Jacob called the<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>name of the place Bethel, because God spoke<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>with him there.</l><l n="16">And they journeyed from Bethel.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And there was still a span of the land to pass to come to Ephrath,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and Rachel travailed, and she she hardened in labour.</l><l n="17"><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>And it was, when she hardened in labour, that the<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>midwife said to her, ‘Do not fear, because this, too, is a son for you.’</l><l n="18"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And it was, as her soul was departing, because she died, that she called his name<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>Ben-Oni. And his father called him Benjamin.</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Rachel died. And she was buried on the way to Ephrath. It is Beth-Lehem.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="20">And Jacob set a pillar on her grave.<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>It is the pillar of Rachel’s grave to this day.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="21">And Israel journeyed, and pitched his tent beyond<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>Migdal Eder.</l><l n="22">And it was, when Israel sojourned<milestone unit="page" n="58r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>in that land, that Reuben went and lay with Bilhah, the concubine.<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of his father. And Israel heard it. Now the sons of Jacob were<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>twelve.</l><l n="23">The sons of Leah: Jacob’s firstborn,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Reuben, and Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Zebulun.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="24">The sons of Rachel: Joseph, and Benjamin.</l><l n="25">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the sons of Bilhah, Rachel’s maidservant: Dan, and Naphtali.</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the sons of Zilpah, Leah’s maidservant: Gad, and Asher. These are<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the sons of Jacob, who were born to him in Paddan-Aram.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="27">And Jacob came to Isaac his father to Mamre, to the city<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of Arbah, it is Hebron, where Abraham<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and Isaac lived.</l><l n="28">And the days of Isaac were a hundred and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>eighty years.</l><l n="29">And Isaac rested and died, and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>was gathered to his people, being old and full of days. And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>his sons Esau and Jacob buried him.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
