<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Exodus 3</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Exodus 3</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex003-P89v-L4_trl" n="4" prev="ADub.III.73.002.002.trl.xml#Ex002-P89v-L4_trl" />
                        <l n="1">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            And Moses pastured the flock of Jethro, his father-in-law, the priest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            of Midian. And he led the flock behind the wilderness,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            and came to the mountain of God, to Horeb.</l>
                        <l n="2">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            the angel of the Lord appeared to him in the midst of fire
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            out of the midst of the blackthorn. And he looked, and, lo, the blackthorn
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            burned with fire, and the blackthorn was not consumed.</l>
                        <l n="3">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            And Moses said, ‘Let me now turn aside, and see this
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            great sight, why the blackthorn is not burnt.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="4">And the Lord saw that he turned aside to look at, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            God called to him out of the midst of the blackthorn, and said, ‘Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            Moses.’ And he said, ‘Lo, am I here.’</l>
                        <l n="5">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            God said, ‘Do not come near here. Take off your shoes from your feet,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            because the place on which you stand is holy ground.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="6">And He said, ‘I am the God of your father, the God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.’ And Moses hid
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            his face, because he was afraid to look on the divine Presence.</l>
                        <l n="7">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            And the Lord said, ‘I have surely seen the affliction of my people
                            <milestone unit="page" n="90r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            who are in Egypt, and have heard their cry in front of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            of their oppressors, because I learned their sorrows.</l>
                        <l n="8">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            my command has come down to rescue them from the hand of the Egypt, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            to bring them up from that land to a better land and widespread land flowing
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            |with| milk and honey, to the place of the Canaanites, and the Hittites,
                            and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="9">And now, lo, the cry of the children of Israel has come
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            before me, and also I have seen the oppression with which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            the Egyptians oppress them.</l>
                        <l n="10">And now come,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and I will send you to Pharaoh, and bring out my people,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the children of Israel from Egypt.’</l>
                        <l n="11">And Moses said
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            to God, ‘Who am I that I should go to Pharaoh and that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            I should bring out the children of Israel from Egypt?’</l>
                        <l n="12">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            God said, ‘Because my help will be with you, and this
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            is a sign for you that I am sending you. When you will bring out the people
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            from Egypt, you will serve God on this mountain.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="13">And Moses said to God, ‘Lo,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            if I come to the children of Israel and say to them, “The God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of your fathers has sent me to you,” and if they say to me, “What is his name?”,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            what will I say to them?’</l>
                        <l n="14">And God said to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            ‘<emph>I am who I am</emph>,’ and He said, ‘Thus shall you say to the children
                            <milestone unit="page" n="90v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            of Israel, “<emph>I Am</emph> has sent me to you.”’</l>
                        <l n="15">And God said moreover
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            to Moses, ‘Thus you shall say to the children of Israel, “The Lord God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            of your fathers, the God <supplied reason="lost">of</supplied> Abraham,
                            the God of Isaac, and the God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of Jacob, has sent me to you.” This is my name forever,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and this is my memorial to every single generation.</l>
                        <l n="16">Go, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            gather the elders of Israel together, and say to them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            “The divine Presence of the Lord God of your fathers appeared to me,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob, saying, “I have surely remembered
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            you and what has been done to you in Egypt.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="17">And I have said let me bring you out from the affliction of Egypt
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            to the land of the Canaanites and the Hittites and the Amorites and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            Perizzites and the Hivites and the Jebusites, to a land flowing
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            |with| milk and honey.””</l>
                        <l n="18">And they will listen to your voice, and you shall come, you and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            the elders of Israel, to the king of Egypt, and you shall say to him,
                            “The Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            God of the Hebrews has met with us. And now
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            let us go a three days’ journey in the wilderness and let us
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            offer a sacrifice to the Lord our God.”</l>
                        <l n="19">But I know that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            the king of Egypt will not empower you to go,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            and not by a mighty hand.</l>
                        <l n="20">And I will reach out my wrath,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and punish Egypt with all my wonders which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            I will do in the midst of it, and after that he will let you go.</l>
                        <l n="21">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="91r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            And I will put the favour of these people in Egypt’s eyes,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and it shall be that when you go, you will not go empty.</l>
                        <l n="22">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            And every woman shall take a loan from her neighbour, and of anyone who lives
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            in her house: silver vessels, and golden vessels, and clothing.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            And you will put them on your sons, and on your daughters,
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex003-P91r-L6_trl" n="6" next="ADub.III.73.002.004.trl.xml#Ex004-P91r-L6_trl" />
                            and you will plunder Egypt.’</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
