<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 28</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 28</title><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="1">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Isaac called Jacob, and blessed him and commanded him, and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>he said to him, ‘You shall not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan.</l><l n="2">Arise,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>go to Paddan-Aram, to the house of Bethuel, your mother’s father,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and take you a wife from there of the daughters of Laban, the brother<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of your mother.</l><l n="3">And may the mighty God bless you and spread<milestone unit="page" n="43v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>you and multiply you, that you may become a multitude of people.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="4">And may he give the blessing of Abraham to you<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and to your offspring with you, that you may inherit the land of your sojourning<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>that God gave to Abraham!’</l><l n="5">And Isaac<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>sent Jacob, and he went to Paddan-Aram to Laban, son<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of Bethuel, the Aramean, brother of Rebekah, mother of Jacob<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and Esau.</l><l n="6">And Esau saw that Isaac had blessed<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Jacob, and sent him to Paddan-Aram, to take him from there<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>a wife when he blessed him, and he had commanded him, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>‘You shall not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan.’</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And Jacob listened to the words of his father and his mother, and went<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to Paddan-Aram.</l><l n="8">And Esau saw that<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the daughters of Canaan seemed not good in the eyes of Isaac, his father.</l><l n="9"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And went Esau to Ishmael, and took Mahalath, daughter<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of Ishmael, son of Abraham, sister of Nebaioth,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>besides the wives whom he had, as a wife for him.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/><emph>Parashat Vayetze</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="10">And Jacob went out from<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Beersheba, and went toward Haran.</l><l n="11">And<milestone unit="page" n="44r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>he reached a place, and stayed the night there, because the sun had set. And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>he took one of the stones of that place, and he put it under his head,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and lay down in that place.</l><l n="12">And he dreamed.<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>And, lo: a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reaches<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>to heaven. And, lo, the angels of God ascend and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>descend on it.</l><l n="13">And, lo, the divine Presence<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of the Lord stands above it, and said, ‘I am the Lord God<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of Abraham your father, and the God of Isaac. The land on which<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>you are lying: I will give it to you and to your offspring.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="14">And your offspring will be like the dust of the earth,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and you will spread to the west, and to the east, and to the north,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and to the south. And in you will all the families<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of the earth be blessed.</l><l n="15">And, lo,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>my help is with you, and I will keep you everywhere<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>you go, and I will bring you back to this land. For I will not leave you,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>until I have done that which I have spoken<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>to you of.’</l><l n="16">And Jacob awoke from his sleep, and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>he said, ‘Surely, the divine Presence of Lord is in this place,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and I did not know.’ And he was afraid, and said, ‘How<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>awesome is this place! This is none other but the house<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of God, and this is the gate of heaven.’</l><l n="18">And<milestone unit="page" n="44v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Jacob rose up early in the morning, and took the stone<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>that he had put under his head, and set it up for a pillar, and poured<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>oil on the top of it.</l><l n="19">And he called the name of that<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>place Bethel, though in truth the name of that city was called Luz<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>at first.</l><l n="20">And Jacob vowed a vow, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>‘If God’s help will be with me and will keep<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>me in this way that I go and will give me bread<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to eat, and clothing to put on,</l><l n="21">And I come back<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to my father’s house in peace, then the Lord will become God to me.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="22">And this stone that I have set for a pillar will be<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>for God’s house, <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg014"/<anchor xml:id="del001"/>to compose my prayers and pay<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>my vows<delSpan spanTo="#del002"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg014"/<anchor xml:id="del002"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>, and of everything that you will give me<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>I will surely give the tenth to you.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 28:22.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
