<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Numbers 35</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Numbers 35</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-2-2" n="2" prev="ADub.III.73.004.034.trl.xml#line-2-1" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            to Moses in the steppes of Moab by the Jordan of Jericho, saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">‘Command the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of Israel that they give to the Levites of the share
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            of their possession cities to dwell in, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            you shall give to the Levites pasture lands for the cities all around
                            them.</l>
                        <l n="3">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the cities shall be theirs to dwell in, and their pasture lands shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            for their livestock and for their goods and for all their animals.</l>
                        <l n="4">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            And the pasture lands of the cities which you shall give to the Levites
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            |shall be| from the wall of the city and outward a thousand cubits all
                            around.</l>
                        <l n="5">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            And you shall measure from outside the city on the east side
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            two thousand cubits, and on the south side two thousand
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            cubits, and on the west side two thousand cubits,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and on the north side two thousand cubits, and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            city shall be in the middle. This shall be <addSpan spanTo="#add001"
                                 /><emph>to them</emph><anchor xml:id="add001" /> the pasture lands
                            of the cities.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="6">And the cities which you shall give to the Levites: six
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            cities of refuge that you shall give for the manslayer to flee there, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            you shall give in addition to them forty-two cities.</l>
                        <l n="7">All the cities which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            you shall give to the Levites: forty-eight cities, them and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            their pasture lands.</l>
                        <l n="8">And the cities which you shall give from the possession
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            of the children of Israel: from many you shall give many, and from few
                            <milestone unit="page" n="276r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            you shall give few. Every man shall give from his cities to the Levites
                            according to his share which he takes.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="9">And the Lord spoke to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="10">‘Speak to the children of Israel and say
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            to them, “When you cross the Jordan to the land of Canaan:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="11">And you shall build you cities: they shall be cities of refuge
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            for you, and a manslayer who murders a life mistakenly shall flee
                            there.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="12">And they shall be to you cities for refuge
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            from the avenger, that the manslayer may not die until he stands before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            the congregation for judgment.</l>
                        <l n="13">And of these cities which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            you shall give: you shall have six cities for refuge.</l>
                        <l n="14">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            You shall give three cities across the ford of Jordan, and three
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            cities you shall give in the land of Canaan. They shall be cities of
                            refuge.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="15">These six cities shall be a refuge for the children of Israel and
                            for the stranger and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            for the settler among them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            so that everyone that kills a life mistakenly may flee there.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="16">But if he strikes him with an iron item
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            so that he dies: he is a murderer.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            The murderer shall surely be put to death.</l>
                        <l n="17">And if he strikes him with a hand stone
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            by which one could die, and he dies: he is a murderer.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            The murderer shall surely be put to death.</l>
                        <l n="18">Or if he strikes him with a hand
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            weapon of wood, by which one could die, and he dies: he is a murderer.
                            <milestone unit="page" n="276v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            The murderer shall surely be put to death.</l>
                        <l n="19">The avenger
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            of blood himself shall kill the murderer. When he meets him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            he shall kill him.</l>
                        <l n="20">And if he
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            pushes him from enmity or hurls at him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            through hunting, and he dies,</l>
                        <l n="21">Or if in enmity
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            he strikes him with his hand, and he dies,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the one who struck him shall surely be put to death, he is a murderer:
                            the avenger of blood shall kill
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            the murderer, when he meets him.</l>
                        <l n="22">But if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            he pushed him suddenly without enmity or cast
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            on him any item without hunting,</l>
                        <l n="23">Or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            used any item by which one may die seeing him not, and dropped
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            it on him, and he dies, and he was not his enemy,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            and he did not want his harm,</l>
                        <l n="24">Then
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            the congregation shall judge between the one who struck
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            and the avenger of blood according to these judgments.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="25">And the congregation shall rescue the manslayer
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            from the hand of the avenger of blood, and the congregation shall
                            restore him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to the city of his refuge, where he had fled, and he shall live there
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            until the death of the high priest, whom one anointed with the holy
                            oil.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                        <l n="26">But if the manslayer shall indeed go beyond the border of the city
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            of his refuge, where he had fled,</l>
                        <l n="27">And the avenger of blood finds him
                            <milestone unit="page" n="277r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            outside the borders of the city of his refuge, and the avenger of blood murders
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            the manslayer, he shall not be guilty of blood.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="28">Because he shall live in the city of his refuge
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            until the death of the high priest, and after the death of the high priest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            the manslayer shall return to the land of his possession.</l>
                        <l n="29">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            these things shall be for a statute of judgment to you throughout your generations
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            in all your dwelling places.</l>
                        <l n="30">Anyone who kills a life,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            the murderer shall be murdered according to the word of witnesses.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            And one witness shall not testify against a person so as to die.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="31">And you shall take no ransom for the life of a murderer, because he
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            is guilty of death, but he shall be surely put to death.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="32">In the same way, you shall take no ransom from the one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            who has to fled to the city of his refuge, that he may return to live
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            in the land, until the death of the high priest.</l>
                        <l n="33">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            you shall not defile the land in which you are. Because blood:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            it defiles the land, and no atonement can be made for the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            for the blood that is shed in it except by the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of the one who shed it.</l>
                        <l n="34">Do not defile
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            the land in which you live, in the midst of which my divine Presence
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            dwells, for I, the Lord, my divine Presence
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            dwells among the children of Israel.”’
                            <milestone unit="page" n="277v" />
                        </l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
