<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 39</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 39</title><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="1">And Joseph was brought down to Egypt. And<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Potiphar, a vizier of Pharaoh, superior of the executioners,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>an Egyptian man, bought him from the hand of the Ishmaelites, who had brought him down<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>there.</l><l n="2">And the help of the Lord was with Joseph,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and he was man whom fate favoured in his deeds, and he was in the house<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of his lord, the Egyptian.</l><l n="3">And his lord saw<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>that the Lord’s help was with him, and all that he did:<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the Lord made it prosper in his hand.</l><l n="4">And Joseph found<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>favour in his eyes, and he served him.<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And he appointed him superior over his house,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and all put him in charge of everything that he had.</l><l n="5">And it was<milestone unit="page" n="64v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>from the time that he appointed him superior in his house, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>over all that he had |that| the Lord blessed the<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Egyptian’s house for Joseph’s sake, and the blessing<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of the Lord was on all that he had in the house, and in the field.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="6">And he left all that he had in Joseph’s hand,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and he did not know anything he had, except the<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>bread which he ate. And Joseph was a handsome in form and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>handsome in appearance.</l><l n="7">And it was after these things,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and his lord’s wife lifted her eyes on Joseph,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and she said, ‘Lie with me.’</l><l n="8">But<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>he did not want to, and said to his lord’s wife, ‘Lo, my lord does not know<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>what is with me in the house, and all that he has<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>he put in my charge.</l><l n="9">There is no superior in this house<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>except me, and he has not spared anything from me but you, because<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>you are his wife: how could I do this great wrong?<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>And would sin against God.’</l><l n="10">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>it was, when she spoke to Joseph every day, he did not listen to her,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to lie by her, to be with her.</l><l n="11">And it was<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>one day, and Joseph came to the house to do his work,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and there was none of the people of the house<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>there in the room.</l><l n="12">And the woman caught him<milestone unit="page" n="65r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>by his garment, saying, ‘Lie with me.’ And Josef left<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>his own garment in her hand, and fled, and went<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>outside.</l><l n="13">And it was, when she saw that<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>he had left his garment in her hand, and had fled outside,</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="14">That she called to the men of her house, and said<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>to them, saying, ‘See, he has brought in a Hebrew to us to<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>laugh at us. He came in to me to lie with me, and I cried with a loud<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>voice.</l><l n="15">And it was, when he heard that I lifted<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>up my voice and cried, that he left his garment<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>beside me, and fled, and went outside.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="16">And she laid up his garment by her, until his lord came<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>home.</l><l n="17">And she spoke to him according to these words,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>saying, ‘The Hebrew servant, which you have brought<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to us, came in to me to laugh at me.</l><l n="18">And it was, when I raised<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>my voice and cried, that he left his garment<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>beside me and fled outside.’</l><l n="19">And it was,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spoke to him,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>saying, ‘Your servant did matters like these to me’, that<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his anger was kindled.</l><l n="20">And Joseph’s lord took him, and put him in<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>prison, a place where the lord’s prisoners were imprisoned,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and he was there in the prison.</l><l n="21"><milestone unit="page" n="65v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>But the help of the Lord was with Joseph and showed him mercy,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and gave him favour in the eyes of the superior of the prison.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="22">And the superior of the prison put Joseph in charge of<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>all the prisoners that were in the prison.<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And whatever they did there, he was the one who did it.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="23">The superior of the prison did not look to anything<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>that was under his hand, but the help of the Lord was with him.<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And whatever he did, the Lord made it to prosper.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
