<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 5</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Deuteronomy 5</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="1">And Moses called all Israel and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            said to them, ‘Hear, oh Israel, the statutes
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and judgments which I speak in your ears
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            today. And you shall learn them and be watchful to do them.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="2">The Lord our God made a covenant with us
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            in Horeb.</l>
                        <l n="3">The Lord made this covenant not with our fathers,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            but with us. We, these,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            here, today — all of us are alive.</l>
                        <l n="4">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            The Lord talked with you mind to mind in the mountain from the midst
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of the fire.</l>
                        <l n="5">I was standing between the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            and you at that time to tell you the word
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            of the Lord because you were afraid before the fire, and did not go up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            in the mountain, when he wanted to say:</l>
                        <l n="6">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="289v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            “I am the Lord your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            from the reign of slaves.</l>
                        <l n="7">You shall not have other gods
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            before my power.</l>
                        <l n="8">You shall not make for yourself any carved
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            idol of any image that you would see in the skies above or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            that is in the earth beneath or that is in the water under the
                            earth.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="9">You shall not bow down to them, and you shall not serve them. Because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            I am the Lord your God, God that is jealous, remembering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            the iniquity of the fathers on the children wicked to the third
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            generation and fourth generation of my enemies.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="10">But I am the one who shows mercy to thousands of generations
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            that love reading my Law, and that keep
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            my commandments.</l>
                        <l n="11">You shall not swear to the name of the Lord your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            falsely, because the Lord will not make guiltless the one who
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            would swear to his name in vain.</l>
                        <l n="12">Keep
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the Sabbath day, to keep it holy, as the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            Lord your God commanded you.</l>
                        <l n="13">Six days
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            you shall labour and do all your work,</l>
                        <l n="14">And the seventh
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            day is the Sabbath for the praise of the Lord your God: you shall not do
                            any work:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            you and your son and your daughter and your servant and your
                            maidservant, and your cattle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and your donkey and your livestock, and your stranger that is within
                            your cities —
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            in order that your manservant and your maidservant may rest like
                            you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="290r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="15">And remember that you were a servant in the land of Egypt,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and that the Lord your God brought you out from there with a strong hand
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            and with an outstretched arm. On account of this the Lord your God
                            commanded you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            to keep the Sabbath day.</l>
                        <l n="16">Honour
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            your father and your mother, as the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            Lord your God has commanded you, so that your days may be prolonged, and
                            so that it may be good for you on the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            which the Lord your God gives you.</l>
                        <lg n="17">
                            <l n="17">
                                <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                                You shall not murder.</l>
                            <l n="18">And you shall not commit adultery.</l>
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            <l n="19">And you shall not steal.</l>
                            <l n="20">And you shall not testify against
                                <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                                your fellow to be false witness.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <l n="21">And you shall not desire your fellow’s wife, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            you shall desire your fellow’s house, his field, or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            his servant or his maidservant, or his cattle or his donkey,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            or anything that is your fellow’s.”</l>
                        <l n="22">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            These words the Lord spoke to all your assembly
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            at the mountain from the midst of the fire, the cloud and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            the fog, with a great voice. And he did not add. And he wrote
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            them on two tablets of stone and gave them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to me.</l>
                        <l n="23">And it was, when you heard the voice
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            from the midst of the darkness, and the mountain was burning in fire,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            that you came near to me, all the superiors of your tribes, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            your elders.</l>
                        <l n="24">And you said, “Lo, the Lord our God has showed
                            <milestone unit="page" n="290v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            from the midst of the fire. We have seen this day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            that God does talk with man, and he lives.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="25">And now why should we die? Because this great fire will consume us.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            If we go on hearing
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            the voice of the Lord our God any more, then we will die.</l>
                        <l n="26">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            Because who, |of| all flesh, is there who has heard the voice of the
                            mighty God speaking
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            from the midst of the fire as we have and lived?</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="27">Go near and hear all that the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            Lord our God will say, and speak to us
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            all that the Lord our God shall will speak to you, and we will listen
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            and we will do |it|.”</l>
                        <l n="28">And the Lord heard the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            voice of your words when you were speaking to me, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            the Lord said to me, “I have heard the voice of the words of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            this people that they have spoken to you. They have well said |all| that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            they have spoken.</l>
                        <l n="29">Oh, who would set it so that they would have
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            this thought, to fear me and keep all my
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            commandments for all their days, so that it may be good
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            for them and for their children forever!</l>
                        <l n="30">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            Go, say to them, “Return to your tents.””</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="31">And he said to me, “And you, stand here with me so
                            <milestone unit="page" n="291r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            I may speak to you all the commandments and the statutes
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and the judgments which you shall teach them, that they shall do
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            |them| in the land which I am giving them to inherit it.”</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="32">And you shall be watchful to do them as the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            your God has commanded you. You shall not turn to the right or to the
                            left.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="33">You shall walk in all the ways which the Lord your God has
                            commanded you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            and because of that you will live, and it will be good for you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and you will prolong your days in the land which you shall inherit.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
