<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Numbers 14</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Numbers 14</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="1">And all the congregation raised and let out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            their voices, and the people wept that night.</l>
                        <l n="2">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            And all the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and the whole congregation said to them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            ‘If only we had died in the land of Egypt! Or in this wilderness,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            if only we had died!</l>
                        <l n="3">And why is the Lord bringing us
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            to this land, to fall by the sword? Our wives and our infants
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            will become a prey! Isn’t it better for us to return
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            to Egypt?’</l>
                        <l n="4">And they said one to another, ‘Let’s give
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            us choose a superior, and let us return to Egypt.’</l>
                        <l n="5">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            Moses and Aaron fell on their faces before all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            the assembly of the congregation of the children of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="6">And Joshua,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            son of Nun, and Caleb, son of Jephunneh — those who spied the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            land — tore their clothes.</l>
                        <l n="7">And they spoke to all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, ‘The land, which we passed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to spy it: that land is very, very good.</l>
                        <l n="8">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            Only if the Lords loves us, then he will bring us
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            to this land and give it to us, a land flowing |with| milk
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            and honey.</l>
                        <l n="9">Just do not betray the Lord. And you, do not fear
                            <milestone unit="page" n="235r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            the people of the land, because they are bread for us:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            their shadow is departed from over them, but the Lord’s help is with us.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            Do not fear them.’</l>
                        <l n="10">And all the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            congregation said to stone them with stones. And the divine Presence of
                            the Lord appeared
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            in the tent of meeting to all the children of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="11">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            the Lord said to Moses, ‘How long will this people make me angry?
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            And how long will they not believe me, with all the signs
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            which I have done among them?</l>
                        <l n="12">I will smite them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            with the pestilence, and I will destroy them, and I will make you into a great
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and more powerful kingdom than they.’</l>
                        <l n="13">And Moses said
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            to the Lord, ‘And if the Egyptians hear it, because you brought
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            this people out from among them with your power:</l>
                        <l n="14">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            they will tell it to the inhabitants of this land. They have heard
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            that you, Lord, are among this people, that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            your divine Presence has appeared mind to mind, and that your cloud
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            stands over them, and that you go before them in a pillar of a cloud
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            by daytime and in a pillar of fire
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            by night.</l>
                        <l n="15">And if you kill this people
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            as one man, then the kingdoms which have heard the <supplied
                                reason="lost">hearsay</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"
                             /> of you will speak,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="16">“Because of the lack of the Lord’s power to bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            this people to the land which he swore
                            <milestone unit="page" n="235v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            to give to them, he has slain them in the wilderness.”</l>
                        <l n="17">And now,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            let the power of my Lord be great, according as you have spoken,
                            saying,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="18">“The Lord is slow to anger and abundant in kindness, forgiving
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            iniquity and transgression, and he is surely not making anyone innocent:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            reckoning fathers’ iniquity on evil children to the third
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            generation and fourth generation.”</l>
                        <l n="19">Forgive
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            now, I pray you, the iniquity of this people according to the greatness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            of your mercy, and as you have forgiven the iniquity of this people
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            from the time they left Egypt even until now.’</l>
                        <l n="20">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            And the Lord said, ‘I have forgiven their iniquity according to your
                            word.</l>
                        <l n="21">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            But truly, I am eternal. And as my glory is filling
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            all the earth,</l>
                        <l n="22">So will my word be eternal, because all those men
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            who have seen my glory and my signs
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            that I did in Egypt and in the wilderness, and who have tested me these ten
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            times and have not listened to my voice:</l>
                        <l n="23">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            <seg type="commented" n="#seg001" /><supplied reason="lost">They will
                                not see</supplied><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001" /><ref
                                target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor" /> the land which I swore to their fathers,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            all those that make me angry will not see it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="24">And my servant Caleb: because he had another though
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            with him and walked after my order,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            I will bring him to the land where he went, and he will
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            inherit it to his seed.</l>
                        <l n="25">And the Amalekites
                            <milestone unit="page" n="236r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            and the Canaanites are dwelling in the valley. Turn at daybreak
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and get you to the wilderness by the way of the Red sea.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="26">And the Lord spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="27">‘How long shall I endure with this evil congregation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            which murmurs against me?
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel, which they murmur
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            against me.</l>
                        <l n="28">Say to them:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            “I am eternal — so said the Lord — in no other way but as you have spoken
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            in my ears, so will I do to you.</l>
                        <l n="29">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            Your carcasses shall fall in this wilderness; and all those numbered of you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            according to your whole number, from twenty years old and upward,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            because you have murmured against me:</l>
                        <l n="30">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            <seg type="commented" n="#seg002" /><supplied reason="lost">You will not
                                come</supplied><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg002" /><ref
                                target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor" /> to the land which I swore by my hand
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            to make you dwell therein, except Caleb, son of Jephunneh, and Joshua,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            son of Nun.</l>
                        <l n="31">But your little ones, whom you said would become a prey:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            I will bring them, and they shall know the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            which you have despised.</l>
                        <l n="32">But your carcasses:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            they shall fall in this wilderness.</l>
                        <l n="33">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            And your children shall walk from place to place in the wilderness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            forty years, like shepherds who do not dwell in one place,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            and bear the punishment of your wrongs until the end
                            <milestone unit="page" n="236v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            of your carcasses in the wilderness.</l>
                        <l n="34">After the number of the days
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            that you spied the land, forty days, a day for a year, a day for a year
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            you will <supplied reason="lost">carry</supplied> the punishment of your
                            iniquities, forty years, and you will know
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            my reprimand.</l>
                        <l n="35">I, the Lord, have spoken,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            I will do this — no other thing — to all this evil congregation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            gathered before me: they shall end in this wilderness, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            they shall die there.”’</l>
                        <l n="36">And the men whom Moses sent
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            to spy the land and returned and made
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            all the congregation to murmur against him in order to bring up a
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            slander on the land:</l>
                        <l n="37">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the men that brought up an evil slander on the land died by the plague
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="38">But Joshua, son
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            of Nun, and Caleb, son of Jephunneh stayed alive out of those men
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            who went to spy the land.</l>
                        <l n="39">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            And Moses told these words to all the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            of Israel, and the people mourned greatly.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="40">And they rose up early at dawn, and went up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to the top of the mountain, saying, ‘Lo, we are here, and we will go up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            to the place which the Lord has said, because we have sinned.’</l>
                        <l n="41">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            And Moses said, ‘Why is this that you transgress the command of the Lord?
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            But this thought will not prosper.</l>
                        <l n="42">Do not go up — because
                            <milestone unit="page" n="237r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            the Lord’s help is not among you — so you will not die before your
                            enemies.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="43">Because the Amalekites and the Canaanites are there
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            before you, and you shall fall by the sword, because you have turned aside
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            from the order of the Lord, and the Lord’s help will not be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            with you.’</l>
                        <l n="44">But they were proud to go up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            to the top of the mountain. And the ark, the covenant of the Lord, and Moses
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            set out from the camp.</l>
                        <l n="45">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            then the Amalekites came down, and the Canaanites who dwelt in that mountain,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and slew them, and beat them, as far as the
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-10-1" n="10" next="ADub.III.73.004.015.trl.xml#line-10-2" />
                            place called Hormah.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: <emph>hearing</emph>; a mistranslation
                            based on the confusion of BHeb. <foreign xml:lang="he"
                                style="unicode-bidi: embed;">שֵׁמַע </foreign>
                            ‘hearsay’ (Num 14:15) with Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he"
                                style="unicode-bidi: embed;">שֵׁמַע </foreign>
                            ‘hearing’. Repeated in H, and R. Translated correctly in C, M, and
                            E.</note>
                        <note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">K: <emph>if they see</emph>; a
                            mistranslation repeated in a number of manuscripts resulting from
                            literal translation of the Hebrew conditional clause, cf. Gen 14:23, Num
                            14:30, Num 32:11, Deu 1:35. | TKow.01: <emph>if they see</emph>. | H:
                                <emph>if they see</emph>. | C: <emph>if they see</emph>. | M:
                                <emph>if they see</emph>. | E: <emph>if they see</emph>. | R:
                                <emph>if they see</emph>.</note>
                        <note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">K: <emph>if you come</emph>; a
                            mistranslation repeated in a number of manuscripts resulting from
                            literal translation of the Hebrew conditional clause, cf. Gen 14:23, Num
                            14:23, Num 32:11, Deu 1:35. | TKow.01: <emph>if you come</emph>. | H:
                                <emph>if you come</emph>. | C: <emph>if you come</emph>. | M:
                                <emph>if you come</emph>. | E: <emph>if you come</emph>. | R:
                                <emph>if you come</emph>.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
