<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Exodus 9</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Exodus 9</title><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l>And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Come to Pharaoh,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and speak to him, saying, “Thus says the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>God of the Hebrews, “Let my people go, so<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>may they serve me.</l><l n="2">Because if you are not willing<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>to let go and you are still holding them strongly,</l><l n="3">Lo,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the wrath of the Lord will be on your livestock that are in the field, on the horses,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>on the donkeys, on the camels, on the cattle, and on the sheep: a very severe pestilence.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="4">And the Lord will separate between the livestock<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of Israel and the livestock of Egypt. And nothing will die of all<milestone unit="page" n="99v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>that is of the children of Israel.””’</l><l n="5">And the Lord has set<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>an appointed time, saying, ‘At daybreak the Lord will do this thing<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>in the land.’</l><l n="6">And the Lord did that<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>thing after daybreak, and all the livestock of Egypt died,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>but of the livestock of Israel not one died.</l><l n="7">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Pharaoh sent, and, lo, there was not one of the livestock of Israel dead.<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the people go.</l><l n="8">And the Lord said to Moses<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and to Aaron, ‘Take to you handfuls<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of lime kiln soot, and Moses shall sprinkle it toward the skies<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>in the sight of Pharaoh.</l><l n="9">And it shall become fine dust<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>over all the land of Egypt, and shall become<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>boils spreading with abscesses on man and on livestock,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>all over the land of Egypt.’</l><l n="10">So they took<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>soot of the lime kiln, and stood before<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>Pharaoh. And Moses sprinkled it up toward heaven, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>it became boils spreading with abscesses on man, |and| on livestock.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="11">And the magicians could not stand before<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Moses by reason of the boils, for the boils were on the<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>magicians, and on all Egypt.</l><l n="12">And the Lord hardened<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the heart of Pharaoh, and he did not listen to them — as<milestone unit="page" n="100r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the Lord had spoken to Moses.</l><l n="13">And the Lord said to Moses,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘Rise up early in the morning, stand before Pharaoh, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>say to him, “Thus said the Lord God of the Hebrews, “Let<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>my people go, so that they may serve me.</l><l n="14">Because<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>this time I will send all my punishments at your heart, and at your servants,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and at your people, so that you may know that there is none like me in all<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>the earth.</l><l n="15">Because by now I could have reached out my wrath,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and smite you and your people with pestilence, and you would have been<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>cut off from the earth.</l><l n="16">And, of a truth, for this reason<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>I have raised you up: to show you my power, so<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>that my name may be declared in all the earth.</l><l n="17">If you are still<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>exalting yourself against my people not to let them go:</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="18">Lo, at this time at daybreak I will cause very strong hail to fall,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>such as never has been in Egypt from the day it was founded<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>until now.</l><l n="19">And now send, gather<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>your livestock and all that you have in the field. All the<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>men and livestock that shall be found in the field and is not gathered<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>home: the hail will come down on them, and they will die.””’</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="20">The one who feared the word of the Lord among the servants of Pharaoh<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>made his servants and his livestock flee to the houses.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="21">And the one who did not pay attention to the word of the Lord<milestone unit="page" n="100v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>left his servants and his livestock in the field.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="22">And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Reach out your hand<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>toward the skies, so that there may be hail in all the land of Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>on man, and on livestock, and on every plant<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of the field in the land of Egypt.’</l><l n="23">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Moses reached out his staff toward the skies, and the Lord gave thunder<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and hail, and sparked fire ran on the ground, and the Lord rained hail<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>on the land of Egypt.</l><l n="24">And there was hail, and fire was sparking<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>in the midst of hail, very strong, such as there was none<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>like it in all the land of Egypt since it became a kingdom.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="25">And the hail smote in all the land of Egypt all<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>that was in the field, both man and animal, and the hail smote<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>all the plants of the field and broke every tree of the field.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="26">Only in the land of Goshen, where<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the children of Israel were, was there no hail.</l><l n="27">And Pharaoh sent,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and called for Moses and Aaron, and said to them, ‘I sinned<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>this time. The Lord is righteous, and I and my people<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>are wicked.</l><l n="28">Pray to the Lord, and may it be enough of<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>mighty thundering and hail, and let me let you go, and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>you shall not continue to stay.’</l><l n="29">And Moses said to him, ‘As I go<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>out of the city, I will reach out my hands before the Lord. The<milestone unit="page" n="101r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>thunder will cease, and there will be no more hail, so that you may<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>know that, indeed, the earth is in the Lord’s hand.</l><l n="30">And you<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and your servants: <seg type="commented" corresp="#seg001"/>I know that until this punishment leaves, you will fear<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>before the Lord God<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>.</l><l n="31">And the flax<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and the barley was smitten, because the barley was in the ear, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the flax was in blades.</l><l n="32">But the wheat<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and the rye were not smitten, because they were covered.’</l><l n="33"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And Moses went out of the city from before Pharaoh, and spread<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>his hands to the Lord, and the thunders and the<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>hail ceased, and the rain was not poured on the earth.</l><l n="34">And Pharaoh saw<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>that the rain and the hail and the thunders were ceased,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and he sinned yet again, and hardened his heart, he and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>his servants.</l><l n="35">And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the children of Israel go — as the Lord had spoken through the<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>prophecy of Moses.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative translation.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
