<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Numbers 18</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Numbers 18</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-6-2" n="6" prev="ADub.III.73.004.017.trl.xml#line-6-1" />
                        <l n="1">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the Lord said to Aaron, ‘You and your sons and your father’s house
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            with you shall bear the punishment of the iniquity of the sanctuary,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and you and your sons with you shall bear the punishment
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            of the iniquity of your priesthood.</l>
                        <l n="2">And bring forward your brothers,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the tribe of Levi, the tribe of your father, with you as well,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            and they shall be joined to you and minister to you, and you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            and your sons with you |shall minister| before the tent of law.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="3">And they shall keep your charge and the charge of all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the tent, but they shall not come near the vessels of the Holy and the altar,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            so they will not die, both they and you.</l>
                        <l n="4">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            And they shall be joined to you and keep the charge of the tent
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of meeting, for all the service of the tent, and an outsider shall not
                            come near
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            to you.</l>
                        <l n="5">And you shall keep the charge of the Holy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and the charge of the altar, so there will not be anger any more
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            on the children of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="6">And I, lo, I have taken
                            <milestone unit="page" n="243v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            your brothers, the Levites, from among the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            of Israel, to give them as a gift to you for the Lord, to do the service
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            in the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="7">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            you and your sons with you shall keep your priesthood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            for everything at the altar, and within the veil, and you shall
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            serve: I have given your priesthood to you as a gift for service. And the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            outsider that comes near shall be put to death.’</l>
                        <l n="8">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            the Lord spoke to Aaron, ‘And I, lo, have given you the charge
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of my heave offerings of all the holies of the children of Israel.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            I have given them to you as an anointing, and to your sons, as an eternal
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            statute.</l>
                        <l n="9">This shall be yours of the holy of holies,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            from the fire: every offering of theirs, every grain offering of theirs,
                            and every
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            sin offering of theirs, and every guilt offering of theirs, which they
                            shall pay back to me.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            It is holy of holies for you and for your sons.</l>
                        <l n="10">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            In the holy of holies you shall eat it. Every male shall eat it.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            It shall be holy to you.</l>
                        <l n="11">And this is yours: the heave offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            of their gifts, with all the wave offerings of the children of Israel.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            I have given them to you and to your sons and to your daughters with you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            as an eternal statute. Everyone who is clean in your house shall eat
                            it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                        <l n="12">All the oil of the olive oil, and all the oil of the must and of
                            the grain,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            the firstfruits of them which they shall give to the Lord, I have given
                            <milestone unit="page" n="244r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            them to you.</l>
                        <l n="13">And the firstfruits of all that is in their land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            which they will bring to the Lord, shall be yours. Everyone who is clean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            in your house shall eat it.</l>
                        <l n="14">Everything devoted in Israel
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            shall be yours.</l>
                        <l n="15">Every opening of the womb of all flesh
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            which they bring forward to the Lord, both among men <addSpan
                                spanTo="#add001" /><emph>and</emph><anchor xml:id="add001" />
                            animals, shall be yours.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            Just: you shall surely redeem the firstborn of man, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            you shall redeem the firstborn of unclean animals.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="16">And those that are to be redeemed from a month old you shall redeem
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            according to your valuation, five mithqals of silver according to the
                            mithqal of the Holy:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            it is twenty <emph>gög</emph>s.</l>
                        <l n="17">Just: you shall not redeem the firstborn
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            of a cattle or the firstborn of a sheep or the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            firstborn of a goat. They are holy.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            You shall sprinkle their blood on the altar, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            you shall burn their fat for an offering by fire, an aroma of acceptance
                            to the Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="18">And their meat shall be yours, like the breast
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            of the wave offering and like the right thigh it shall be yours.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="19">All the heave offerings of the holy things which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            the children of Israel devote to the Lord I have given to you and to
                            your sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            and to your daughters with you, an eternal statute:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            it is a covenant made forever before the Lord to you and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            to your offspring with you.’</l>
                        <l n="20">And the Lord said to Aaron,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="244v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            ‘You shall take no portion in their land, and there shall be no share
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            for you among them. I am your portion and your share
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            among the children of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="21">And to the children of Levi,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            lo, I have given every tenth in Israel for a portion, a reward for their service
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            which they serve, the service of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="22">And the children of Israel shall not come near
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the tent of meeting anymore, so as to bear the punishment of sin and
                            die.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="23">But the Levites shall do the service
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of the tent of meeting, and they shall bear the punishment of their iniquity,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            it is an eternal statute throughout your generations. And they shall not
                            take a part among the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            of Israel:</l>
                        <l n="24">Because I have given to <supplied reason="lost">the
                                Levites</supplied> the tithes of the children of Israel which they
                            dedicated as a heave offering to the Lord as a portion. On account of
                            this I have said to them: they shall take no portion among the children
                            of Israel.’</l>
                        <l n="25">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="26">‘And speak
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            to the Levites and say to them, “When you take from the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of Israel the tithes which I have given you from them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            for your portion, then you shall dedicate of it a heave offering of the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            a tithe of the tithe.</l>
                        <l n="27">And your heave offering shall be reckoned to you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            like grain from the threshing-floor and like wine from the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            wine press.</l>
                        <l n="28">Thus you also shall dedicate, you too, a heave offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of the Lord of all your tithes which you take from the children of Israel.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            And you shall give the Lord’s heave offering from it to Aaron,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            the priest.</l>
                        <l n="29">From all your gifts you shall separate
                            <milestone unit="page" n="245r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            every heave offering of the Lord, from all of the oil of its holier
                            part.”</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="30">And you shall say to them, “When you have separated its oil
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            from it, then it shall be reckoned to the Levites like the crop
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of the threshing-floor and like the crop of the wine press.</l>
                        <l n="31">And you shall eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            it in every place, you and your households, for it is a reward
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            for you, a reward for your service in the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="32">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            you shall bear no punishment for a sin when you have separated
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            from it the oil of it. And you shall not defile the holy things of the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of Israel, and you will not die.”’</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
