<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Deuteronomy 4</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Deuteronomy 4</title><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="1">And now, oh Israel, listen to the statutes<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and to the judgments, which I teach you to do them, so that<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>you may live, and you may come and inherit<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the land which the Lord God of your fathers is giving you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="2">You shall not add to the word which I command<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>you, and you shall not take away from it, in order to keep the commandments<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of the Lord your God which I command you.</l><l n="3">It is your eyes<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>that saw what the Lord did at Baal-Peor<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and that every men who went after Baal-Peor:<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the Lord your God has destroyed them from among you.</l><l n="4">But you<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>who were clinging to the Lord your God: you are alive,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>every one of you, today.</l><l n="5">Look: I have taught you statutes<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and judgments as the Lord my God commanded me,<milestone unit="page" n="286r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>that you should do so within the land to which you are coming<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to inherit it.</l><l n="6">Keep therefore and do them, for this is<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>your wisdom and your reason in the sight of the peoples which<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>shall hear all these statutes and will say,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>“Only a wise and rational people is this great kingdom.”</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Because who is a great kingdom that has the Providence of God so near<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to them, as the Lord our God is, in all times of our calling<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to him?</l><l n="8">And who is a great kingdom that has statutes<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and judgments so righteous as all this Law, which I set<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>before you this day?</l><l n="9">Only take heed to yourself<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and watch your soul very much, lest you forget the<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>things that your eyes have seen, and lest they depart<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>from your reason, all the days of your life. But make them known to your sons,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and to your sons’ sons.</l><l n="10">The day that you stood<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>before the Lord your God in Horeb, when the Lord said<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to me, “Gather the people to me, and I will make them hear<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>my words, that they may learn<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to fear me all the days that they shall live<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>on the earth, and that they may teach their children.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="11">And you came near and stood at the foot of the mountain,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and the mountain burned with fire to the midst of heaven:<milestone unit="page" n="286v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>darkness, clouds, and fog.</l><l n="12">And the Lord spoke<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to you from the midst of the fire: You heard the voice of the words,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>but you saw no form, just sound.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="13">And he told you his covenant,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>which he commanded you to do, the ten commandments, and he wrote<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>them on two tablets of stone.</l><l n="14"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the Lord commanded me at that time to teach you<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>statutes and judgments, for you to do them in the land<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to which you are crossing to inherit it.</l><l n="15"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And take good heed to your souls — because you did not see<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>any image on the day that the Lord spoke to you in Horeb<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>from the midst of the fire —</l><l n="16">Lest you corrupt your ways<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and make you a carved idol, a form<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of any image, a form of male or<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>female,</l><l n="17">A form of any animal that<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>is on the earth, a form of any winged bird that flies<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>in the skies,</l><l n="18">A form of anything that creeps<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>on the ground, a form of any fish that is in the waters<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>beneath the earth,</l><l n="19">And lest you lift up<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>your eyes to heaven and you see the sun<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and the moon and the stars, all the host<milestone unit="page" n="287r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of heaven, and you go astray to worship them and serve<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>them, because the Lord your God has apportioned them to all peoples<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>under all the skies.</l><l n="20">But<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the Lord has taken you, and he brought you out from the iron furnace,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>from Egypt, to be to him a people of share, as it is this day.</l><l n="21"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And the Lord was angry with me because of you, and he<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>swore that I should not cross the Jordan, and that I should come<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to that good land, which the Lord your God gives you for a share.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="22">Because I will die in this land. I will not cross<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Jordan. But you are crossing, and you will inherit that good<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>land.</l><l n="23">Take heed to yourselves, lest<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>you will forget the covenant of the Lord your God that he made<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>with you and you will make a carved idol for yourself, of any<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>image, which the Lord your God has commanded you not to do,</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="24">Because the Lord your God: he is like consuming fire, he is a jealous<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>God.</l><l n="25">Because if you beget children and children’s children<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and grow old in the land, and if you corrupt your ways<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and make a carven idol, a form of anything,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and if you do what is evil in the sight of the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>your God, to make him angry,</l><l n="26">I will call<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>heaven and earth to witness against you today,<milestone unit="page" n="287v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>that you will utterly perish from off the land to which you<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>you are crossing the Jordan to inherit it. You will not prolong<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>your days on earth, but you will be utterly destroyed.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="27">And the Lord will scatter you among the peoples, and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>you will be left few in number among the kingdoms where the Lord will lead you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="28">And there you will serve those who serve<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>gods, the work of human hands, of wood and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>stone, that do not see or hear or eat<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>or smell.</l><l n="29">But if from there you will beseech<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>the Lord your God, you will find his wishes,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>if you beseech him with all your heart and with all your soul,</l><l n="30"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And if all these words come on you when you are in tribulation,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>in the latter days, and<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>if you return with repentance as far as to the Lord your God and obey his voice,</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="31">Because the Lord your God is a merciful God, he will not leave<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>you and he will not destroy you and he will not forget the<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>covenant of your fathers which he swore to them.</l><l n="32">Because ask,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>now, of the first days that were before you, from the<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>day that God created man on the earth, and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>from the one edge of the skies to the edge of the skies: has there been<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>|anything| like this great thing? Or has |anything| like it been heard?</l><milestone unit="page" n="288r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="33">Did ever people hear the voice of God<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>speaking from the midst of the fire the way you have heard —<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and lived?</l><l n="34">Or has God ever been used to<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>going and taking him a kingdom from the midst of another kingdoms<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>with trials, with signs, and with tokens, and with war,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and with a strong hand, and with an outstretched arm, and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>with great fears, like all that the Lord your God did for you<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>in Egypt in your sight?</l><l n="35">You have been shown<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>in order to know that the Lord: he is the God. There is no other<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>besides him.</l><l n="36">From the skies he had you hear<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>his voice in order to discipline you, and on the earth<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>he showed you his great fire, and you heard his words<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>from the midst of the fire.</l><l n="37">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>because he loved your fathers, he chose<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>their offspring after them, and brought you out<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>from great Egypt with his Providence,</l><l n="38">To destroy<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>nations from before you greater and mightier than you are, to bring you in,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to give you their land for a share,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>as it is this day.</l><l n="39">Know therefore today, and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>repeat it in your mind, that the Lord: he is the God in the skies above<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and on the earth beneath: there is none else.</l><l n="40"><milestone unit="page" n="288v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And you shall keep therefore his statutes and his commandments<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>which I command you today, so it will be good for you<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and to your children after you, and that you may prolong<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>your days on the earth, which the Lord your God gives you,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>for all the days.’</l><l n="41">Then Moses set apart<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>three cities at the ford of Jordan toward the sun’s rising,</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="42">That the manslayer might flee there, the one who would murder his neighbour<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>without knowing — and he was not his enemy<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>for long; and he shall flee to one of these cities<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and he shall live:</l><l n="43">Bezer<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>in the wilderness, in the plain country, of the tribe of Reuben,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and Ramoth in Gilead, of the tribe of Gad,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and Golan in Bashan, of the tribe of Manasseh.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="44">And this is the Law which Moses set<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>before the children of Israel.</l><l n="45">These are the<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>laws <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>and</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> the statutes and the judgments which Moses spoke<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>to the children of Israel, after they came out from the land<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of Egypt,</l><l n="46">At the ford of Jordan, <seg type="commented" corresp="#seg001"/>in<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>a place called <emph>Gay</emph><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> opposite Beth-Peor,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>in the land of Sihon of the king of the Amorites who dwelt<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>at Heshbon, whom Moses and the children of Israel defeated,<milestone unit="page" n="289r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>after they come out from the land of Egypt.</l><l n="47">And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>they inherited his land, and the land of Og, king<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>of Bashan, the two kings of the Amorites, who were at the ford<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of Jordan toward the sun’s shining,</l><l n="48">From<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Aroer, which is by the bank of the river Arnon, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>as far as to Mount Sion, that is Hermon,</l><l n="49">And all the<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>steppe, |from| the ford of Jordan eastward, and as far as to the sea<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of the steppe below the riverbeds <seg type="commented" corresp="#seg002"/>of the summit<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg002"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/>.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">A mistranslation based on interpreting Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">בַּגַּיְא </foreign>‘in the valley’ as a place name.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">A literal translation of Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">הַפִּסְגָּה </foreign>‘of Pisgah’. | TKow.01: <emph>of the summit</emph>. | H: <emph>of the summit</emph>. | C: <emph>of the rock</emph>. | R: <emph>of the rock</emph>.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
