<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 25</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 25</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l><emph>Parashat Behar</emph></l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            to Moses on Mount Sinai, saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            ‘Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them, “When you come
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            to the land which I give you, then the land shall keep a Sabbath
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            for the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="3">Six years you shall sow your field,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            and six years you shall prune your vineyard, and you shall gather its
                            produce.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="4">And in the seventh year shall be a Sabbath of complete rest to the land,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            a Sabbath for the Lord: you shall not sow your field and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            you shall not prune your vineyard.</l>
                        <l n="5">That which grows of its own accord of your harvest you shall not reap,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and you shall not gather the dispersed grapes. It shall be a year of
                            complete rest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to the land.</l>
                        <l n="6">And the Sabbath of the land shall be for food for you:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            for you and for your servants and maidservants and for your hired man
                            and for your settler that
                            <milestone unit="page" n="200v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            lives with you,</l>
                        <l n="7">And for your livestock, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            for the wild animals that are in your land shall be all its produce to
                            eat.</l>
                        <l n="8">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            you shall count seven Sabbaths of years for you: seven times seven years.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            And the days of the seven Sabbaths of years will be for you forty-nine
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            years.</l>
                        <l n="9">And you shall have the calling voice of the trumpet pass
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month: on the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            day of atonement you shall have the voice of the trumpet pass through
                            all your land.</l>
                        <l n="10">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            And you shall hallow the year of the fiftieth year and proclaim
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            liberty in the land to all the inhabitants thereof. It is a jubilee, it
                            shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            liberty for you. And you shall return every man to his possession, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            you shall return, every man to his family.</l>
                        <l n="11">The year of the fiftieth year is a jubilee,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            it shall be for you. You shall not sow, you shall not reap that which
                            grows of itself
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            in it and you shall not gather what is dispersed of it.</l>
                        <l n="12">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            Because it is a year of jubilee. It shall be holy to you. You shall eat
                            from the field.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            its produce.</l>
                        <l n="13">In the year of this jubilee you shall return every
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            man to his possession.</l>
                        <l n="14">And if you sell anything
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            to your fellow or buy anything of your fellow’s hand,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            you shall not torment one his brother.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="15">You shall buy from your fellow by the number of years after the jubilee,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            by the number of years of crops he shall sell to you:</l>
                        <l n="16">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            According to the multitude of years you shall increase its selling price,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="201r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            and according to the fewness of years you shall diminish the selling
                            price of it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            because according to the number of crops he sells to you.</l>
                        <l n="17">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            You shall not torment one another, but you shall fear your God, because
                            I am
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the Lord your God.</l>
                        <l n="18">And you shall do my statutes
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and keep my judgments and do them, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            then you will dwell in the land securely.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="19">And the land will give its fruit, and you will eat to the full, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            you will dwell on it securely.</l>
                        <l n="20">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            if you shall say, “What shall we eat, if in the seventh year we may not sow
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            or gather in our produce?”</l>
                        <l n="21">Then I will command
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            my blessing on you in the sixth year, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            it will make grow the produce for three years.</l>
                        <l n="22">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            you will sow the eighth year and eat the old produce
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            until the ninth year: you will eat the old |produce| until its produce
                            arrives to you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="23">The land shall not be sold <supplied reason="lost"
                                >†forever</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor" />, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            the land is mine, because you are strangers and settlers with me.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="24">And in all the land of your possession you shall give a redemption
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            for the land.</l>
                        <l n="25">If your brother becomes poor and sells any of his possession,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            then his closest relative shall come and shall redeem
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            his brother’s sale.</l>
                        <l n="26">And a man who has no
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            relative, but his hand can attain it and he finds enough for his
                            redemption:</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="201v" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="27">Then let him count the years of his sale and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            restore what has increased to the man to whom he sold it, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            he shall return to his possession.</l>
                        <l n="28">And if his hand has not found
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            enough to restore it to him, his sale shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            in the hand of the one who bought it until the year of jubilee, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            it shall come out in the jubilee, and he shall return to his
                            possession.</l>
                        <l n="29">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            And a man who sells a dwelling house in a walled city:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            its redemption shall be until the end of the year of its sale — there
                            shall be a year
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            for its redemption.</l>
                        <l n="30">And if it is not redeemed by the completion of a
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            full year, then the house that is in the walled city shall be established
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            <supplied reason="lost">†forever</supplied> to the one who bought it
                            throughout his generations. It shall not come out even in the
                            jubilee.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="31">And the houses of the homesteads which have no wall
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            around them shall be counted as the fields of the country. It shall
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            have redemption, and it shall come out in the jubilee.</l>
                        <l n="32">And the cities of the Levites,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the houses of the cities of their possession: the Levites shall have
                            eternal redemption.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="33">And if one of the Levites redeems: then it comes out, a sale
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            of a house or a city of his possession, in the jubilee, because the
                            houses of the cities
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of the Levites are their possession among the sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="34">But the field of pastureland of their cities
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            shall not be sold, for it is their eternal possession.</l>
                        <l n="35">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            if your brother becomes poor and his hand slips with you, then
                            <milestone unit="page" n="202r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            you shall strengthen him — a stranger or a setter — and he shall live
                            with you.</l>
                        <l n="36">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            Do not take interest or profit from him, but you shall fear your God, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            your brother shall live with you.</l>
                        <l n="37">You shall not lend him your silver
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            for interest, and you shall not give him your grain for profit.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="38">I am the Lord your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            to give you the land of Canaan, to be God to you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="39">And if your brother becomes poor beside you and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            is sold to you, you shall not make him work a servant’s work.</l>
                        <l n="40">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            He shall be like a settler, he shall serve you until the year of
                            jubilee.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="41">And then he shall go out from you, he and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            his children with him, and shall return to his own family and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            to the possession of his fathers shall he return.</l>
                        <l n="42">For they are my servants,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            whom I brought out from the land of Egypt. They shall not be sold like
                            the sale
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of a servant.</l>
                        <l n="43">You shall not rule over him oppressively, but
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            shall fear your God.</l>
                        <l n="44">And your servants and maidservants that you shall have
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            shall be of the kingdoms that are around you: you shall buy servants
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and maidservants from them.</l>
                        <l n="45">And also from the children of the settlers who
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            live with you: you shall buy from them and of their families
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            that are with you, whom they begat in your land. And they shall become
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            a possession for you.</l>
                        <l n="46">And you shall take them as an inheritance
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            for your children after you, to inherit as a possession.
                            <milestone unit="page" n="202v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            You shall make them work forever. But your brothers, the children of
                            Israel —
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            a man toward his brother: you shall not rule over them oppressively.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="47">And if the hand of a stranger and settler with you attains it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            and your brother with him becomes poor and sells himself to the stranger
                            |and| settler
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            with you or to a godless of the stranger’s family:</l>
                        <l n="48">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            After he is sold he shall have redemption. One of his brothers shall redeem
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            him.</l>
                        <l n="49">Either his uncle or his uncle’s son shall redeem
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            him, or a close relative to his body of his family shall redeem him; or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            if his hand can attain it, he shall redeem himself.</l>
                        <l n="50">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            he shall calculate himself with the one who buys him from the year that
                            he was sold to him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            to the year of jubilee: and the silver of his sale shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            by the number of years. Its shall be with him like the days of a hired
                            worker.</l>
                        <l n="51">If
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            there are still many years, he shall pay back his redemption according
                            to them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            from the silver that he was bought for.</l>
                        <l n="52">And if a few years remain
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            to the year of jubilee, he shall calculate it for him. According
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            to his years shall he return him the silver of his redemption.</l>
                        <l n="53">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            As a hired servant he shall be with him every year, and he shall not
                            rule over him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            oppressively in your sight.</l>
                        <l n="54">And if he is not redeemed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            in these |years|, he shall go out in the year of jubilee, he and his
                            children with him.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                        <l n="55">Because the children of Israel are servants to me. They are my servants,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            whom I brought out from the land of Egypt. I am the Lord your God.
                        </l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="203r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="56">You shall make no vanities for yourselves, and you shall not set up
                            a carved idol or a pillar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            for yourselves and you shall not set up any engraved stones in your land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            to bow down over it, because I am the Lord your God.</l>
                        <l n="57">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            You shall keep my Sabbaths and fear my sanctuary. I am the Lord.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            <emph>Parashat Bechukotai</emph></l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An uncertain translation of
                                <emph>ovelikḱa</emph>, cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he"
                                style="unicode-bidi: embed;">לַצְּמִיתֻת </foreign>
                            ‘forever’.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
