<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 21</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 2<supplied reason="lost">1</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="1">And the Lord remembered<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Sarah, as he had said, and the Lord did to Sarah as he<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>had spoken.</l><l n="2">And Sarah conceived and bore<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>a son for Abraham in his old age, at the appointed time of which<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>God had spoken to him.</l><l n="3">And Abraham called the<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>name of his son that was born to him Isaac, whom Sarah bore to him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="4">And Abraham circumcised Isaac,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>his son, at eight days old, as God had commanded him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="5">And Abraham was a hundred years old when<milestone unit="page" n="29r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Isaac, his son, was born to him.</l><l n="6">And Sarah said,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘God has made laughter for me. Everyone who hears will laugh for me.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="7">And she said, ‘Who would have spoken to Abraham that<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Sarah would nurse children? Yet I have borne a son in his old<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>age.’</l><l n="8">And the child grew, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>was weaned. And Abraham made a great feast<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>on the day that Isaac was weaned.</l><l n="9">And Sarah saw<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the son of Hagar, the Egyptian, whom she had borne<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to Abraham, making fun of Isaac.</l><l n="10">So<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>she said to Abraham, ‘Throw out this maidservant and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>her son, for the son of this maidservant will not inherit<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>with my son, Isaac.’</l><l n="11">And these words seemed bad<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>in Abraham’s eyes because of his son.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="12">And God said to Abraham, ‘Let it not seem bad<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>in your eyes because of the boy and because of maidservant.<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>In all that Sarah has said to you, listen to her voice, for<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>through Isaac shall your offspring be named.’</l><l n="13">And also<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of the son of the maidservant I will make a kingdom, because<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>he is your offspring.’</l><l n="14">And Abraham got up early in the morning,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and took bread, and a bottle of water, and gave it to Hagar,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>he put it on her shoulder, and the child, and<milestone unit="page" n="29v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and sew her out. And she went away and wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="15">And the water was finished in the bottle,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and she cast the child under one of the<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>trees.</l><l n="16">And she went, and sat down<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>opposite him, being away about the span of a shot of an arrow from a bow, for<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>she said, ‘Let me not see the child in his death.’ And she went and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>sat down opposite him and she raised her voice and wept.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="17">And God heard the voice of the boy,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven, and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>said to her, ‘What is |wrong| to you, oh Hagar?’ Do not fear, because<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>God has heard the voice of the boy where he is.</l><l n="18">Arise,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>take the boy, <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg008"/<anchor xml:id="del001"/>and strengthen your hand with him<delSpan spanTo="#del002"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg008"/<anchor xml:id="del002"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>because I will make him into a great kingdom.’</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water;<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and she went, and filled the bottle with water, and gave<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the boy a drink.</l><l n="20">And God’s help was<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>with the boy, and he grew, and dwelt in the wilderness,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and became an archer and bowman.</l><l n="21">And he dwelt<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>in the wilderness of Paran, and his mother took him a wife<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>from the land of Egypt.</l><l n="22">And it was at that time that<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>Abimelech and Phicol, the superior of his army, said to Abraham,<milestone unit="page" n="30r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>saying, ‘God’s help is with you in all that you do.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="23">And now swear to me here by God, in case<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>you were to deal falsely with me, or with my grandson, or with my great-grandson. Like the kindness that<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>I have done with you, you shall do with me, and with the people of the land in which<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>you have lived.’</l><l n="24">And Abraham said, ‘Let me swear.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="25">And Abraham reproved Abimelech about<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>a well of water, which Abimelech’s servants had seized.</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And Abimelech said, ‘I do not know who has done this very thing;<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and also: you did not tell me; and also,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>I did not hear of it except for today.’</l><l n="27">And Abraham took<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>sheep and cattle, and gave them to Abimelech; and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the two of them made a covenant.</l><l n="28">And Abraham set seven<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>lambs of the flock by themselves.</l><l n="29">And Abimelech said<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to Abraham, ‘What are these seven lambs that<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>you have set by themselves?’</l><l n="30">And Abraham said, ‘Because<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>you shall take these seven lambs from my hand that they may be<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>a witness to me that I have dug this well.’</l><l n="31"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>On account of this he called that place Beersheba, because<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the two of them swore there.</l><l n="32">And they made a covenant<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>at Beersheba. And Abimelech and Phicol, the superior of his army,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>rose up and returned to the land of the Philistines.</l><l n="33">And Abraham planted<milestone unit="page" n="30v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>a tree in Beersheba and called there on the name of the Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the God of eternity.</l><l n="34">And Abraham lived in the land of the Philistines<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>many days.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">A mistranslation of Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">וְהַחֲזִ֥יקִי אֶת־יָדֵךְ בֹּו </foreign>‘and hold him with your hand’; repeated in H. Translated correctly in C, V, and R.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
