<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 14</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Genesis 14</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="1">And it was in the days of Amraphel, king of Shinar, Arioch,<milestone unit="page" n="18v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer, king of Elam, and Tidal,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>king of Goiim:</l><l n="2">These kings made war with Bera, king of Sodom, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>with Birsha, king of Gomorrah, with Shinab, king of Admah, and<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Shemeber, king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela, that is,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Zoar.</l><l n="3">All these gathered in the Valley of Siddim,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>that is the salt sea.</l><l n="4">Twelve years they served<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Chedorlaomer, and in the thirteenth year they rebelled.</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And in the fourteenth year came Chedorlaomer, and the kings that<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>were with him, and smote the Rephaim in Ashteroth-Karnaim,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and the Zuzim in Ham, and the Emim in Shaveh-<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>-Kiriathaim.</l><l n="6">And the Horites in the mountains<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of Seir as far as the plain El-Paran, which is by the wilderness.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="7">And they returned <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>and came</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> to Enmishpat, that is Kadesh, and smote<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>all the people of the plain of the Amalekites and also the<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Amorites who were dwelling in Hazazon-Tamar.</l><l n="8">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>there went out the king of Sodom, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela, that is, Zoar, and they lined up<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>with them in |one| army in the Valley of Siddim.</l><l n="9"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>With Chedorlaomer, king of Elam, and with Tidal, king of Goiim,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and Amraphel, king of Shinar, and Arioch, king of<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>Ellasar; four kings with five.</l><l n="10">And the Valley<milestone unit="page" n="19r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of Siddim was full of clay wells, and the kings of Sodom<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and Gomorrah fled, and fell there to be safe, and those who remained<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>fled toward the mountain.</l><l n="11">And they took all the goods of Sodom<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and Gomorrah, and all their food, and they went.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="12">And they took Lot, and his goods, the son<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of Abram’s brother, and they went. And he had been living in Sodom.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="13">And an escapee came and told Abram<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the Hebrew, and he was living on the plains of Mamre<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the Amorite, brother of Eshcol, and brother of Aner;<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and they were covenant partners of Abram.</l><l n="14">And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Abram heard that his kinsman had been taken captive, and he armed<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>his trained men, born in his house, three hundred and eighteen,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and went in pursuit as far as Dan.</l><l n="15">And he divided his forces against them,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>by night, he and his servants, and smote them, and pursued<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>them to the place called Hobah, which is at the left of Damascus.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="16">And he took back all the goods, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>also his brother Lot, and his goods, he took<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>back the women also, and the people.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="17">And the king of Sodom went out to meet him after his return<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>from beating Chedorlaomer, and the kings<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>that were with him, at the Valley of Shaveh. That is, the King’s Valley.</l><milestone unit="page" n="19v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="18">And Melchizedek, king of Salem, brought forth bread and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>wine. And he was the priest of the |most| high God before them.</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he blessed him, and said, ‘Blessed be Abram before the |most| high<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>God, creator of heaven and earth.</l><l n="20">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>praised is the |most| high God, who has donated your enemies to your hand.’<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And Abram gave him a tithe from everything.</l><l n="21">And<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the king of Sodom said to Abram, ‘Give the souls to me, and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>take the goods for yourself.’</l><l n="22">And Abram said to the king<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of Sodom, ‘I have raised my hand with an oath to the Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>the |most| high God, the creator of heaven and earth:</l><l n="23"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg004"/<anchor xml:id="del001"/><supplied reason="lost">I will not take</supplied><delSpan spanTo="#del002"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg004"/<anchor xml:id="del002"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> a thread or a sandal strap from all<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>that is yours, and you should not say, “I have made Abram rich.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="24">Except only that which the servants have eaten,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and the portion of the men who went with me, Aner,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Eshcol, and Mamre: let them take their portion.’</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: <emph>if I take</emph>; a mistranslation repeated in a number of manuscripts resulting from literal translation of the Hebrew conditional clause, cf. Num 14:23, Num 14:30, Num 32:11, Deu 1:35. | TKow.01: <emph>if I take</emph>. | H: <emph>if I take</emph>. | C: <emph>if I take</emph>. | M: <emph>if I take</emph>. | E: <emph>if I take</emph>. | V: <emph>if I take</emph>. | R: <emph>if I take</emph>.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
