<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 16</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Genesis 16</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="1">And Sarai, Abram’s wife, bore him no children. And she<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>had an Egyptian maidservant whose name was Hagar.</l><l n="2">And Sarai said<milestone unit="page" n="21r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to Abram, ‘Lo, now, the Lord has restrained me from bearing:<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>Come to my maidservant. Maybe I will be childed through her.’<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>And Abram listened to the words of Sarai.</l><l n="3">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Sarai Abram’s wife took Hagar her own maidservant the Egyptian,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>after Abram had dwelt ten years in the land<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of Canaan, and gave her to her own husband Abram<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to be his wife.</l><l n="4">And he came to Hagar, and she conceived.<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And she saw that she had conceived, and her mistress was despised<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>in her eyes.</l><l n="5">And Sarai said to Abram,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>‘My wrong is on you! I gave my maidservant to your bosom,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and she saw that she had conceived, and I became despised<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>in her eyes. May the Lord judge between you and me!’</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="6">But Abram said to Sarai, ‘Lo, your maidservant<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>is in your hand. Do to her as it would seem good in your eyes.’<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And Sarai mistreated her, and she fled from before her.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="7">And the angel of the Lord found her by a spring of water<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>in the wilderness, by the spring on the way to Shur.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="8">And he said, ‘Oh Hagar, Sarai’s maidservant,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>where have you come from and where are you going?’ And Hagar said,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>‘I flee from the face of my mistress Sarai.’</l><l n="9">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the angel of the Lord said to her, ‘Return to your mistress, and suffer under her hands.’<milestone unit="page" n="21v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And the angel of the Lord said to her,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘I will surely multiply your offspring, and it will not be countable because of its multitude.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="11">And the angel of the Lord said to her, ‘Lo, you<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>are pregnant, and you will bear a son. You shall call his name Ishmael,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>because the Lord has heard your affliction.</l><l n="12">And he will be a wild<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>man, his hand against everyone and everyone’s hand against him, and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>he will dwell over against all his brethren.’</l><l n="13">And she called the name of the angel<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of the Lord that spoke to her, ‘You God, see me’, for she said,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>‘Now, I have even seen the angel, after I had been seen<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>in the house of Abram.’</l><l n="14">Therefore the<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>well was called, by him who called it, Beer-Lahai-Roi. Lo, it is between<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Kadesh and Bered.</l><l n="15">And Hagar bore<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Abram a son: and Abram called his son’s name Ishmael,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>whom Hagar bore.</l><l n="16">And Abram was eighty-six<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>years old when Hagar bore Ishmael to Abram.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
