<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 23</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 23</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-6-2" n="6" prev="ADub.III.73.003.022.trl.xml#line-6-1" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">‘Speak to the children of Israel,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and say to them, “The feasts of the Lord, which you shall call
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            holy convocations: these are my feasts.</l>
                        <l n="3">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            Six days shall work be done, but in the seventh day is a Sabbath,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the day of complete rest, a holy convocation. You not do any work. It is
                            a Sabbath to the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            in all your dwelling places.</l>
                        <l n="4">These are the feasts of the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            the holy convocations, which you shall proclaim in their appointed
                            times:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="5">In the first month, on the fourteenth day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            of the month, at twilight, is the offering of the Passover to the
                            Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="6">And on the fifteenth day of the same month
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            is the feast of unleavened bread to the Lord. You shall eat unleavened
                            bread seven days.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="7">In the first day you shall have a holy convocation:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            you shall not do any slave labour on it.</l>
                        <l n="8">And you shall bring forward
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            an offering by fire to the Lord seven days. In the seventh day is a holy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            convocation: you shall not do any slave labour on it.”’</l>
                        <l n="9">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="page" n="197r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="10">‘Speak to the children of Israel,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and say to them, “When you will come to the land which I am giving
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            to you and you shall reap its harvest, you shall bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the sheaf of the beginning of your harvest to the priest.</l>
                        <l n="11">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            he shall elevate the sheaf before the Lord, to be accepted for you.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            The priest shall elevate it the next day after Sabbath.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="12">And that day when you elevate the sheaf you shall do
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            an unblemished one-year-old lamb for a burnt offering to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="13">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            And its grain offering shall be two-tenths |of a measure| of fine
                            |flour| mixed with oil,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            an offering by fire to the Lord, a pleasing aroma. And its drink
                            offering shall be wine,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the fourth part of a <emph>hin</emph>.</l>
                        <l n="14">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            you shall not eat bread or parched ear of grain or groats until that
                            very same
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            day that you have brought an offering for your God. It is an eternal
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            statute throughout your generations in all your dwelling places.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="15">And you shall count to you from the day after the Sabbath,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            from the day that you brought the sheaf of the wave offering: seven
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            Sabbaths shall be complete.</l>
                        <l n="16">You shall count until the day after the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            seventh Sabbath fifty days and you shall bring forward a new grain offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="17">You shall bring from your dwelling places
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            two breads for the wave offering. They shall be of two-tenths |of a
                            measure| of fine flour,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            they shall be baked leavened, they are the firstfruits to the Lord, <seg
                                type="commented" n="#seg001" />because that is the ripeness
                            <milestone unit="page" n="197v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            of wheat<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001" /><ref target="#fn1"
                                type="noteAnchor" />.</l>
                        <l n="18">And you shall bring forward with the bread
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            seven unblemished one-year-old lambs and one calf, the young of cattle,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            and two rams. They shall be for a burnt offering to the Lord with
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            their grain offering and their drink offerings, an offering by fire, a
                            pleasing aroma
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="19">And you shall do one kid of the goats
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            for a sin offering and two one-year-old lambs for a sacrifice of peace
                            offerings.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="20">And the priest shall elevate them with the bread of the firstfruits
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            for a wave offering before the Lord with the two lambs. They shall be holy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            to the Lord for the priest.</l>
                        <l n="21">And you shall proclaim on the same
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            day that it may be a holy convocation to you. You shall not do any duty
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            work. It shall be an eternal statute for you in all your dwelling places
                            throughout your generations.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="22">And when you reap the harvest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            of your land, you shall not finish harvesting the edge of your field and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            you shall not gather the gathering of your harvest: you shall leave them
                            for the poor and for the stranger.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            I am the Lord your God.”’</l>
                        <l n="23">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="24">‘Speak to the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            of Israel, saying, “In the seventh month, on the first day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of the month you shall have day of complete rest, a memorial of praise,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            a holy convocation.</l>
                        <l n="25">You shall not do any slave labour on it, and you shall bring forward
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            an offering by fire to the Lord.”’</l>
                        <l n="26">And the Lord spoke to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="27">Just: on the tenth day of this seventh month,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="198r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            it is the day of atonement. There shall be a holy convocation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            to you, and you shall afflict your souls with a fast. And you shall
                            bring forward
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            an offering by fire to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="28">And you shall not do any work on that very same day,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            because it is a day of atonement, to ask for atonement
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            for you before the Lord your God.</l>
                        <l n="29">Because any soul who
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            will not be afflicted with a fast on this very same day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            will be cut off from among his people.</l>
                        <l n="30">And any soul who does any
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            work on that very same day: I will destroy that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            soul from among his people.</l>
                        <l n="31">You shall not do any work:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            an eternal statute throughout your generations in all your dwelling
                            places.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="32">It is a Sabbath, a day of complete of rest, for you, and you shall afflict
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            your souls with fast: on the ninth day of the month
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            at evening, from evening to evening, shall you keep
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            your Sabbath.”’</l>
                        <l n="33">And the Lord spoke to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="34">‘Speak to the children of Israel, saying,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            “On the fifteenth day of this seventh month
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            is the feast of Sukkot, seven days to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="35">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            On the first day is a holy convocation. You shall not do any slave
                            labour.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="36">For seven days you shall bring forward an offering by fire to the Lord.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            On the eighth day there shall be a holy convocation to you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            and you shall bring forward an offering by fire to the Lord. It is a
                            solemn assembly, you shall not do any slave labour.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="198v" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="37">These are the feasts of the Lord, which you shall proclaim
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            to be holy convocations, to offer an offering by fire to the Lord, a
                            burnt offering, and a grain offering,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            a sacrifice, and drink offerings, each day’s |thing| on its day,</l>
                        <l n="38">Besides the Sabbaths
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of the Lord, and besides your gifts, and besides all your vows,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and besides all your freewill offerings which you give to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="39">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            Just: On the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have gathered in
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the produce of the land, you shall celebrate a feast of the Lord seven days.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            On the first day is a day of complete rest and on the eighth day is
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            a day of complete rest.</l>
                        <l n="40">And before the first day you shall take for yourself,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            <seg type="commented" n="#seg002" />in order to make the booths<anchor
                                type="commented" xml:id="seg002" /><ref target="#fn2"
                                type="noteAnchor" />, the fruit of splendid trees, the leaves
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            of palm trees, and the boughs of thick trees, and willows of the river,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            and you shall rejoice before the Lord your God seven days.</l>
                        <l n="41">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            And you shall celebrate it, a feast to the Lord, seven days in the year,
                            an eternal statute
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            through your generations. You shall celebrate it in the seventh
                            month.</l>
                        <l n="42">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            You shall dwell in booths seven days. All native Israelites
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            shall dwell in booths,</l>
                        <l n="43">So that your generations may know
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            that I made the children of Israel to dwell in booths when I brought
                            them out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            from the land of Egypt. I am the Lord <seg type="commented" n="#seg003"
                             />their God<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg003" /><ref
                                target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor" />.”’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="44">And Moses spoke the feasts of the Lord to the children
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-20-1" n="20" next="ADub.III.73.003.024.trl.xml#line-20-2" />
                            of Israel.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Lev
                            23:17.</note>
                        <note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">An uncertain translation of <emph>sukot
                                išĺaḿakḱa</emph>, an interpretative addition to Lev 23:40.</note>
                        <note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">Possibly a mistranslation, cf. Heb.
                                <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">אֱלֹהֵיכֶם </foreign>
                            ‘you God’. Cf., however, e.g. Exo 29:46.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
