<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Exodus 28</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Exodus 28</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex028-P131v-L12_trl" n="12"
                            prev="ADub.III.73.002.027.trl.xml#Ex027-P131v-L12_trl" />
                        <l n="1">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             And bring near to you Aaron, your brother, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             his sons with him, <supplied reason="lost">from</supplied> among the
                            children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             of Israel, to serve me as priests — Aaron, Nadab and Abihu,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             Eleazar and Ithamar, Aaron’s sons.</l>
                        <l n="2">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             you shall make holy garments for Aaron, your brother, for glory and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             for beauty.</l>
                        <l n="3">And you shall speak to all that are wise hearted,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             whom I have filled with the spirit of wisdom, that they shall make
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             Aaron’s garments to sanctify him, that he may serve
                            <milestone unit="page" n="132r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             me as priest.</l>
                        <l n="4">And these are the garments which they shall make: a breastplate,
                            and an ephod,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and a robe, and an embroidered shirt, a turban, and a girdle. And they
                            shall make holy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             garments for Aaron, your brother, and his sons, to serve me as
                            priests.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="5">And they shall take gold, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             blue and purple and scarlet silk,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             and the linen.</l>
                        <l n="6">And they shall make the ephod of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             gold, of blue and of purple and of scarlet silk, and twined
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             linen, embroiderer’s work.</l>
                        <l n="7">It shall have its two shoulders joined
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             at their two edges, and so it shall be joined together.</l>
                        <l n="8">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             And the embroidered band, which is on it, shall be made like its work,
                            and be of one piece with it:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             of gold, of blue and purple and scarlet silk,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             and twined linen.</l>
                        <l n="9">And you shall take two onyx stones,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             and engrave on them the names of the sons of Israel:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="10">Six of their names on one stone,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             and the other six names of the rest on the second stone,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             according to their birth.</l>
                        <l n="11">With the work of an
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             engraver in stone, |like| the engravings of a signet, you shall engrave
                            the two
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             stones with the names of the sons of Israel. You shall
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             make them surrounded by golden filigree.</l>
                        <l n="12">And you shall put the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             two stones on the shoulders of the ephod,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             stones of remembrance for the sons of Israel, and Aaron shall bear
                            <milestone unit="page" n="132v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             their names before the Lord on his two shoulders for remembrance.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="13">And you shall make golden filigree,</l>
                        <l n="14">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             two chains finished in pure gold. You shall make them of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             rope work and put the rope chains
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             on the filigree.</l>
                        <l n="15">And you shall make the breastplate of judgment
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             of embroiderer’s work, you shall make it like the work of the ephod.
                            You shall make it of gold,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             of blue and of purple and of scarlet silk, and of twined linen.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="16">It shall be foursquare and doubled, the length
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             of it a span, and the breadth of it a span.</l>
                        <l n="17">And you shall put it
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             there <addSpan spanTo="#Ex-028-add001_trl" /><emph>a filling of
                                stones</emph><anchor type="addSpan" xml:id="Ex-028-add001_trl" />:
                            four rows of stones. A row of a ruby, an emerald, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             a carbuncle: the one row.</l>
                        <l n="18">And the second
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             row: a kohl stone, a sapphire, and a diamond.</l>
                        <l n="19">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             And the third row: a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst.</l>
                        <l n="20">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             And the fourth row: a beryl, and an onyx, and a jasper.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             They shall be set in golden filigree.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="21">And the stones shall be with the names of the sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of Israel, twelve, with their names; they shall be engravings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             of a signet, each with its name, for twelve tribes.</l>
                        <l n="22">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             And you shall make chains finished in pure gold,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             rope work, on the breastplate.</l>
                        <l n="23">And you shall make
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             two rings of gold on the breastplate and shall put the two
                            <milestone unit="page" n="133r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             rings on the two ends of the breastplate.</l>
                        <l n="24">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             you shall put the two ropes of gold on the two rings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             which are on the ends of the breastplate.</l>
                        <l n="25">And you shall put the two
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             ends of the two ropes on the two settings,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             and put them on the shoulders of the ephod opposite the front of
                            it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="26">And you shall make two rings of gold,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and you shall put them on the two ends of the breastplate
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             in its edge, which is in the inside edge of the ephod.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="27">And you shall make two rings of gold, and shall put
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             them on the two shoulders of the ephod underneath,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             opposite the front of it, opposite the place of coupling, above the
                            embroidered
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             |band| of the ephod.</l>
                        <l n="28">And they shall set
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             the breastplate by its rings on the rings of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             ephod with a blue string, so that it may be above embroidered |band|
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             of the ephod, and that the breastplate shall not lifted from the
                            ephod.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="29">And Aaron shall bear the names of the sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of Israel in the breastplate of judgment on his heart when he comes in
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             into the holy place, for a remembrance before the Lord always.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="30">And you shall put in the breastplate of judgment the Urim
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             and the Thummim, and they shall be on Aaron’s heart
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             when he goes in before the Lord. And Aaron shall bear
                            <milestone unit="page" n="133v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             the judgment of the children of Israel on his heart before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             the Lord always.</l>
                        <l n="31">And you shall make the robe
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             of the ephod all of blue.</l>
                        <l n="32">And its head-opening<ref n="1" target="#Ex-028-fn1_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             shall be within it. It shall have an edging for its opening all around,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             weaver’s work, it shall have an <addSpan spanTo="#Ex-028-add002_trl"
                                 /><emph>edge</emph><anchor type="addSpan"
                                xml:id="Ex-028-add002_trl" /> like that of a coat of mail so it will
                            not be torn.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="33">And you shall make on its hems pomegranates of blue
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and of purple and of scarlet silk, on its hems
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             all around, and bells of gold among them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             all around.</l>
                        <l n="34">A golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             and a pomegranate, on the robe’s hems all around.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="35">And it shall be on Aaron for ministering: and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             the sound of it shall be heard when he goes to the holy place before
                            the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             and when he comes out, and he shall not die.</l>
                        <l n="36">And you shall make a diadem
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             of pure gold, and engrave on it, like the engravings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             of a signet: “<emph>Holy to the Lord</emph>.”</l>
                        <l n="37">And you shall put it
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             on a blue string, that it may be on the turban.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             It shall be on the front of the turban.</l>
                        <l n="38">And it shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             on Aaron’s forehead, that Aaron may bear the sin
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             of the holy things, which the children of Israel shall consecrate
                            according to all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             their holy gifts. And it shall be on his forehead always
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             for acceptance <addSpan spanTo="#Ex-028-add003_trl" /><emph>for
                                them</emph><anchor type="addSpan" xml:id="Ex-028-add003_trl" />
                            before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="39">And you shall embroider
                            <milestone unit="page" n="134r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             the shirt of linen, and you shall make the turban of linen, and you
                            shall make the girdle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             of embroiderer’s word.</l>
                        <l n="40">And for Aaron’s sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             you shall make shirts, and you shall make for them girdles, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             you shall make for them high caps — for glory and for beauty.</l>
                        <l n="41">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             you shall put them on Aaron, your brother, and on his sons with him –
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             and you shall anoint them, and ordain them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and sanctify them, that they may serve me as priests.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="42">And you shall make them white dual trousers to cover the flesh
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             of their nakedness; they shall be from hips to thighs.</l>
                        <l n="43">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             they shall be on Aaron and on his sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             when they come to the tent of meeting or when they come near to the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             altar to minister in the holy place, and they shall not bear
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             a punishment of iniquity, and they will <supplied reason="lost"
                                >not</supplied> die. It is an eternal statute for him
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex028-P134r-L14_trl" n="14"
                                next="ADub.III.73.002.029.trl.xml#Ex029-P134r-L14_trl" />
                             and for his offspring after him.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-028-fn1_trl" type="footnote">Lit. ‘edge for its
                            head’.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
