<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Leviticus 9</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Leviticus 9</title><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l><emph>Parashat Shemini</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="1">And it was<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>on the eighth day, Moses called Aaron<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and his sons and the elders of Israel.</l><l n="2"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>And he said to Aaron, ‘Take you a young calf of cattle<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering, unblemished, and bring them forward<milestone unit="page" n="171r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>before the Lord.</l><l n="3">And you shall speak to the children of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>saying, “Take you a kid of the goats for a sin offering and a calf and a lamb,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>unblemished one-year-olds, for a burnt offering,</l><l n="4">And a bull and a ram for peace offerings<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>to sacrifice before the Lord, and a grain offering mixed with oil,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>because today the divine Presence of the Lord will appear to you.”’</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And they brought that which Moses commanded before the tent of meeting,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and all the congregation drew near and stood before the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="6">And Moses said, ‘This is the word which the Lord commanded<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>that you should do, and the divine Presence of the Lord will appear to you.’</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And Moses said to Aaron, ‘Come forward to the altar, and make<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>your sin offering and your burnt offering, and ask for atonement for yourself<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and for the people, and make the offering of the people,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and ask for atonement for them, as the Lord commanded.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="8">And Aaron came forward to the altar and slaughtered the calf<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of the sin offering that he had.</l><l n="9">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the sons of Aaron brought forward the blood to him, and he dipped his finger<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>in the blood and put it on the horns of the altar and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>poured out the blood at the base of the altar.</l><l n="10"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>And he burned the fat and the kidneys and the<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>extra |fat| from the liver of the sin offering on the altar,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>as the Lord commanded Moses.</l><l n="11">And<milestone unit="page" n="171v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>he burned the flesh and the skin in fire outside<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the camp.</l><l n="12">And he slaughtered the burnt offering,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and Aaron’s sons gave him promptly the blood, and he sprinkled<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>it on the altar all around.</l><l n="13">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>they gave him promptly the burned offering according to its pieces and the head,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and he burned them on the altar.</l><l n="14">And<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>he washed the entrails and the knees, and he burned<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the burnt offering on the altar.</l><l n="15">And he brought forward the<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>people’s offering and took the kid of the sin offering that<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>was for the people and slaughtered it, and he made a sin offering like the first.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="16">And he brought forward the burnt offering and made it<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>according to the |required| manner.</l><l n="17">And he brought forward the grain<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>offering and filled his hand from it and burned it on the altar –<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>besides the morning’s burnt offering.</l><l n="18">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>he slaughtered the bull and the ram for<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>a sacrifice of peace offerings that was for the people. And Aaron’s sons<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>gave him promptly the blood, and he sprinkled it on the altar<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>all around,</l><l n="19">And the fat from the bull<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and from the ram, the |fat| tail, and the fat which covers<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the stomach, and the kidneys, and the extra<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>|fat| of the liver.</l><l n="20">And they put the fat<milestone unit="page" n="172r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>on the breasts, and he burned <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>the fat</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> on the altar.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="21">And Aaron elevated the breasts and the right thigh<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>for a wave offering before the Lord, as Moses commanded.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="22">And Aaron raised his hands<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>toward the people and blessed them after he<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>had come down from making the sin offering and the burnt offering and the peace offerings.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="23">And Moses and Aaron came to the tent of meeting<milestone unit="line" n="8"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>to pray before God to make the fire come down from heavens<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to consume the offerings that were on the altar<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>. And when they<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>came out, they blessed the people, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>the divine Presence of the Lord appeared to all the people.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="24">And fire came out from before the Lord and consumed<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the burnt offering and the fat on the altar,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and the people saw, they sang praises<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and fell on their faces.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Interpretative addition to Lev 9:23.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
