<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Exodus 10</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Exodus 10</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l><emph>Parashat Bo</emph></l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord said to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             ‘Come to Pharaoh, because I have hardened
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             his heart and the heart of his servants for the purpose of my setting
                            <milestone unit="page" n="101v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             these my signs of mine in the midst of them,</l>
                        <l n="2">And for the purpose
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             that you may tell in the ears of your son, and of your son’s
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             son, what I have done wonders in Egypt and my signs
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             which I have set among them, and that you may know that I am the
                            Lord.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="3">And Moses and Aaron came to Pharaoh, and said
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             to him, ‘Thus said the Lord God of the Hebrews, “How long
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             will you not want to break yourself before me? Let my people go, so
                            that they
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             may serve me.</l>
                        <l n="4">Because if you are not willing to let
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             my people go, lo, at daybreak I will bring locust
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             in your border.</l>
                        <l n="5">And they will cover the face of the earth, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             one will not be able to see the earth. And they will eat the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             residue of that which is escaped, which remained to you from the hail,
                            and will eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             every tree which grows for you from the field.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="6">And your houses will fill up, and the houses of all your servants,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             and the houses of all the Egyptians, which your fathers, or your
                            fathers’
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             fathers did not see from the times that they were on the earth to this
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             day.”’ And he turned, and went out from before Pharaoh.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="7">And Pharaoh’s servants said to him, ‘How long
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             shall this be a snare to us? Let those men go, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             may they serve the Lord their own God.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             Do you want to learn that Egypt is destroyed before you let them
                            go?’</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="102r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="8">And Moses and Aaron turned to Pharaoh,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and he said to them, ‘Go, serve the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             your God. But who will be they that shall go?’</l>
                        <l n="9">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             And Moses said, ‘We will go with our children and with our old,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             with our sons and with our daughters, we will go with our flocks and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             with our cattle, because we are obliged to hold a feast to the
                            Lord’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="10">And he said to them, ‘Let the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             Lord’s help be so with you when I will let you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             and your young ones go, see, because evil is before you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="11">Not so! Go now, you, young men, and serve
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             the Lord, because you wanted this.’ And he drove them out from
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             before Pharaoh.</l>
                        <l n="12">And the Lord said to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             ‘Reach out your hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             and it shall come up on the land of Egypt, and it shall eat every
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             plant of the land, all that the hail has left.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="13">And Moses reached out his staff over the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of Egypt, and the Lord drove an east wind on the land all that day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             and all the night. It was morning, and the east wind
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             brought the locusts.</l>
                        <l n="14">And the locusts went up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             over all the land of Egypt and lingered
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             in all the borders of Egypt, very strong: before it there were no
                            <milestone unit="page" n="102v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             such locusts like it, and after them there will not be such.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="15">And they covered the face of the whole earth, so that the land was
                            darkened,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             and they ate every plant of the land, and all the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             fruit of the trees which the hail had left. And there remained not any
                            green
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             thing in the trees, or in the plants of the field, in all the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             of Egypt.</l>
                        <l n="16">And Pharaoh hurried to call for Moses
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and Aaron, and he said, ‘I have sinned against the Lord your God,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             and against you.</l>
                        <l n="17">And now, forgive
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             my sin only this once, and pray to the Lord your
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             God, that he may take from me just this death away.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="18">And he went out from before Pharaoh, and prayed to
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="19">And the Lord turned back a
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             very strong west wind, and took away the locusts,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             and drove them into the Red Sea. Not one locust was left
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             in all the border of Egypt.</l>
                        <l n="20">But the Lord hardened
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             Pharaoh’s heart, and he did not let the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of Israel go.</l>
                        <l n="21">And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Reach out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             your hand toward the skies, that there may be darkness over the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             of Egypt, even darkness which may be touched.’</l>
                        <l n="22">And Moses reached out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             his hand toward the skies, and there was a foggy darkness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             in all the land of Egypt three days.</l>
                        <l n="23">They did not see
                            <milestone unit="page" n="103r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             one another, neither rose any from his place for three
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             days. But all the children of Israel had light in their
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             places of dwelling.</l>
                        <l n="24">And Pharaoh called to Moses, and said,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             ‘Go, serve the Lord, only let your flocks and your cattle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             be left. Your little ones shall go with you as well.’</l>
                        <l n="25">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             Moses said, ‘You must give us also sacrifices and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             burnt offerings, so we will do them to the Lord our God.</l>
                        <l n="26">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             our livestock will go with us as well. Not a hoof will be left,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             because of them we will take to serve the Lord our God,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             and we do not know with what kind of sacrifice we will serve
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             the Lord, until we come there.’</l>
                        <l n="27">But
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             the Lord hardened Pharaoh’s heart, and he did not want to let
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             them go.</l>
                        <l n="28">And Pharaoh said to him, ‘Go
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             from before me, take heed to yourself, see my face no more,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             because in that day you see my face you shall die.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="29">And Moses said, ‘You have spoken the truth,
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex010-P103r-L17_trl" n="17"
                                next="ADub.III.73.002.011.trl.xml#Ex011-P103r-L17_trl" />
                             I will not see your face again.’</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
