<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 34</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Numbers 34</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="1">And the Lord spoke<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to Moses, saying,</l><l n="2">‘Command the children of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and say to them, “When you come to the land, to the land of Canaan,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>this is the land that will fall to you as a share, the land of Canaan<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>by its borders:</l><l n="3">And your will be the south side,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>from the wilderness of Zin next to Edom,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and your will be the south border from the edge of the salt<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>sea eastward.</l><l n="4">And your border will turn<milestone unit="page" n="274v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>from the south to the ascent of Akrabbim,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and pass on to Zin. And its ends will be from the south<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to Kadesh-Barnea, and will go out to Hazar-Addar and pass on to Azmon.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="5">And the border shall turn from Azmon to the river of Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and the ends of it will be to the sea.</l><l n="6">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the western border: you shall have the Great Sea for a border.<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>This will be your west border.</l><l n="7">And this will be<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>your north border: from the Great Sea you shall mark |it| out<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>for yourself to Mount Hor.</l><l n="8">From Mount Hor you shall mark |it| out to Lebo-<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Hamath, and the ends of the border will be at Zedad.</l><l n="9"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And the border shall go out to Ziphron, and the ends of it will be at Hazar-Enan.<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>This will be your north border.</l><l n="10">And you shall mark out<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>your <supplied reason="lost">east</supplied> border from Hazar-Enan to Shepham.</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And the border will go down <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/><supplied reason="lost">from Shepham toward Riblah</supplied><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>, on the east side<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to the fountain of water, and the border will go down and will reach<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to the eastern side of the Sea of Kinnereth.</l><l n="12">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the border shall go down to the Jordan, and the ends of it will be at the Salt Sea.<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>This will be your land by its borders all around.’</l><l n="13"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>And Moses commanded the children of Israel, saying, ‘This is the<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>land which you shall divide by lot, which the Lord commanded to give to the nine<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>tribes and to the half tribe:</l><l n="14">Because the tribe<milestone unit="page" n="275r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of the children of Reuben by the house of their fathers and the tribe of the children<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of Gad by the house of their fathers and the half tribe of Manasseh had taken their share.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="15">The two tribes and the half tribe had taken their share<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>across the ford of Jordan of Jericho toward the sun rising, eastward.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="16">And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l><l n="17"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>‘These are the names of the men who shall divide the land to you:<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Eleazar, the priest, and Joshua, son of Nun.</l><l n="18"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>And you shall take one leader of each tribe, one leader of each tribe, to share<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the land.</l><l n="19">And these are the names of the men:<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Of the tribe of Judah: Caleb, son of Jephunneh.</l><l n="20">And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of the tribe of the children of Simeon: Shemuel, son of Ammihud.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="21">Of the tribe of Benjamin: Elidad, son of Chislon.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="22">And the prince of the tribe of the children of Dan: Bukki, son<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of Jogli.</l><l n="23">The prince of the children of Joseph, of the tribe of the children<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of Manasseh: Hanniel, son of Ephod.</l><l n="24">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the prince of the tribe of the children of Ephraim: Kemuel, son of Shiphtan.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="25">And the prince of the tribe of the children of Zebulun: Elizaphan,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>son of Parnach.</l><l n="26">And the prince of the tribe of the children of Issachar:<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Paltiel, son of Azzan.</l><l n="27">And the prince of the tribe<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>of the children of Asher: Ahihud, son of Shelomi.</l><l n="28"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And the prince of the tribe of the children of Naphtali: Pedahel, son of Ammihud.’</l><milestone unit="page" n="275v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="29">These are the ones whom the Lord commanded to divide |the inheritance| to the children<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of Israel in the land of Canaan.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">A mistranslation based on interpreting BHeb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">מִשְּׁפָם הָרִבְלָה </foreign>‘from Shepham toward Riblah’ as one place name.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
