<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 46</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Genesis 46</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="1">And Israel journeyed with all that he had, and came<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>to Beersheba, and offered sacrifices to the God<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of his father Isaac.</l><l n="2">And God’s angel came<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to Israel in the visions of the night, and said,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>‘Jacob, Jacob.’ And he said, ‘Lo, I am here.’</l><l n="3"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And he said, ‘I am God, the God of your father. Do not fear<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to go down to Egypt, because I will make you into a great kingdom<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>there.</l><l n="4">I will go down with you to Egypt, and I will also<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>surely bring you out again. And Joseph will put his hand on your eyes<milestone unit="line" n="21"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>when you die<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>.</l><l n="5">And Jacob rose up<milestone unit="page" n="78v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>from Beersheba. And the sons of Israel took Jacob,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>their father, and their little ones and their wives<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>with the wagons which Pharaoh had sent to take him.</l><l n="6">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>they took their livestock, and their goods, which they had gained<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in the land of Canaan, and came to Egypt, Jacob, and all his offspring<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>with him:</l><l n="7">He brought his sons, and his sons’ sons<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>with him, his daughters, and his sons’ daughters,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and all his offspring with him to Egypt.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="8">And these are the names of the sons of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>who came to Egypt, Jacob and his sons:<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Reuben, Jacob’s firstborn.</l><l n="9">And the sons of Reuben:<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Hanoch, and Pallu, and Hezron, and Carmi.</l><l n="10">And the sons<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of Simeon: Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Shaul the son of a Canaanite woman.</l><l n="11">And the sons<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of Levi: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari.</l><l n="12">And the sons<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Perez, and Zarah. And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sons<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of Perez were Hezron, and Hamul.</l><l n="13">And the sons of Issachar:<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Tola, and Puvah, and Iob, and Shimron.</l><l n="14">And<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the sons of Zebulun: Sered, and Elon, and Jahleel.</l><l n="15">These<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>are the sons of Leah, whom she bore to Jacob in Paddan-Aram,<milestone unit="page" n="79r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and Dinah, his daughter, all the souls of his sons and his daughters,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>thirty-three.</l><l n="16">And the sons of Gad: <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>Ziphion, and Haggi</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/>, Shuni, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Ezbon, Eri, and Arodi, and Areli.</l><l n="17">And the sons of Asher:<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah, their sister.<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And the sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel.</l><l n="18"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>These are the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah, his daughter,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and these she bore to Jacob, sixteen souls.</l><l n="19"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>The sons of Rachel, Jacob’s wife: Joseph, and Benjamin.</l><l n="20"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And Manasseh and Ephraim were born to Joseph in the land of Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>whom Asenath, daughter of Potiphera, priest of On, bore to him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="21">And the sons of Benjamin were Belah, and Becher, and Ashbel,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Gera, and Naaman, Ehi, and Rosh, Muppim, and Huppim, and Ard.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="22">These are the sons of Rachel, who were born to Jacob. All<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the souls were fourteen.</l><l n="23">And the son of Dan: Hushim.</l><l n="24"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And the sons of Naphtali: Jahzeel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shillem.</l><l n="25"><milestone unit="line" n="16"/>These are the sons of Bilhah, whom Laban gave to Rachel his daughter,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and she bore these to Jacob. All the souls were seven.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="26">All the souls that came with Jacob into Egypt, who came out<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>from his thigh, besides Jacob’s sons’ wives, all<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the souls were sixty-six.</l><l n="27">And the sons of Joseph,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>who were born to him in Egypt, were two souls. All the souls of the house of Jacob,<milestone unit="page" n="79v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>who came to Egypt, were seventy.</l><l n="28">And he sent Judah<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>before him to Joseph, to teach the way before him<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to Goshen. And they came to the land of Goshen.</l><l n="29">And Joseph harnessed his chariot, and went up to meet Israel, his father, to Goshen, and appeared himself to him, and he fell on his neck,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and wept on his neck as well.</l><l n="30"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And Israel said to Joseph, ‘Let me die now,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>after I have seen your face, that you are still alive.’</l><l n="31">And<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Joseph said to his brothers, and to the people of his father’s house,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>‘I will go up, and tell Pharaoh, and say to him, “My brothers,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and the people of my father’s house, who were in the land of Canaan, came<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to me.</l><l n="32">And the men are shepherds,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>because they were keepers of livestock, and they have brought their flocks,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and their cattle, and all that they have.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="33">And it shall be, if Pharaoh calls you and says,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>“What is your work?”:</l><l n="34">And you shall say, “Your servants<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>were keepers of livestock from our youth until now, both<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>we and our fathers as well,” in order that you may dwell in the land<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of Goshen, because every shepherd is an abomination to the Egyptians.’</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 46:4.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
