<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 19</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 1<supplied reason="lost">9</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="1">And the two envoys came<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to Sodom in the evening, and Lot was sitting in the gate of Sodom,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and Lot saw and rose up to meet them and he bowed<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>with his face toward the ground.</l><l n="2">And he said, ‘Lo, I pray you,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>my lords, turn in now, into your servant’s house, and spend the night and wash<milestone unit="page" n="25v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>your feet, and you shall rise up early and go on your way.’ And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>they said, ‘No, for we will spend the night in the street.’</l><l n="3">And he pressed<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>them greatly, and they turned in to him, and entered his house,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and he made for them drink and baked cake, and they ate.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="4">But before they lay down, the men of the city, the men<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of Sodom, surrounded the house, both youth and old,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>all the people to the last |man|.</l><l n="5">And they called<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Lot, and said to him, ‘Where are the men who came<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to you this night? Bring them out to us, and let us harass them.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="6">And Lot went out to them at the door, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>shut the covering |of the door| behind him.</l><l n="7">And he said, ‘I pray<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>you, brothers, do not do bad.</l><l n="8">Lo, now,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>I have two daughters who have not known a man. Let me bring them out<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to you, and do you to them as it seems good in your eyes. Only<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to these men do nothing, because they have come<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to have shelter in the shadow of my ceiling.’</l><l n="9">And they said,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>‘Move away!’ And they said, ‘This one came to live, and then<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>he surely judged! Now we will do worse |things|<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to you than to them!’ And they harassed Lot, the man, greatly and came near to break<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the door.</l><l n="10">But the men reached<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>their hand out and brought Lot into the house<milestone unit="page" n="26r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and shut the covering of the door.</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And they smote the men that were at the door of the house<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>with blindness, both small and great, and they wearied |themselves|<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>with finding the door.</l><l n="12">And the men<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>said to Lot, ‘Whom do you have here besides? Son-in-law, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>your sons, and your daughters, and anyone you have<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>in the city, bring them out of the place.</l><l n="13">Because we are destroying<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>this place, because their cry has become big<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>before the Lord, and the Lord has sent us to destroy<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>it.’</l><l n="14">And Lot went out, and spoke to his sons-in-law,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>who married his daughters, and said, ‘Arise, get out of this place,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>because the Lord will destroy the city.’ But he seemed<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>as one who mocks in the eyes of his sons-in-law.</l><l n="15">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>when the morning arose, then the envoys urged<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Lot, saying, ‘Arise, take your wife, and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>your two daughters who are here, lest you be perished because of the iniquity<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of the city.’</l><l n="16">But he lingered, so<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the men seized his hand, and his wife’s hand, and the hands<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of his two daughters, with the Lord’s mercy on him,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and they brought him out and set him outside the city.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="17">And it was when they were bringing them out,<milestone unit="page" n="26v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>|and| he said, ‘Escape for your life. Do not look behind you,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>neither stay in all the valley, escape to the mountain, lest<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>you be perished.’</l><l n="18">And Lot said to them, ‘I pray you,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>my lords.</l><l n="19">Lo, now, your servant has found favour in your eyes,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and you have magnified your kindness, which you have done to me in<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>keeping my soul alive. But I cannot escape to the<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>mountain, lest some evil reach me, and I die.</l><l n="20"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Lo, now, this city is near to flee there, and it is small. Let me escape<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>now there — lo, it is small — and my soul shall stay alive.’</l><l n="21"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And the envoy said to him, ‘Lo, I granted you a favour<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>in this matter as well, not to ruin the city of which you have spoken.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="22">Hurry, escape there, because I cannot do<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>anything until you get there.’ Therefore the name of <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>it<anchor xml:id="del001"/>
							<addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>the city</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> was called Zoar.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="23">The sun was shining upon the earth when Lot<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>came to Zoar.</l><l n="24">Then the Lord rained<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>sulphur and fire on Sodom and on Gomorrah, from<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the Lord out of the skies.</l><l n="25">And he ruined those<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>cities, and all the valley, and<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>all the inhabitants of the cities, and what grew on the ground.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="26">But his wife looked behind him, and she became<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>a pillar of salt.</l><l n="27">And Abraham rose up early at dawn<milestone unit="page" n="27r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to the place where he stood before the Lord.</l><l n="28"><milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And he looked toward Sodom and Gomorrah and toward all<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the land of the valley, and he looked, and, lo, thick smoke of the land was rising<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>like the smoke of a lime kiln.</l><l n="29">And it was,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>when God destroyed the cities of the valley, that God remembered<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Abraham, and sent Lot out of the midst<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of the ruining, when he ruined the cities<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>in one of which Lot dwelt.</l><l n="30">And Lot went up from Zoar,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and dwelt in the mountain, and his two daughters with him,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>because he feared to dwell in Zoar, and he dwelt in a cave,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>he and his two daughters.</l><l n="31">And the older said<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to the younger, ‘Our father is old, and there is not a man on the earth<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>to come to us after the way of all the earth.</l><l n="32">Come,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>let us make our father drink wine, and we will lie with him, that<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>we may revive offspring from our father.’</l><l n="33">And they made their own father drink<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>wine that night. And the older came and lay<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>with her father. And he did not know when she lay down, or when she arose.</l><l n="34"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>And it was after dawn that the older said to the younger, ‘Lo,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>I lay last night with my father. Let us make him drink wine this night as well,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and you come and lie with him, that we may revive offspring from our father.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="35">And they made their own father drink wine that night as well,<milestone unit="page" n="27v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and the younger arose and lay with him,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and he did not know when she lay down, or when she arose.</l><l n="36"><milestone unit="line" n="3"/>And both the daughters of Lot became pregnant by their father.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="37">The older bore a son and called his name<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Moab. He was the father of the Moabites to this day.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="38">The younger also bore a son<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and called his name Ben-Ammi. He was the father of Ammon<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to this day.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
