<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 16</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 16</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l><emph>Parashat Acharei Mot</emph></l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            to Moses after the death of the two sons of Aaron —
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            when they came forward before the Lord, and died.</l>
                        <l n="2">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Speak to Aaron, your brother, that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            he shall not come at all times to the Holy within the veil before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the cover which is over the ark, so that he may not die, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            my divine Presence will appear in a cloud over the mercy seat.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="3">Aaron shall come to the Holy with this: with the blood of a calf,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            the young of cattle, for a sin offering, and with the blood of a ram for
                            a burnt offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="4">He shall put on the holy white shirt, and the white dual trousers
                            shall be
                            <milestone unit="page" n="186r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            on his body and shall be girded with the white girdle, and he shall wrap
                            himself with the white turban.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            They are the holy clothes. And he shall wash
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            his body in water and put them on.</l>
                        <l n="5">And he shall take from the congregation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of the children of Israel two kids of the goats for a sin offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and one ram for a burnt offering.</l>
                        <l n="6">And Aaron shall bring forward
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            his calf of the sin offering, which is for himself, and ask for atonement
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            for himself and for his house.</l>
                        <l n="7">And he shall take the two
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            goats and set them before the Lord at the door
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="8">And Aaron shall cast lots over the two goats,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            one lot for the Lord and one lot for Azazel.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="9">And Aaron shall bring forward the goat on which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            the lot for Lord arose and he shall make it a sin offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="10">And the goat, on which the lot for Azazel arose
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            shall be stood alive before the Lord to ask for atonement
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            over it, to let him go to Azazel, to the wilderness.</l>
                        <l n="11">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            And Aaron shall bring forward the calf of the sin offering, which is for
                            himself, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            shall ask for atonement for himself and for his house, and shall
                            slaughter the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            calf of the sin offering which is for himself.</l>
                        <l n="12">And he shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            a censer full of burning coals of fire from off the altar before the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and a handful of fine sweet incense, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            he shall bring it within the veil.</l>
                        <l n="13">And he shall put the
                            <milestone unit="page" n="186v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            incense on the fire before the Lord, so that the cloud of the incense
                            may cover
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            the cover that is on the testimony, so that he does not die.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="14">And he shall take of the blood of the calf and sprinkle it with
                            his finger before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the cover eastward, and he shall sprinkle of the blood with his finger
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            before the cover seven times.</l>
                        <l n="15">Then he shall slaughter the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            goat of the sin offering that is for the people and bring its blood within
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the veil and do with that blood as he did with the blood of the calf, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            he shall sprinkle it on the cover and before the cover.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="16">And he shall ask for atonement over the Holy, because of the uncleanness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            of the children of Israel and because of their transgressions in all
                            their sins.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            And he shall do so for the tent of meeting that dwells with them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            in the midst of their uncleanness.</l>
                        <l n="17">And there shall be no man
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            in the tent of meeting when he comes to ask for atonement in the Holy,
                            until he comes out,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and he shall ask for atonement for himself and for his household and for
                            all the congregation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="18">And he shall go out to the altar that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            is before the Lord and ask for atonement for it, and he shall take of
                            the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            of the calf and of the blood of the goat, and he shall put it on the horns
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of the altar all around.</l>
                        <l n="19">And he shall sprinkle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of the blood on it with his finger seven times and cleanse it and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            sanctify it from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.</l>
                        <l n="20">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            And when he finishes atoning for the Holy and the tent
                            <milestone unit="page" n="187r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            of meeting and the altar, then he shall bring forward the live
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            goat.</l>
                        <l n="21">And Aaron shall reach out both his hands over the head
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            of the live goat and confess over him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            all the iniquities of the children of Israel and all their transgressions
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            in all their sins, putting them on the head of the goat,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and he shall send him away by the hand of man in readiness to the
                            wilderness.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="22">And the goat shall carry on itself
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            all their iniquities to the desert. And he shall let the goat go
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            in the wilderness.</l>
                        <l n="23">And Aaron shall come to the tent of meeting and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            shall take off the white garments that he put on when he came to the Holy,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and he shall leave them there.</l>
                        <l n="24">And he shall wash his body
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            with water in the holy place and put on his garments, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            he shall go out and make his burnt offering and the burnt offering of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            people and ask for atonement for himself and for the people.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="25">And he shall burn the fat of the calf on the altar.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="26">And the one who let the goat go to Azazel shall wash
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            his clothes and wash his body in water, and after that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            he shall come to the camp.</l>
                        <l n="27">And he shall carry the calf for the sin offering and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            the goat for the sin offering whose blood was brought in to ask for atonement
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            in the Holy, outside the camp. And they shall burn
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            their skins and their flesh and
                            <milestone unit="page" n="187v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            their dung in fire.</l>
                        <l n="28">And the one who burns them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            shall wash his clothes and wash his body in water, and after that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            he shall come to the camp.</l>
                        <l n="29">And it shall be a statute forever to you:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall afflict
                            your souls
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and do no work at all, either <supplied reason="lost">a
                                native</supplied><ref n="1" target="#Lev-016-fn1_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> or a stranger who lives
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            among you.</l>
                        <l n="30">Because on this day he will ask for atonement for you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            to cleanse you. You shall be clean from all your sins before the
                            Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="31">It is a Sabbath, the day of complete rest to you, and you shall
                            afflict your souls —
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            a statute forever.</l>
                        <l n="32">And the priest,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            whom one shall anoint and who will fill his hand to serve as a priest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            in his father’s place shall ask for atonement and shall put on the white
                            clothes, the holy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            clothes.</l>
                        <l n="33">And he shall ask for atonement for the holy sanctuary,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            and he shall ask for atonement for the tent of meeting and for the
                            altar, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            he shall ask for atonement for the priests and for all the people of the
                            congregation.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="34">And this shall be an everlasting statute to you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            to ask for atonement for the children of Israel for all their sins once
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            a year.’ And he did as the Lord commanded Moses.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="Lev-016-fn1_trl" type="footnote">K: ‘poor’; a scribal error,
                            cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">הָאֶזְרָח </foreign>
                            ‘a native of your own country’; cf. Exo 12:19, Exo 12:48, Exo 12:49, and
                            Lev 17:15.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
