<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 17</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 17</title><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="1">And Abram was ninety-nine years old, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>divine Presence</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/>
							<supplied reason="lost">of the</supplied> Lord appeared to Abram, and said to him, ‘I am mighty God;<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>walk before me, and be unblemished.</l><l n="2">And I will give<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>my covenant between me and you, and I will multiply you<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>greatly.’</l><l n="3">And Abram fell on his face:<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and the divine Presence of God talked with him, saying,</l><milestone unit="page" n="22r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="4">‘I: lo, my covenant is with you, and you will be a father<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of many kingdoms.’</l><l n="5">And your name will not be called<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Abram, but your name will be Abraham, because<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>I will make you the father of a mass of kingdoms.</l><l n="6">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>I will spread you greatly, and I will make you into kingdoms,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and kings will come out of you.</l><l n="7">And I will establish<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>my covenant between me and you and your<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>offspring after you throughout their generations for an everlasting<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>covenant, to be God to you and to your offspring after you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="8">And I will give to you and to your offspring<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>after you the land of your sojourning, all the land of<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Canaan, for an everlasting possession, and I will be your<ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> God.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="9">And God said to Abraham, ‘And you:<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>you shall keep my covenant, you, and your offspring after you<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>throughout their generations.</l><l n="10">This is my covenant, which you shall keep, between me<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and you and <supplied reason="lost">your offspring after you</supplied>: every male among you is to be circumcised.</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And you shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskins, and it shall be a sign<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of the covenant between me and you.</l><l n="12">And at eight days old<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>every male shall be circumcised among you throughout your generations, he who is born in the house,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>or bought with silver of any foreign nation, who is not<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of your offspring.</l><l n="13">He shall surely be circumcised<milestone unit="page" n="22v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>who is born in your house, and he who is bought with your silver, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant.</l><l n="14">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the uncircumcised male child, whose flesh of his foreskin is not circumcised,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>that soul shall vanish from among his own people that<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>are the congregation of angels, for he has broken my covenant.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="15">And God said to Abraham, ‘Sarai, your wife:<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>you shall not call her name Sarai, because her name is Sarah.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="16">And I will bless her, and moreover, I will give you a son<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>by her. I will bless her, and she will be a mother of kingdoms,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>kings of peoples will be from her.’</l><l n="17">Then Abraham fell<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>on his face, and was pleased, and said in his heart,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>‘Will a child be born to a man who is a hundred years old? And will Sarah, who is ninety,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>bear?’</l><l n="18">And Abraham said to God,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>‘If only Ishmael might live before you!’</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>God said, ‘Sarah your wife will, indeed, bear you a son,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and you shall call his name Isaac. And I will establish<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant, for his offspring<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>after him.</l><l n="20">And as for Ishmael:<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>I inform you, lo, I will bless him, and will spread him,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and will multiply him greatly. Twelve princes<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>shall he beget and I will make him into a great nation.</l><l n="21">But<milestone unit="page" n="23r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>I will establish my covenant with Isaac, whom Sarah shall bear to you<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>at this time next year.’</l><l n="22">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he finished talking with him, and the divine Presence of God<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>went up from Abraham.</l><l n="23">And Abraham took<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Ishmael his son, and all that were born in his house,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and all that were bought with his silver, every male<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>among the people of Abraham’s house, and he circumcised the flesh<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of their foreskins in the same day, as<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the divine Presence of God had spoken with him.</l><l n="24">And Abraham<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>was ninety-nine years old when he was circumcised, the flesh of his foreskin.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="25">And Ishmael his son was thirteen years old<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>when he was circumcised at the flesh of his foreskin.</l><l n="26">In<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the same day was Abraham circumcised, and<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Ishmael, his son.</l><l n="27">And all the men of his house, born<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>in the house, and bought with silver from all foreigners, were<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>circumcised with him.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Probably a scribal error, cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">לָהֶם </foreign>‘to them’ (Gen 17:8).</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
