<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 23</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 2<supplied reason="lost">3</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/></title><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="1">And the life of Sarah was<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>a hundred years and twenty-seven years, these were the years of the life<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>of Sarah.</l><l n="2">And Sarah died in the city of Arba,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>that is, Hebron, in the land of Canaan, and Abraham came to mourn<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>for Sarah, and to weep for her.</l><l n="3">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Abraham rose up from in front of his dead, and he spoke to the sons<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of Heth, saying,</l><l n="4">‘Even if I am a stranger: but I want<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to be a settler with you. Give me a possession of a sepulchre<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>with you, that I may bury my dead from in front of me’.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="5">And the children of Heth answered Abraham,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>saying to him,</l><l n="6">‘Hear us, my lord. You are a prince<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of God among us. Bury your dead in the choice of our sepulchres.<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>None of us will begrudge you his sepulchre,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>|to hold you back| from burying your dead.’</l><l n="7">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Abraham rose, and bowed himself to the people of the land, to the children<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of Heth.</l><l n="8">And he spoke with them, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>‘If you are willing to bury my dead<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>from in front of me, hear me and entreat for me Ephron<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the son of Zohar:</l><l n="9">That he may give me the cave<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>of Machpelah, <supplied reason="lost">which is</supplied> his, which is in the end of his field. For the full silver<ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>he shall give it to me among you as possession of a sepulchre.’</l><milestone unit="page" n="32v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="10">And Ephron was sitting among the children<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of Heth, and Ephron the Hittite answered Abraham in the hearing<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the children of Heth, of all who were coming to the gate of his city, saying,</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="11">‘No, my lord, hear me: I give you the field,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and I give you the cave that is in it. In the sight of<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of my people I give it to you. Bury your dead.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="12">And Abraham bowed down before the people of the<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>land,</l><l n="13">And spoke to <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>Abraham<anchor xml:id="del001"/>
							<addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>Ephron</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> in the hearing of the people<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of the land, saying, ‘Really, if only you would listen<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to me! I shall give you the silver for the field. Take it from me, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>I shall bury my dead there.’</l><l n="14">And Ephron answered<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Abraham, saying to him,</l><l n="15">‘Oh my lord,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>listen to me. The land is worth four hundred mithqals of silver:<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>what is that between me and you? And bury your dead.’</l><l n="16">And Abraham listened<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to the words of Ephron, and Abraham weighed out<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>for Ephron the silver<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>that he had spoken of in the hearing of the children on Heth, four hundred weights<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of silver, current money with the merchants.</l><l n="17">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the field of Ephron in Machpelah, which was to the east of Mamre, the<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>field with the cave that was in it and all the trees that were in the field,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>that were in all the borders all around was established:</l><l n="18">For Abraham<milestone unit="page" n="33r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>as a purchase in the presence of the children of Heth, all who were coming<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to the gate of his city.</l><l n="19">And after this,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Abraham buried <addSpan spanTo="#add002"/><emph>so</emph><anchor xml:id="add002"/> Sarah, his wife, in the cave of the field of<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Machpelah before Mamre, that is, Hebron, in the land<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of Canaan.</l><l n="20">And the purchase of the plain,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and of the cave that is in it was established, from the children of Heth for Abraham<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>for a possession of a sepulchre.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: The beginning of parashat Chayei Sarah is not indicated.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">I.e., <emph>for full price</emph>.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
