<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 41</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 41</title><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l><emph>Parashat Miketz</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="1">And it was in the course of two<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>years, and Pharaoh dreamed: and, lo,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>he stands by the Nile.</l><l n="2">And, lo, there came up out of the Nile<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>seven cows beautiful-looking and plump, and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>they fed in the reeds.</l><l n="3">And, lo, seven other cows<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>came up after them out of the river, of bad-looking<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and thin, and they stood by the other cows<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>on the bank of the river.</l><l n="4">And<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the bad-looking and thin cows ate up the seven<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>beautiful-looking and fat cows.<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And Pharaoh awoke.</l><l n="5">And he slept and dreamed<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the second time: and, lo, seven ears of grain came up on one<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>stalk, plump and good.</l><l n="6">And, lo, seven<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>thin ears and lashed by the east wind sprung up<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>after them.</l><l n="7">And the seven empty ears swallowed<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the seven healthy and full ears. And<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Pharaoh awoke, and, lo, the dream ended.</l><l n="8">And it was<milestone unit="page" n="67v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>in the morning, and his spirit was troubled, and he sent and called<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>for all the magicians of Egypt, and all its wise men.<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>And he told them his dream, but there was none of them that could interpret |them|<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>to Pharaoh.</l><l n="9">Then the superior of the cup-bearers spoke<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>to Pharaoh, saying, ‘I do remember my faults<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>this day.</l><l n="10">Pharaoh was angry with his servants,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and put me under guard in the house of the superior of the executioners,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>me and the superior of the bakers.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="11">And we dreamed a dream in one night,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>I and he, we dreamed each man according to the interpretation of his dream.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="12">And a young man was there with us, a Hebrew,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>servant to the superior of the executioners. And we told him, and he interpreted<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>to us our dreams: to each man according to his interpretation<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>he did interpret.</l><l n="13">And it was — as he interpreted to us,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>so it was: me he restored to my place, and him he hanged.’</l><l n="14"><milestone unit="line" n="16"/>And Pharaoh sent and called Joseph, and they made him run<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>from the prison, and he let him shave and change<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his clothes, and he came to Pharaoh.</l><l n="15">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Pharaoh said to Joseph, ‘I have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>it. And I have heard about you, saying, you understand<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>a dream to interpret it.’</l><l n="16">And Joseph answered Pharaoh,<milestone unit="page" n="68r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>saying, ‘It is other than me: God shall restore<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the health of Pharaoh.’</l><l n="17">And Pharaoh spoke<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to Joseph, ‘In my dream, lo, I stand on the bank<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of the Nile:</l><l n="18">And, lo, there came up out of the Nile seven<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>cows, plump and beautiful in form and they fed<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>in the reed.</l><l n="19">And, lo, seven other cows<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>came up after them, gaunt and very bad-looking<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and thin, such as I never saw in all the land<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of Egypt for badness.</l><l n="20">And the cows,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>those thin and the ill ate up the first seven<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>fat cows.</l><l n="21">And they went inside them,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and it could not be known that they had entered them, but they appearance<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>was still ill as at the beginning. And I awoke.</l><l n="22"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And I saw in my dream, and, lo, seven ears came up<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>on one stalk, full and good.</l><l n="23">And, lo,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>seven ears, shrivelled, thin, and lashed by the east wind<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>sprung up after them.</l><l n="24">And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the thin ears swallowed the seven<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>good ears. And I told |this| to the magicians, but there was none that could explain<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>its interpretation to me.’</l><l n="25">And Joseph said to Pharaoh,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>‘The dream of Pharaoh is one: God<milestone unit="page" n="68v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>has told Pharaoh what he is doing.</l><l n="26">The seven good cows<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>are seven years, and the seven good ears are seven<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>years: the dream is one.</l><l n="27">And the seven<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>thin and ill cows that came up after them<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>are seven years, and the seven empty ears<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>lashed by the east wind will be seven years of famine.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="28">This is the word which I have spoken to Pharaoh:<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>It has shown to Pharaoh what God is doing.</l><l n="29">Lo, seven<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>years of great plenty are coming in all the land of Egypt.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="30">And seven years of famine will arise after them, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>all the plenty will be forgotten in the land of Egypt, and the<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>famine will consume all the people of the land.</l><l n="31">And<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the plenty will not be known in the land by reason of the famine that will follow,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>for it will be very severe.</l><l n="32">And the doubling of<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Pharaoh’s, as for that, it is because the word is ready before<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>God, and God hastens to do that.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="33">Now let Pharaoh seek out a <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/><supplied reason="lost">man rational and wise, and set him as a superior over the land of Egypt. </supplied></l><l n="34"><supplied reason="lost"> Let Pharaoh do this</supplied><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>, and let him appoint<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>rulers over the land, and take the fifth part<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>over the land of Egypt in the seven years of plenty.</l><l n="35"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And let them gather all the grain of those good years<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>that are coming, and gather the grain<milestone unit="page" n="69r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>under the authority of Pharaoh, let them keep the grain in the cities.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="36">And that food shall be for reserve to the people of the land<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>for the seven years of famine, which will be in the land of Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>that the people of the land may not perish through the famine.’</l><l n="37"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And the words seemed good in the eyes of Pharaoh, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>in the eyes of all his servants.</l><l n="38">And Pharaoh said<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to his servants, ‘Will we find such a man as this is,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>a man in whom there is the inspiration of God?’</l><l n="39">And Pharaoh said<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to Joseph, ‘Since God has let you know about all this,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>there is none so rational and wise as you are.</l><l n="40">Be<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>a superior over my house, and according to your word<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>shall all my people move. Only by the matters of the throne<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>will I be greater than you.’</l><l n="41">And Pharaoh said<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to Joseph, ‘See, I have set you superior over all the land<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of Egypt.’</l><l n="42">And Pharaoh took off his ring<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>from his hand, and put it on Joseph’s hand,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and clothed him in linen clothing, and put a gold chain<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>on his neck.</l><l n="43">And he had him driven<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>in the second chariot which he had, and they cried<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>in front of him to bow the knee and to make him superior over all the land<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of Egypt.</l><l n="44">And Pharaoh said<milestone unit="page" n="69v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to Joseph, ‘I am Pharaoh, and without your authority shall no man lift up<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>his hand or foot to rule in all<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the land of Egypt.’</l><l n="45">And Pharaoh called Joseph’s name<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Zaphenath-Paneah. And he gave him Asenath, daughter<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of Potiphera, priest of On, for a wife. And the<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>fame of Joseph’s rule went out over all the land of Egypt.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="46">And Joseph was thirty years old when he stood before<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Pharaoh, king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from before<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Pharaoh, and passed over all the land of Egypt.</l><l n="47"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And in the seven plenteous years the earth produced<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>by handfuls.</l><l n="48">And he gathered up all<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the grain of the seven years, which were in the land of Egypt, and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and he put the grain in the cities: he put the grain of the city’s fields<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>that were around it inside of it.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="49">And Joseph gathered grain as the sand<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of the sea, in great abundance, until he ceased to number it,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>because it was without number.</l><l n="50">And two sons were born to Joseph<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>before the year of famine came, which Asenath,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>daughter of Potiphera, priest of On, bore to him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="51">And Joseph called the name of the firstborn<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>Manasseh: ‘Because God has made me forget all my affliction,<milestone unit="page" n="70r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and all my father’s house.’</l><l n="52">And the name<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of the second called the Ephraim: ‘Because God has spread me<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>in the land of my affliction.’</l><l n="53">And the seven years<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of plenty, that was <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>seven<anchor xml:id="del001"/>
							<addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>in the land</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> of Egypt, finished.</l><l n="54">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the seven years of famine started to come, as Joseph had said.<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And the famine was in all lands, but in all the land of Egypt<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>there was bread.</l><l n="55">And when all the people of the land of Egypt starved<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>for bread, and the people cried to Pharaoh<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>for bread, and Pharaoh said to all the people<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of Egypt, ‘Go to Joseph. Do what he says to you.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="56">And the famine was over all the face<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of the earth. And Joseph opened all the treasuries in which<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>there was grain, and sold grain to all the people of Egypt.<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And the famine became stronger in all the land of Egypt.</l><l n="57"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And all the people of the earth came to Egypt, to Joseph, to buy<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>grain, because the famine became stronger in all lands.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Reconstructed on the basis of the Hebrew original, H, C, and Gen 41:39–40.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
