<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 20</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Deuteronomy <supplied reason="lost">20</supplied></title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Deut020-P313v-L6_trl" n="6" prev="ADub.III.73.005.019.trl.xml#Deut019-P313v-L6_trl" />
                        <l n="1">When you will go out to battle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            against your enemies, and you will see horses and chariots
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and a people more than you, you shall not be afraid of them, because the help
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of the Lord your God is with you, who brought you out from the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            of Egypt.</l>
                        <l n="2">And it shall be, when you come near to the war,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the priest shall come near and speak to the people.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="3">And he shall say to them, “Hear, oh Israel,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            you are coming near to war against your enemies today.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            Let not your hearts soften. Do not fear and do not panic and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            do not despond before them.</l>
                        <l n="4">Because the Lord your God,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            his divine Presence is that goes with you to fight <supplied
                                reason="lost">for</supplied> you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            against your enemies, to save you.”</l>
                        <l n="5">And the overseers shall speak
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            to the people, saying, “Which is the man who has built
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            a house, and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to his house,
                            lest he die
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            in the battle, and another man dedicate it.</l>
                        <l n="6">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            And which is the man who has planted a vineyard, and, in the same way,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="314r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            has not yet harvested it? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            in the battle, and, in the same way, another man harvest it.</l>
                        <l n="7">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            And which is the man who has betrothed a wife, and has not taken her?
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            another man take her.”</l>
                        <l n="8">And the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            overseers shall continue speaking to the people, and they shall say,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            “Which is the man who fears to kill another |man| and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            is |too| soft-hearted to be killed? Let such a man go and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            return to his house, so he will not melt his brothers’ heart
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            like his heart.”</l>
                        <l n="9">And it shall be,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            when the overseers finish speaking to the people,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            that they shall appoint the superiors of the armies at the head of the
                            people.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="10">When you come near to a city to fight against it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            you shall call to it for peace.</l>
                        <l n="11">And it shall be,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            if it makes to you an answer of peace and opens its gates to you, then
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            it shall be, that all the people that are found in shall be for you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            to pay tribute, and they shall serve you.</l>
                        <l n="12">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            And if it makes no peace with you, but will make war against you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            then you shall oppress it.</l>
                        <l n="13">And when
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            the Lord your God gives it into your hands, you shall slay all its males
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            with the edge of the sword.</l>
                        <l n="14">Just: the women and the infants
                            <milestone unit="page" n="314v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            and the cattle and all that is in the city, all its goods:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            you shall plunder for yourselves. And you shall eat the spoil of your
                            enemies which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            the Lord your God has given you.</l>
                        <l n="15">Thus you shall do to all the cities
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            which are very far from you, which are not of the cities
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            of these kingdoms.</l>
                        <l n="16">But
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            of the cities of these people which the Lord your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            is giving you for an inheritance, you shall not leave any soul
                            alive.</l>
                        <l n="17">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            Because you shall utterly destroy them — the Hittites and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            Amorites, the Canaanites and the Perizzites, the Hivites and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            Jebusites — as the Lord your God has commanded you,</l>
                        <l n="18">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            so that they may not teach you to do like all their repulsive
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            things which they have done to their gods, and so you sin
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            against the Lord your God.</l>
                        <l n="19">When you oppress
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            a city for many days, <addSpan spanTo="#add001" /><emph>to make war
                                against </emph><supplied reason="lost">it</supplied><anchor
                                xml:id="add001" />, to take it, you shall not destroy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            its fruit trees by elevating an axe against them, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            you will eat from it, so you shall not cut them down so that they go
                            from in front of you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            for oppression, because the fruit tree of the field is man’s life.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="20">Only a tree that you know that it is not a tree that gives fruits:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            you shall destroy it and cut it down, and you shall build a fortress
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            against the city that makes war with you, until it falls.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
