<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 45</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 45</title><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Joseph was not able to endure before all them that stood by him,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and he cried, ‘Take away every man from before me.’ And no one stayed<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>with him when Joseph made himself known to his brothers.</l><l n="2">And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>he wept aloud: and the Egyptians<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and the house of Pharaoh heard it.</l><l n="3">And<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Joseph said to his brothers, ‘I am Joseph! Is my father still<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>alive?’ And his brothers were not able to answer him,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>because they were troubled in front of him.</l><l n="4">And Joseph said<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to his brothers, ‘Come near to me, now.’ And they came near. And he said, ‘I am<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Joseph your brother, whom you sold to Egypt.</l><l n="5">And now<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>be not annoyed and may there be no anger in your eyes that you sold<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>me here, because God did send me ahead of you to feed you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="6">For it is two years that the famine has been in<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the land, and it is five more years that there will be no ploughing<milestone unit="page" n="77r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>or harvest.</l><l n="7">And God sent me ahead of you to put<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>for you a remnant on earth and to keep you alive for a great deliverance.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="8">And now, it was not you who sent me here, but<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>God. And he has made me a father to Pharaoh and lord<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of all his house and a ruler over all the land of Egypt.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="9">Hurry, and go up to my father, and say to him, “Thus<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>says your son Joseph, “God has made me lord of all Egypt. Come down to me,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>do not tarry.</l><l n="10">And you shall dwell in the land of Goshen,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and you shall be near to me, you, and your children, and your children’s children,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and your flocks, and your cattle, and all that is yours.</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And I will nourish you there, because there are five more years of famine, lest<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>you and your household and all that is yours will be impoverished.””</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>And, lo, your eyes see, and the eyes of my brother<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Benjamin, that it is my mouth that speaks to you <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>|directly| and not<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>through an interpreter<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>.</l><l n="13">And you shall tell my father<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of all my glory in Egypt and of all that you have seen, and you shall haste<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and bring down my father here.’</l><l n="14">And he fell on<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his brother Benjamin’s neck and wept, and Benjamin<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>wept on his neck.</l><l n="15">And he kissed<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>all his brothers, and wept on them. And after that<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>his brothers talked with him.</l><l n="16">And the<milestone unit="page" n="77v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>rumour was heard in Pharaoh’s house, saying, ‘Joseph’s brothers have come,’<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and it seemed good in Pharaoh’s eyes and in the eyes of<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>his servants.</l><l n="17">And Pharaoh said to Joseph,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>‘Say to your brothers, “Do this: Press your livestock, and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>go, come to the land of Canaan.</l><l n="18">And take<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>your father and your households, and come to me: and let me give<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>you the good of the land of Egypt, and you shall eat<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the goods of the land.</l><l n="19"><seg type="commented" n="#seg002"/>And even if you were to be commanded<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>not to let to carry the grain with wagons:<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg002"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/> but<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>I now command you, do this: Take wagons for yourself<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>from the land of Egypt, for your little ones and for your wives, and take<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>your father, and come.</l><l n="20">And let your eye not pity<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>your vessels, for the good of all the land of Egypt<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>is yours.”’</l><l n="21">And the sons of Israel did so.<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And Joseph gave them wagons, according to the command of Pharaoh, and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>gave them provisions for the way.</l><l n="22">To all of them he gave<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>each man change of clothes, but to Benjamin he gave three hundred<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>pieces of silver, and five changes of clothes.</l><l n="23">And to his father<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>he sent after this manner: ten donkeys carrying |some|<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>of the goods of Egypt, and ten donkeys carrying grain<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and bread and provision for his father for the way.</l><l n="24"><milestone unit="page" n="78r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>So he sent his brothers away, and they went, and he said<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to them, ‘Do not quarrel on the way.’</l><l n="25">And they went up from Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and came to the land of Canaan to Jacob their father.</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="4"/>And they told him, saying, ‘Joseph is still alive,’ and that he<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>rules over all the land of Egypt. And Jacob’s heart was troubled,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>because he did not believe them.</l><l n="27">And they told him<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>all the words of Joseph, which he had spoken to them, and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him. And<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the spirit of Jacob, their father, revived.</l><l n="28">And Israel said,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>‘It will be very good for me! If Joseph, my son,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>is still alive. Let me go and let me see him before I die.’</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 45:12.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 45:19.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
