<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 8</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Deuteronomy 8</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-2-2" n="2" prev="ADub.III.73.005.007.trl.xml#line-2-1" />
                        <l n="1">All the commandments which I command you today
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            you shall be watchful to do, that you may live and multiply
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            and come and inherit the land which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            the Lord swore to your fathers.</l>
                        <l n="2">And you shall remember
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            all the way which the Lord your God made you walk these
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            forty years in the wilderness, to oppress you, to test you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            to know what was in your heart, whether you would keep his commandments
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            or not.</l>
                        <l n="3">And he oppressed you and made you hunger
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and fed you with manna, which you had not known
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and your fathers had not known, to let you know that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            man does not live by bread alone, but
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            a man lives by every word that proceeds out of the mouth of the
                            Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="4">Your clothing did not wear away on you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            and your foot did not become scabbed these forty years.</l>
                        <l n="5" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="5">You shall also know in your mind that, as a man disciplines his
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            son, so the Lord your God disciplines you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="6">And you shall keep the commandments of the Lord your God,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            to walk in his ways and to fear him.</l>
                        <l n="7">Because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            the Lord your God brings you to a good land, a land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            of rivers of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and
                            <milestone unit="page" n="295r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            hills,</l>
                        <l n="8">A land of wheat and barley and vines and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            fig trees and pomegranates, a land of olive oil, and honey,</l>
                        <l n="9">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            A land in which you will eat bread without poverty,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            you will not lack anything in it, a land whose stones are iron,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and from whose hills you may dig copper.</l>
                        <l n="10">And when you have eaten
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and are full, you shall bless the Lord your God for the good
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            land which he has given you.</l>
                        <l n="11">Take heed to yourself, lest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            you forget the service of the Lord your God so as not to keep his commandments
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and his judgments and his statutes which I command you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            today,</l>
                        <l n="12">Lest you eat and are full and build fine houses
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and dwell |there|,</l>
                        <l n="13">And your cattle and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            your flock is multiplied, and your silver and your gold is multiplied, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            all that you have is multiplied,</l>
                        <l n="14">And your heart be proud,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and you forget the service of the Lord your God,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            who brought you out from the land of Egypt, from the reign of
                            slaves,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="15">Who made you walk in the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            great and awesome wilderness of fiery serpents and adders
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            and thirst, because there was no water, who brought out water for you
                            from the diamond
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            rock,</l>
                        <l n="16">Who fed you in the wilderness with manna,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            which your fathers had not known, in order to oppress you and in order
                            to test
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            you, to do good for you in the end,</l>
                        <l n="17">And
                            <milestone unit="page" n="295v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            if you say in your heart, “My power and the strength of my hand made
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            this wealth for me.”</l>
                        <l n="18">Then you shall remember
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            the Lord your God, because it is he that gives you power to
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            gather goods, so as to establish his covenant which he swore
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            to your fathers, as it is this day.</l>
                        <l n="19">And it shall be,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            if you indeed forget the Lord your God and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            go after the service of other gods and serve them and worship them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            I call witness regarding you today that you will surely perish.</l>
                        <l n="20">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            Like the kingdoms that the Lord destroys before you, so will you perish,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            because you would not listen to the voice of the Lord your God.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
