<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Deuteronomy 21</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Deuteronomy <supplied reason="lost">21</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="1">If a dead |man| is found in the land which the Lord your God is giving to you<milestone unit="page" n="315r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to possess, fallen in the field, |and| if it is not known who has killed<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>him,</l><l n="2">Then your elders and your judges shall come out,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and they shall measure to the cities which are around the dead |man|.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="3">And it shall be, the city which is nearest to the dead |man|:<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and the elders of that city shall take a calf of a cattle which<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>has never been used for work and which has not pulled in the yoke.</l><l n="4"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the elders of that city shall bring down the calf<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to a tough valley that is not worked with and it is not sown,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and they shall stab the calf to death there in the valley.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="5">And the priests, sons of Levi, shall come near, because<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>the Lord your God has chosen them to minister to him and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to bless Israel in the name of the Lord, and by their word<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>is every verdict and every illness.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And all the elders of that city that are nearest to the dead |man|<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>shall wash their hands over the calf<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>which was stabbed to death in the valley by the river.</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And they shall begin and say, “Our hands have not spilled<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>this blood, and our eyes have not seen him<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>who killed him.</l><l n="8">Forgive the sin of your people<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Israel, whom you have redeemed, oh Lord, and do not set the guilt of innocent<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>blood in the midst of your people Israel.” And<milestone unit="page" n="315v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the guilt of innocent blood will be forgiven them.</l><l n="9">So shall you drive away<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the guilt of innocent blood from the midst of you, when you will do what is right<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>in the eyes of the Lord.<milestone unit="line" n="4"/><emph>Parashat Ki Teitzei</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="10">When you will go out to war<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>against your enemies, and the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>your God will give them into your hands, and you will take captive their captives,</l><l n="11"/><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="11">And you will see a beautiful woman in captivity, and you will love<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>her and take her to be your wife,</l><l n="12">Then<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>you shall bring her into your house, and she shall make the hair of her head be shaved,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and she shall trim her nails,</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="13">And she shall remove the clothing of her captivity<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>from off her. And she shall live in your house and cry<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>because of her father and her mother a month of days. And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>after that you shall come to her and marry her, and she shall be<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>your wife.</l><l n="14">And it shall be, if you do not love<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>her, you shall let her go into another |man’s| possession, and you shall not sell her<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>for silver. You shall not get profit through her, because<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>you have oppressed her.</l><l n="15">If a man has two<milestone unit="page" n="316r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>wives, one beloved and the other despised, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>they have borne him children, both the beloved and the despised,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and if the firstborn son be of the wife that is despised,</l><l n="16"/><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="16">Then it shall be, when he makes his sons to inherit that which<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>he has, that he shall not be able to make the son of<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the beloved firstborn before the son of the despised,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>|before| the firstborn,</l><l n="17">That he shall recognize the son of the despised,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to give him two portions of all that<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>he has, because he is the first of his strength. The right of the<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>firstbornhood is his.</l><l n="18">If a man has a stubborn<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and rebellious son who does not obey the voice of his father or the voice<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of his mother, and if they discipline him, and if he does not listen to them,</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="19">Then his father and his mother shall hold him<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and bring him out to the elders of his city and to the court of justice<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of his place.</l><l n="20">And they shall say to the elders<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of his city, “This son of ours is stubborn and rebellious,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>he does not listen to our voice, he eats a lot of meat and drinks a lot of wine.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="21">And all the people of his city shall stone him<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>with stones, so that he dies. So shall you drive the evil away<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>from the midst of you, and all Israel shall hear and fear.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="22">And if a man has a sin, a sentence of death, and<milestone unit="page" n="316v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>he is put to death, and you hang him on a tree,</l><l n="23"><milestone unit="line" n="2"/>His body shall not remain all night on the tree, because<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>you shall surely bury him that day: because an accursed of every man is this<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>hanged person by the greatness of his sin which insulted the word of God,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and you shall not defile your land that the Lord your God<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>is giving you as an inheritance.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
