<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 40</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 40</title><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="1"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And it was after these things, the cup-bearer<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of the king of Egypt and his baker sinned against<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>their lord the king of Egypt.</l><l n="2">And Pharaoh<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>was angry at his two officers, at the superior of the cup-bearers,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and at the superior of the bakers.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="3">And he put them under the guard of the house of the superior<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of the executioners, into prison, the place where Joseph<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>was imprisoned.</l><l n="4">And the superior<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of the executioners assigned Joseph with them, and he served<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>them. <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>And they were one year under guard.<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/></l><l n="5">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the two of them dreamed a dream, each his dream, in one night, each man<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>according to the interpretation of his dream, the cup-bearer and the baker<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of the king of Egypt, who were imprisoned<milestone unit="page" n="66r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>in the prison.</l><l n="6">And Joseph came in to them in the morning, and saw<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>them, and, lo, they turned pale.</l><l n="7">And he asked<milestone unit="line" n="3"/><addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>Pharaoh’s</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> officers that were with him under guard in his lord’s house, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>‘Why do your faces look so bad today?’</l><l n="8">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>they said to him, ‘We have dreamed a dream, and there is no interpreter of it.’<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And Joseph said to them, ‘Lo, interpretations are in the hand of God.<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Now, tell me them.’</l><l n="9">And the superior<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>cup-bearer told his dream to Joseph, and<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>said to him, ‘In my dream, lo, a vine was before me,</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="10">And in the vine were three branches. As soon as it budded,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>its blossoms shot forth, and its bunches ripened into grapes.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="11">And Pharaoh’s cup was in my hand. And I took the<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>grapes, and pressed them into Pharaoh’s cup, and<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>I gave the cup into Pharaoh’s hand.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="12">And Joseph said to him, ‘This is the interpretation of it: The three<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>branches are three days.</l><l n="13">Yet within three days<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Pharaoh shall lift up your head, and restore you to your place,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and you shall give Pharaoh’s cup to his hand, after the former<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>manner of life when you were his cup-bearer.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="14">But only remember me <addSpan spanTo="#add002"/><emph>with you</emph><anchor xml:id="add002"/> when it shall be good for you, and<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>practice kindness with me, and make mention of me to Pharaoh,<milestone unit="page" n="66v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and bring me out of this house.</l><l n="15">Because I was stolen<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>away out of the land of the Hebrews, and also here I have done<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>nothing that they should put me into the prison.’</l><l n="16">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the superior of the bakers saw that the interpretation was good, and he<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>said to Joseph, ‘Me too. In my dream: and, lo, I had three white<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>bread baskets on my head.</l><l n="17">And in the<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>highest basket were |some| of all of Pharaoh’s foods, the work of<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>bakers, but the birds ate them out of the basket on my head.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="18">And Joseph answered and said, ‘This<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>is the interpretation thereof: The three baskets are three days.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="19">Yet within three days Pharaoh shall lift your head up from you,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and shall hang you on a tree. And the birds shall eat<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>your flesh from you.’</l><l n="20">And it was<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>on the third day, it was Pharaoh’s birthday, and<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>he made a feast for all his servants. And he lifted up the head of the superior<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of the cup-bearers and of the superior baker<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>among his servants.</l><l n="21">And he<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>restored the superior of the cup-bearers to his position<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of cup-bearership, and he gave the cup<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>in Pharaoh’s hand.</l><l n="22">But he hanged the superior of the<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>bakers, as Joseph had interpreted to them.</l><milestone unit="page" n="67r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="23">And the chief cupbearer did not remember<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>Joseph. And he forgot him.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 40:4.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
