<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Exodus 30</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Exodus 30</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex030-P137r-L14_trl" n="5" prev="ADub.III.73.002.029.trl.xml#Ex029-P137r-L14_trl" />
                        <l n="1">And you shall make an altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            for burning incense. You shall make it of acacia wood.</l>
                        <l n="2">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            A cubit the length of it, and a cubit the breadth of it, it shall be
                            foursquare, and two
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            cubits the height of it, its horns shall be of one piece with it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="3">And you shall overlay it with pure gold, the top of it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and the sides of it all around, and its horns.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            And you shall make a moulding of gold for it all around.</l>
                        <l n="4">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            you shall make two golden rings for it under its moulding, on the two
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            sides of it, you shall make it by its two corners,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and they shall be places for the poles with which to carry it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="5">And you shall make the poles of acacia wood,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            and overlay them with gold.</l>
                        <l n="6">And you shall put
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            it before the veil that is above the ark of the law,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            before the cover that is over the law,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            so that my divine Presence will be ready to appear to you there.</l>
                        <l n="7">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            Aaron shall burn on it fragrant incense every
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            dawn, <supplied reason="lost">when</supplied> he puts in order the
                            lamps, he shall burn
                            <milestone unit="page" n="137v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            it.</l>
                        <l n="8">And when Aaron lights the lamps
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            at twilight, he shall burn it, a perpetual
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            incense before the Lord throughout your generations.</l>
                        <l n="9">You shall not burn
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            on it at other times than these, because it is called
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            alien incense, and do not offer any burnt offering on it, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            you shall not pour a drink offering on it.</l>
                        <l n="10">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            Aaron shall ask for atonement on its horns by pouring once in a year of
                            the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            of the sin offering of the day of atonement: once in the year he shall
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            ask for atonement on it throughout your generations. It is holy of holies
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            to the Lord.’
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            <emph>Parashat Ki Tisa</emph></l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="11">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="12">‘When you count
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            the number of the heads of the sons of Israel, according to their number:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            and each shall give a ransom for his soul to the Lord, when you count
                            them, and there shall be no plague among them, when you count them.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                        <l n="13">Everyone who passes among them that are counted shall give this:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            half a mithqal by the mithqal of the Holy — twenty
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            <emph>gög</emph>s<ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor" /> is one mithqal.
                            A half mithqal: the heave offering to the Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="14">Everyone who passes among them that are counted, from twenty years old
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and upward, shall give the heave offering of the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="15">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="138r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            The rich shall not give more, and the poor shall not give less
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            than half a mithqal, to give the heave offering of the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            to ask for atonement for your souls.</l>
                        <l n="16">And you shall take the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            ransom silver of the children of Israel, and you shall give
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            it for the service of the tent of meeting, and it shall be for a
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            remembrance to the children of Israel before the Lord, to ask for
                            atonement for your souls.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="17">And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="18">‘And you shall make a basin of bronze, and its place also of bronze,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            for washing, and you shall put it between the tent of meeting and the altar,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and you shall put water in it.</l>
                        <l n="19">And Aaron and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            his sons shall wash their hands and their feet there.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="20">When they come to the tent of meeting they shall wash with water,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            and they shall not die — or when they come near to the altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            to serve, to burn offering by fire to the Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="21">And they shall wash their hands and their feet, and they shall not die.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            And it shall be a statute forever to them, to him and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            to his offspring throughout their generations.’</l>
                        <l n="22">And the Lord spoke to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="23">‘And you, take to you the finest spices:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            fragrant musk, five hundred <supplied reason="lost">mithqals</supplied>,
                            fragrant cinnamon, half as much, two
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            hundred and fifty, and fragrant calamus, two hundred and fifty,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="24">And cassia, five hundred by the mithqal of the Holy, and
                            <milestone unit="page" n="138v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            olive oil, a hin.</l>
                        <l n="25">And you shall make of these a holy anointing oil,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            a medicine prepared, the work of an apothecary. It shall be a holy
                            anointing oil.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="26">And you shall anoint the tent of meeting with it and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the ark of the law,</l>
                        <l n="27">And the table and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            all its equipment, and the lampstand and its equipment,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and the altar of incense,</l>
                        <l n="28">And the altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            of burnt offering with all its equipment, and the basin
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and its place.</l>
                        <l n="29">And you shall sanctify them, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            they shall be holy of holies. Anyone who touches them shall be holy.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="30">And you shall anoint Aaron and his sons
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and consecrate them, that they may serve me as priests.</l>
                        <l n="31">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            you shall speak to the children of Israel, saying, “This shall be a holy
                            anointing oil
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            to me throughout your generations.</l>
                        <l n="32">It shall it not be poured on man’s body,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and you shall not make anything else like it in its quantities. It is holy,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            and it shall be holy to you.</l>
                        <l n="33">Anyone who prepares any like it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            or anyone who puts any of it on a foreigner, shall be cut off from his
                            people.”’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="34">And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Take to you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            spices: musk, and willowherb, and galbanum — spices and pure frankincense:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            each shall be separately.</l>
                        <l n="35">And you shall make it incense,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            a medicine, the work of an apothecary, mixed, pure and holy.</l>
                        <l n="36">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            you shall beat some of it very small, and put of it before the law in
                            the tent
                            <milestone unit="page" n="139r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            of meeting, so that my divine Presence will be ready to appear to you there.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            It shall be holy of holies to you.</l>
                        <l n="37">And the incense that you make:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            you shall not make for yourselves in its quantities. It shall be holy to
                            you, for it was made
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            for the service of the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="38">Anyone who will make anything like that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            to smell with it: when he makes it, he will be cut off from his
                            people.’</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Unidentified unit of weight.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
