<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Exodus 29</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Exodus 29</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex029-P134r-L14_trl" n="14"
                            prev="ADub.III.73.002.028.trl.xml#Ex028-P134r-L14_trl" />
                        <l n="1">And this is
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             the thing that you shall do to them to consecrate them, that they may
                            serve
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             me as priests. Take one calf, the young of cattle, and two unblemished
                            rams,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="2">And unleavened bread, and unleavened cakes
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             mixed with oil, and unleavened flans smeared
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             with oil — you shall make them of fine wheat flour.</l>
                        <l n="3">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             And you shall put them into one basket, and bring them in the basket
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             and the calf and the two rams.</l>
                        <l n="4">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="134v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             And you shall bring Aaron and his sons to the door
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             of the tent of meeting and wash them with water.</l>
                        <l n="5">And you shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             the garments and put them on Aaron: the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             shirt, and the robe of the ephod, and the ephod,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             and the breastplate, and you shall gird him with the embroidered |band|
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             of the ephod.</l>
                        <l n="6">And you shall put the turban on his head,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and you shall put the holy crown on the turban.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="7">And you shall take the anointing oil, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             put it on his head, and anoint him.</l>
                        <l n="8">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             And you shall bring near his sons, and you shall put shirts on
                            them.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="9">And you shall gird them with girdles, Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             and his sons, and put the high caps on them.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             And the priesthood shall be theirs for an eternal statute. And you
                            shall ordain
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             Aaron and his sons.</l>
                        <l n="10">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             you shall bring the calf before the tent of meeting, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             Aaron and his sons shall reach out their hands over the head of the
                            calf.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="11">And you shall slaughter the calf before the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             by the door of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="12">And you shall take of the blood of the calf,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             and put it on the horns of the altar with your finger,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             and pour all the blood out at the base of the altar.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="13">And you shall take all the fat that covers the
                            <milestone unit="page" n="135r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             stomach, and the extra of it that is above the liver, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             and burn them on the altar.</l>
                        <l n="14">And you shall burn the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             flesh of the calf, and its skin, and its dung
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             with fire outside the camp. It is a sin offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="15">And you shall take the one ram, and Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and his sons shall reach out their hands over the head of the ram.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="16">And you shall slaughter the ram, and you shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             its blood, and sprinkle it on the altar all around.</l>
                        <l n="17">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             And you shall cut the ram into pieces according to its pieces, and wash
                            its entrails,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             and its legs, and put them on its pieces, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             on its head.</l>
                        <l n="18">And you shall burn the whole
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             ram on the altar. It is a burnt offering to the Lord, it is a pleasing
                            aroma,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             an offering by fire to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="19">And you shall take the second
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             ram, and Aaron and his sons shall reach out their hands over the head
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             of the ram.</l>
                        <l n="20">And you shall slaughter the ram, and you shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of its blood, and put it on the the soft place of the right
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             ear of Aaron, and on the the soft place of the right
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             ear of his sons, and on the thumb of their right
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             hand, and on the great toe of their right
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             foot, and sprinkle the blood on the altar
                            <milestone unit="page" n="135v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             all around.</l>
                        <l n="21">And you shall take of the blood that is on the altar,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it on Aaron, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             on his garments, and on his sons, and on the garments
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             of his sons with him. And he shall be holy, he and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             his garments, <supplied reason="lost">and his sons</supplied>, and his
                            sons’ garments with him.</l>
                        <l n="22">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             And you shall take the fat from the ram and the |fat| tail, and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             fat that covers the stomach, and its extra
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             from the liver, and the two kidneys, and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             fat that is on them, and the right thigh, because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             it is a ram of ordination,</l>
                        <l n="23">And one loaf of bread, and one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             cake of bread with oil, and one flan from the basket
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             of the unleavened bread that is before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="24">And you shall put all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             in the hands of Aaron, and in the hands of his sons;
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             and you shall elevate them for a wave offering before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="25">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             you shall take them from their hands, and burn them on the altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             for a burnt offering, an aroma of acceptance before the Lord. It is an
                            offering by fire
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="26">And you shall take the breast of the ram
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             of Aaron’s ordination, and elevate it for a wave offering before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             the Lord, and it shall be your part.</l>
                        <l n="27">And you shall sanctify
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             the breast of the wave offering, and the thigh of the heave offering,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             which is elevated, and which is separated from the ram of ordination,
                            from what
                            <milestone unit="page" n="136r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             is Aaron’s and from what is his sons’.</l>
                        <l n="28">And it shall be for Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and for his sons as an eternal statute from the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             of Israel, because it is an heave offering. And it shall be an heave
                            offering from the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             of Israel of the sacrifice of their peace offerings: their heave
                            offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="29">And the holy garments of Aaron shall
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             be for his sons after him, to be anointed for
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             high-priesthood and to be ordained in them.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="30">For seven days the priest who is
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             the High Priest from among his sons in his place, who will come to the
                            tent of meeting
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             to serve in the holy place, shall wear them.</l>
                        <l n="31">And you shall take the ram
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             of ordination and boil its flesh in the holy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             place.</l>
                        <l n="32">And Aaron and his sons shall eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             the flesh of the ram, and the bread that is in the basket,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             by the door of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="33">And they shall eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             those things with which the atonement was asked, to ordain
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             them and to sanctify them. And a foreigner shall not eat |of them|,
                            because they are holy.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="34">And if any of the flesh of the ordination or of the bread remains
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             until the morning, then you shall burn the remainder
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             with fire. It shall not be eaten, because it is holy.</l>
                        <l n="35">And you shall do thus to Aaron,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             and to his sons, according to all things which I have commanded you.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             You shall ordain them for seven days,</l>
                        <l n="36">And
                            <milestone unit="page" n="136v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             you shall offer every day a calf for a sin offering for atonement, and
                            you shall sprinkle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             its blood on the altar when you ask for atonement for it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             and you shall anoint it, to sanctify it.</l>
                        <l n="37">Seven
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             days you shall ask for atonement for the altar, and sanctify
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             it, and the alter shall be holy of holies. Anyone who touches the altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             shall be holy.</l>
                        <l n="38">And this is what you shall do on the altar:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             two lambs, one-year-old, for a day, always.</l>
                        <l n="39">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             You shall do the one lamb at dawn, and do the second
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             lamb at twilight.</l>
                        <l n="40">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             a tenth part of an <emph>ephah</emph> of fine flour mingled with
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             the fourth part of a <emph>hin</emph> of beaten olive oil, and the
                            fourth part
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             of a <emph>hin</emph> of wine for a drink offering for the first
                            lamb.</l>
                        <l n="41">And the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             other lamb you shall do at twilight,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             you shall do it according to the offering of the morning, and according
                            to its drink offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             for a pleasing aroma, an offering by fire to the Lord,</l>
                        <l n="42">A continual
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             burnt offering throughout your generations at the door of the tent of
                            meeting before the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             so that my divine Presence will be ready to appear to you there to
                            speak
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             to you there.</l>
                        <l n="43">And my divine Presence will be ready to appear
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             to the children of Israel, and they shall be sanctified by my
                            glory.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                        <l n="44">And I will sanctify the tent of meeting, and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             altar, and I will sanctify Aaron and his sons
                            <milestone unit="page" n="137r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             to serve me as priests.</l>
                        <l n="45">And I will dwell among
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             the children of Israel, and I will be God to them.</l>
                        <l n="46">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             they shall know that I am the Lord their God that brought them out from
                            the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             of Egypt, that I may dwell with my divine Presence among them.
                            <milestone unit="Ex029-P137r-L14_trl" xml:id="line-5-1" n="5"
                                next="ADub.III.73.002.030.trl.xml#Ex030-P137r-L14_trl" />
                             I am the Lord their God.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
