<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 5</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 5</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Lev005-P163r-L9_trl" n="9"
                            prev="ADub.III.73.003.004.trl.xml#Lev004-P163r-L9_trl" />
                        <l n="1">And if a soul
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             sins: and hears the voice of a curse, and is a witness,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             whether he has seen or known of it: if he does not tell of it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             he shall bear his punishment.</l>
                        <l n="2">Or if a soul who touches any
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             unclean thing, whether it be a carcass of an unclean wild animal or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             a carcass of unclean cattle, or a carcass of unclean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             creeping animal, and it is hidden from him, and he had become unclean
                            and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             guilty,</l>
                        <l n="3"><addSpan spanTo="#Lev-005-add001_trl" /><emph>Or if</emph>
                            <supplied reason="lost">he touches</supplied>
                            <emph>the uncleanness of</emph>
                            <supplied reason="lost">a man</supplied>, <emph>of whatever sort</emph>
                            <supplied reason="lost">the uncleanness</supplied>
                            <emph>may be with which</emph>
                            <supplied reason="lost">he becomes unclean, and</supplied>
                            <emph>it is</emph>
                            <supplied reason="lost">hidden from him</supplied><emph>, and then he
                                had come to know and had become </emph><supplied reason="lost"
                                >guilty</supplied>,</l>
                        <l n="4">Or if a soul swears so as to express
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             with his lips to do bad or to do good –
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             whatsoever it be that a man shall express with an oath — and it is
                            hidden
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             from him, and he comes to know of it and he is guilty in one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             of these:</l>
                        <l n="5">And it shall be that when he shall become guilty by one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             of these things that he shall confess that he has sinned in that
                            thing,</l>
                        <l n="6">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="163v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             And he shall bring his guilt offering to the Lord for his sin
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             which he has sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a kid of the
                            goats,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             for a sin offering. And the priest shall ask for atonement for him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             from his sin.</l>
                        <l n="7">And if his hand cannot attain enough for
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             a sheep, he shall bring his guilt offering for having sinned:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, to the Lord, one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             for a sin offering, and one for a burnt offering.</l>
                        <l n="8">And he shall bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             them to the priest, and he shall bring forward that which is for the
                            sin offering first,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             and <supplied reason="lost">wring off</supplied><ref n="1"
                                target="#Lev-005-fn1_trl" type="noteAnchor" /> its head from the
                            point opposite its back of the neck, but
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             shall not separate it.</l>
                        <l n="9">And he shall sprinkle some of the blood of the sin offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             on the side of the altar, and the rest of the blood shall be drained
                            out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             at the base of the altar. It is a sin offering.</l>
                        <l n="10">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             he shall make the second one a burnt offering, according to the
                            |required| manner. And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             the priest shall ask for atonement for him from his sin which he has
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.</l>
                        <l n="11">And if his hand cannot attain
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             enough for two turtledoves, or two young pigeons,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             he shall bring as his offering for having sinned the tenth
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             part of an <emph>ephah</emph> of fine flour for a sin offering. He
                            shall put no
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             oil on it and he shall put no frankincense on it, because it is a sin
                            offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                        <l n="12">And he shall bring it to the priest, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             the priest shall take a full handful of it, his incense, and
                            <milestone unit="page" n="164r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             burn it on the altar, next to the offerings by fire of the Lord. It is
                            a sin offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="13">And the priest shall ask for atonement for him, for his sin
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             that he has sinned in one of these, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             his sin will be forgiven. And it shall be the priest’s, as a grain
                            offering.”’</l>
                        <l n="14">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="15">‘If a soul
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             commits a trespass, and sins by mistake among the holy things
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             of the Lord: he shall bring for his guilt offering to the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             an unblemished ram from the flock with your valuation by mithqals of
                            silver,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             by the mithqal of the Holy, for a guilt offering.</l>
                        <l n="16">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             for what he sinned from the Holy he shall pay and add to it the fifth
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             part of it and give it to the priest.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             And the priest shall ask for atonement for him with the ram
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             of the guilt offering, and his sin will be forgiven.</l>
                        <l n="17">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             if a soul who sins, commits one of the commandments
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             of the Lord that are not to be done, and did not know and became
                            guilty,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             he shall bear his punishment.</l>
                        <l n="18">And he shall bring an unblemished ram
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             from the flock with your valuation for a guilt offering, to the priest,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             and the priest shall ask for atonement for the mistake
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             that he made and knew it not, and his sin will be forgiven.</l>
                        <l n="19">It is a guilt
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             offering: he has certainly become guilty to the Lord.’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="20">And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="21">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="164v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             ‘If a soul sins, and commits a trespass against the Lord, and deceives
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             his friend in |a matter of| deposit or |something| set in hand or by
                            robbery,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             or if he has oppressed his friend,</l>
                        <l n="22">Or has found
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             something lost and lies about it and swears to a falsehood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             — for one of any of these that a man does to sin by it:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="23">And it shall be, if he has sinned and is guilty, he shall return
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             the spoil that he robbed or what he got by oppression
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             or the deposit that was deposited with him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             or the lost thing that he found,</l>
                        <l n="24">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             Or anything about which he has sworn to a falsehood, and he
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             shall pay it in full and shall add to it a fifth of it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             he shall give it to him to whom it belongs on the day of his being
                            guilty.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="25">And he shall bring his guilt offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             to the Lord: an unblemished ram from the flock with your valuation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             for a guilt offering, to the priest.</l>
                        <l n="26">And the priest shall ask for atonement
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             for him before the Lord, and his sin will be forgiven
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             for any one out of all that he has done to become guilty through
                            it.’</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="Lev-005-fn1_trl" type="footnote">K: <emph>shave</emph>; a
                            mistranslation, cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he"
                                style="unicode-bidi: embed;">וּמָלַ֧ק </foreign>
                             ‘wring off’.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
