<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 7</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 7</title><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And the Lord said to Noah, ‘Come you,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and all your household into the ship, for I have seen you as righteous<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>before me in this generation.</l><l n="2">Of every clean animals<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>take with you by sevens, male and his female, and of the<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>animals that are not clean by two, the male and his female.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="3">Also of birds of the skies by sevens,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the male and the female, to keep their offspring alive on the face<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of all the earth.</l><l n="4">Because yet seven days, and I will cause it to rain<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>on the earth forty days and forty nights, and I will destroy<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>every living thing that I have created from off the face<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of all the earth.’</l><l n="5">And Noah did everything as the<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Lord commanded him.</l><l n="6">And Noah was six hundred years old,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and the flood of waters was on the earth.</l><l n="7">And<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Noah came in, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>with him, into the ship, |to escape| from before the waters of the flood.</l><milestone unit="page" n="10r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="8"><supplied reason="lost">Of clean animals, and of animals that are not</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><supplied reason="lost">clean, and of birds, and</supplied> everything that creeps on the ground:</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="9">They went into the ship by twos to Noah,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>male and his female, as God had commanded Noah.</l><l n="10">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>it was after seven days that the waters of the flood were<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>on the earth.</l><l n="11">In the six hundredth year of Noah’s life,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>in the second month, the seventeenth day of the month,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>on that day all the springs <supplied reason="lost">of</supplied> the great deep broke up,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and the windows of the skies were opened.</l><l n="12">And<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>the rain was on the earth forty days and forty nights.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>In the very same day came Noah, and <supplied reason="lost">Shem</supplied>,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah’s wife, and the <supplied reason="lost">three</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>wives of his sons with them, to the ship.</l><l n="14"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>They, and every wild animal according to its kind, and all the livestock according to their kind,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and every creeping animal that creeps on the earth, according to its kind,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and every bird, according to its kind, every winged bird.</l><l n="15"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And they came to Noah to the ship, two by two of all<milestone unit="line" n="18"/><supplied reason="lost">flesh</supplied> in which is the breath of life.</l><l n="16">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>those that came, male and female of all flesh, came <supplied reason="lost">as</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>God <supplied reason="lost">had commanded</supplied> him. And the Lord shut it above him.</l><l n="17"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><supplied reason="lost">And</supplied> the flood was forty days on the earth,<milestone unit="page" n="10v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and the waters <supplied reason="lost">increased</supplied>, and raised the ship, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>it was raised above the earth.</l><l n="18">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the waters increased, and multiplied greatly on the earth,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and the ship was on the face of the waters.</l><l n="19"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And the waters increased very greatly on the earth,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and they covered all the high mountains that were under all the skies.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="20">Fifteen cubits above, the waters increased<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>as they covered the mountains.</l><l n="21">And all flesh expired<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>that moved on the earth: among the birds and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>among the livestock and among the wild animals and among all the creeping animals that creep<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>on the earth and all the man:</l><l n="22">Everything<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>that had the breath of life in its nostrils of all that was in the dry land,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>died.</l><l n="23">And he destroyed every nation<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>which was on the face of the earth, both man and livestock<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and creeping animals and birds of the skies, and they were destroyed<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>from the earth. And only Noah was left, and those who were with him in the ship.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="24">And the waters increased on the earth<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>a hundred and fifty days.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
