<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 50</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 50</title><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="1">And Joseph fell on his father’s face,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and wept over him, and kissed him.</l><l n="2">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Joseph commanded his servants, the physicians, to embalm<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his father. And the physicians embalmed Israel.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="3">And forty days were filled for him, because this is how<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the days of those who are embalmed are filled. And the Egyptians wept for him<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>seventy days.</l><l n="4">And the days of his weeping passed,<milestone unit="page" n="85v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and Joseph spoke to the house of Pharaoh, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘If now I have found favour in your eyes, speak<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>now in the ears of Pharaoh, saying,</l><l n="5">“My father<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>made me swear, saying, “Lo, I will die. In my grave,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>which I have dug for me in the land of Canaan: you shall bury me there.”<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And now, let me go now, and let me bury my father,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and I will come back.”’</l><l n="6">And Pharaoh said, ‘Go and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>bury your father as he had you swear.’</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And Joseph went to bury his father, and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>all the servants of Pharaoh went with him, the elders of his house, and all the elders<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of the land of Egypt,</l><l n="8">And all the people of Joseph’s house, and his brothers,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and the people of his father’s house. Only <supplied reason="lost">their little ones and</supplied> their flocks and their<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>cattle they left in the land of Goshen.</l><l n="9">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>both chariots and horsemen went with him. And it was a very great camp.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="10">And they came to the threshing-floor of<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the place which is called Atad, which is at the ford of Jordan, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>there they cried with a great and very strong cry. And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>he made a mourning for his father for seven days.</l><l n="11">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the inhabitants of the land of Canaan saw the mourning in<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the place which is called <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>Goren the Atad<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>, and they said, ‘This is a strong<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>mourning to the Egyptians.’ Therefore the name of it was called Abel-Mizraim,<milestone unit="page" n="86r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>which is at the ford of Jordan.</l><l n="12">And his sons did<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to him as he had commanded them.</l><l n="13">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>his sons carried him to the land of Canaan, and buried<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>him in the cave of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham bought<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>with the field for a possession of a sepulchre from Ephron the Hittite,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>before Mamre.</l><l n="14">And Joseph returned to Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>he, and his brothers, and all that went with him<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to bury his father, after he had buried his father.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="15">And Joseph’s brothers saw that their father was dead,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and they said, ‘Joseph will perhaps be hostile to us,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and will certainly pay back to us all the evil which we payed<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to him.’</l><l n="16">And they sent a message to Joseph, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>‘Your father had command before he died:</l><l n="17">“So shall you say<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to Joseph, “Forgive now, we pray you, the trespass of your brothers<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and their sin, because they payed you evil.”” And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>now, forgive the trespass of the servants of the God of your father.’<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And Joseph wept when they spoke to him.</l><l n="18">And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his brothers also went and fell down before him,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and they said, ‘Lo, we are your servants.’</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Joseph said to them, ‘Do not fear, because am I in the place of God?</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="20">And you thought bad against me.<milestone unit="page" n="86v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>God thought for good: to make it as it is this day, to save<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>many people alive.</l><l n="21">And now, do not fear: I<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>will nourish you and your little ones.’ And he comforted them, and spoke<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>to their hearts.</l><l n="22">And Joseph dwelt in Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>he and the people of his father’s house. And Joseph lived a hundred<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and ten years.</l><l n="23">And Joseph saw Ephraim’s children<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of the third generation. Also the children of Machir, son of Manasseh,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>were brought up on Joseph’s knees.</l><l n="24"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And Joseph said to his brothers, ‘I will die. And God<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>will surely remember you and bring you out of this land<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>to the land which he swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="25">And Joseph made the sons of Israel swear,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>saying, ‘God will surely remember you, and you shall take<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>my bones from here.’</l><l n="26">And Joseph died,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>a hundred and ten |years| old. And they embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>in Egypt.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/><emph>With the help of Him who declares the end from the beginning</emph><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><emph>the peshatim of the Book of Genesis are finished.</emph><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><emph>And now I start to write the peshatim of the Book of Exodus</emph><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><emph>with the help of Him who is praised by all the souls.</emph><milestone unit="page" n="87r"/></l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: <emph>Goren ol Atad</emph>, a partial translation of Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">אֶת־הָאֵבֶל בְּגֹרֶן הָֽאָטָד </foreign>‘on the threshing-floor of Atad’.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
