<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Exodus 12</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Exodus 12</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex012-P104r-L4_trl" n="4"
                            prev="ADub.III.73.002.011.trl.xml#Ex011-P104r-L4_trl" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             in the land of Egypt, saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">‘This month
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             is the beginning of months to you. It is the first
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             month of the year for you.</l>
                        <l n="3">Speak to all the congregation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             of Israel, saying, “In the tenth day of this month
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             they shall take to them every man a sheep, according to the house of
                            their fathers,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             a sheep for a house.</l>
                        <l n="4">And if the people of the house be fewer
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             than those who would eat the sheep, then he
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             and his neighbour that is close to his house shall take according to
                            the number of souls,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             according to every person’s eating you shall appoint yourself for the
                            lamb.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="5">Your sheep shall be unblemished male, a one-year-old young;
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             you shall take it from the sheep or from the goats.</l>
                        <l n="6">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             And you shall keep it until the fourteenth day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of the same month. And the whole assembly of the congregation of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             Israel shall slaughter it at twilight.</l>
                        <l n="7">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             they shall take of the blood, and put it on the two side posts
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             and on the upper door post,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             on the houses in which they shall eat it.</l>
                        <l n="8">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="104v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             And they shall eat the flesh in this night, they shall eat it roasted
                            in fire
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             with unleavened bread |on| bitter herbs.</l>
                        <l n="9">Do not eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            <emph>jaḥny</emph><ref n="1" target="#Ex-012-fn1_trl" type="noteAnchor"
                             /> or boiled in water,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             but roasted in fire: its head with its knees, and with the entrails.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             (10) And you shall let nothing of it remain until the morning, and that
                            which remains of it
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             until the morning you shall burn in fire.</l>
                        <l n="11">And thus shall you eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             it: your hips shall be girded, your shoes shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             on your feet, and your staff in your hand; and you shall eat it
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             in haste. It is the Lord’s Passover.</l>
                        <l n="12">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             And my command will pass through the land of Egypt this night,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             and will slay all the firstborn in the land of Egypt,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             both man and beast, and I will do punishments against all the gods of
                            Egypt.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             I am the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="13">And the blood shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             to you for a sign on the houses where you are, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             I will see the blood, and I will have mercy on you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             and the plague will not be on you to destroy you when I slay
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             in the land of Egypt.</l>
                        <l n="14">And this day shall be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             to you for a memorial, and you shall keep it a feast to the Lord
                            throughout your generations,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             as an eternal statute, you shall keep it as a feast.</l>
                        <l n="15">Seven days
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             shall you eat unleavened bread, but before the first day you shall
                            remove
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             leaven from your houses. Because anyone who eats leavened |bread| from
                            <milestone unit="page" n="105r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             the first day until the seventh day, that soul will be cut off
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             from Israel.</l>
                        <l n="16">And there shall be for you a holy convocation on the first day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             and a holy convocation on the seventh day.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             No work shall be done on them. Just what is eaten by every man: that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             alone shall be done for you.</l>
                        <l n="17">And you shall observe the unleavened
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             bread, because in this very day I have brought your hosts
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             out from the land of Egypt. And you shall observe this day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             throughout your generations as an eternal statute.</l>
                        <l n="18">In the first
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             month, on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             you shall eat unleavened bread, until the twenty-first day of the
                            month,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             in the evening.</l>
                        <l n="19">Seven days leaven shall not be found in your
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             houses, because anyone who eats that which is leavened, that soul shall
                            be cut off
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             from the congregation of Israel, both a stranger and a <supplied
                                reason="lost">native</supplied><ref n="2" target="#Ex-012-fn2_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> of that land.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="20">You shall eat nothing leavened. In all your dwellings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             you shall eat unleavened bread.’</l>
                        <l n="21">And Moses called for all the elders
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             of Israel, and said to them, ‘Pull out and take yourself
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             a sheep according to your families, and slay the Passover
                            sacrifice.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="22">And you shall take an aspergillum bunch and dip it in the blood
                            that is in the vessel,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             and touch the lintel and the two side posts
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             with some of the blood that is in the vessel. And you shall not go out
                            at the door
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             of the house until the morning.</l>
                        <l n="23">For the command of the Lord <supplied reason="lost"
                                >will</supplied> pass through to slay
                            <milestone unit="page" n="105v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             Egypt, and it shall see the blood on the lintel,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and on the two side posts, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             the Lord will have mercy on the door, and will not allow the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             destroyer to come in to your houses to slay.</l>
                        <l n="24">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             you shall observe this word for a statute to you and to your children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             forever.</l>
                        <l n="25">And it shall be, when you come to the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             which the Lord will<ref n="3" target="#Ex-012-fn3_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> give you as he has spoken, that you shall keep
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             this service.</l>
                        <l n="26">And it shall be, that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             your sons will say to you, “What is this service for you?”</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="27">And you shall say, “It is the sacrifice of the offering of the
                            Passover
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             to the Lord who had mercy on the houses of the children of Israel
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             in Egypt, when he slew Egypt, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             saved our houses.”’ And the people bowed down and worshiped.</l>
                        <l n="28">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             And the children of Israel went away and did as the Lord had commanded
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             Moses and Aaron. They did so.</l>
                        <l n="29">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             it was at midnight, and the Lord slew all the firstborn in the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             of Egypt, from the firstborn of Pharaoh that sat on his throne
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             to the firstborn of the captive that was in the prison,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             and all the firstborn of the livestock.</l>
                        <l n="30">And Pharaoh rose up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             in the night, he, and all his servants, and all the Egyptians, and
                            there was a great
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             cry in Egypt, because there was not a house where there was not one
                            <milestone unit="page" n="106r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             dead.</l>
                        <l n="31">And Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             by night, and said, ‘Rise up, and go out from among my people,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             both you and the children of Israel. And go, serve the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             as you have said.</l>
                        <l n="32">Take your sheep also,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             your cattle, as you have said, and go and bless
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             me as well.’</l>
                        <l n="33">And the people of Egypt became forceful on the people
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             to hurry to drive them out from the land, because they said,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             ‘We are all dead.’</l>
                        <l n="34">And the people lifted and placed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             their dough on their shoulders before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             it leavened, their leavening vessels being
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             bound up in their bedsheets.</l>
                        <l n="35">And the children of Israel
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             did according to the word of Moses, and they borrowed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             from the Egyptians vessels of silver and vessels of gold and
                            clothing.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="36">And the Lord gave the people’s favour
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             in the eyes of the people of Egypt, so that they lent
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             to them. And they plundered Egypt.</l>
                        <l n="37">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             the children of Israel journeyed from Rameses to Succoth.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             The young men, besides children: six times a hundred thousand on
                            foot.</l>
                        <l n="38">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             also a wild multitude went up with them, and sheep, and cattle,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             a very strong livestock.</l>
                        <l n="39">And they baked
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             unleavened dough which they brought out of Egypt: cakes of unleavened
                            bread, because it was not leavened,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="106v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             because they were driven out of Egypt and could not delay, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             they also had not prepared provisions for themselves.</l>
                        <l n="40">And the stay
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             of the children of Israel that they stayed in Egypt, was four hundred
                            years and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             thirty years.</l>
                        <l n="41">And it was in the course of the four hundred and thirty
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             years, and it was on the very same day that all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             the hosts of the Lord went out from the land of Egypt.</l>
                        <l n="42">It is a night
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             to be observed for the Lord for bringing them out from the land of
                            Egypt. This is this night
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             to be observed for the Lord by all the children of Israel throughout
                            their generations,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            <seg type="commented" corresp="#Ex-012-seg001_trl" />for taking them out
                            even from this exile<anchor type="commented" xml:id="Ex-012-seg001_trl"
                                 /><ref n="4" target="#Ex-012-fn4_trl" type="noteAnchor" />.</l>
                        <l n="43">And the Lord said
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             to Moses and Aaron, ‘This is the statute of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             Passover: no foreigner shall eat of it.</l>
                        <l n="44">And every man’s servant
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             that is bought for silver, if you have circumcised him, then
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             he shall eat thereof.</l>
                        <l n="45">A settler and an hired servant shall not eat thereof.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="46">It shall be eaten in one house, you shall not bring out any of the
                            flesh
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             outside of the house, and you shall not break a bone of it.</l>
                        <l n="47">All
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             the congregation of Israel shall do it.</l>
                        <l n="48">And if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             a stranger shall live with you, and shall want to do the Passover
                            sacrifice to the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             it is needed to let him be circumcised, every male, and then
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             he may come near to do it, and he shall be as one of the <supplied
                                reason="lost">native</supplied><ref n="5" target="#Ex-012-fn5_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> of the land. But no
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             uncircumcised person shall eat of it.</l>
                        <l n="49">One teaching shall be to the <supplied reason="lost"
                                >native</supplied><ref n="6" target="#Ex-012-fn6_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" />,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             and to the stranger who lives among you.’</l>
                        <l n="50">
                            <milestone unit="page" n="107r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             And all the children of Israel did as the Lord commanded
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             Moses and Aaron, so did they.</l>
                        <l n="51">And it was
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             the very same day: the Lord brought out the children
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Ex012-P107r-L4_trl" n="4"
                                next="ADub.III.73.002.013.trl.xml#Ex013-P107r-L4_trl" />
                             of Israel from the land of Egypt with their hosts.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-012-fn1_trl" type="footnote">A name of a meat dish; cf.
                            Mam.Kipch. <emph>jaḫny</emph> ‘étuvée de viande’ (A. Zajączkowski 1958:
                            23).</note>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-012-fn2_trl" type="footnote">K: ‘poor’; a scribal error,
                            cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">וּבְאֶזְרַח </foreign>
                             ‘or a native’; cf. Exo 12:48, Exo 12:49, Lev 16:29, and Lev
                            17:15.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-012-fn3_trl" type="footnote">K: ‘would’; a scribal error,
                            cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">יִתֵּן </foreign>
                             ‘will give’.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-012-fn4_trl" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to
                            Exo 12:42.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-012-fn5_trl" type="footnote">K: ‘poor’; a scribal error,
                            cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">כְּאֶזְרַח </foreign>
                             ‘as a native’; cf. also Exo 12:19, Exo 12:49, Lev 16:29, and Lev
                            17:15.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Ex-012-fn6_trl" type="footnote">K: ‘poor’; a scribal error,
                            cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">לָֽאֶזְרָח </foreign>
                             ‘to a native’; cf. also Exo 12:19, Exo 12:48, Lev 16:29, and Lev
                            17:15.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
