<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 9</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 9</title><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="1">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>God <supplied reason="lost">blessed</supplied> Noah and his sons, and said<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to <supplied reason="lost">them</supplied>, ‘Spread, and multiply, and fill the earth.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="2">And the fear of you and the dread of you will be on every<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>wild animal of the earth, and on every bird <supplied reason="lost">of</supplied> the skie<supplied reason="lost">s</supplied>,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>on all that moves on the earth, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>on all the <supplied reason="lost">fishes</supplied> of the sea. They are <supplied reason="lost">given</supplied> into your rule.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="3">Every moving thing that lives shall be for <supplied reason="lost">food</supplied> for you;<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>I have given everything to you like the greenness of plants.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="4">Except you shall not eat flesh with its life: its blood.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="5">And except I will require your blood, for you lives.<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>I will require for it from the <supplied reason="lost">hand</supplied> of every wild animal and from the hand of a man.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>I will require for a man’s life from the hand of each man’s <supplied reason="lost">brother</supplied>.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>One who sheds man’s blood: his blood will be shed by another man,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>because God created man in the image of angels.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="7">And you, spread, and multiply,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>multiply greatly on the earth and multiply in it.’</l><l n="8">And God said<milestone unit="page" n="12v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to Noah, and to his sons with <supplied reason="lost">him, saying</supplied>,</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="9">‘And I, lo, I establish my <supplied reason="lost">covenant with</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="3"/>you, and with your offspring after you.</l><l n="10">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>with every living creature that is with you, the birds, the <supplied reason="lost">livestock, and every</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>wild animal of the earth with you that goes out of the ark,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>with every wild animal of the earth.</l><l n="11">And I will establish<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>my covenant with you that never again shall all flesh be killed<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>by the waters of the flood, and never again shall there be waters of flood<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to destroy the earth’.</l><l n="12">And God said, ‘This is the sign<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of the covenant that I make between me and you and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>every living creature that is with you, for all generations of the world.</l><l n="13"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>I have set my rainbow in the cloud, and it shall be a sign of the covenant<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>between me and the earth.</l><l n="14">And it shall be, when I bring a<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>cloud over the earth, that the rainbow will be seen in the cloud:</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="15">And I will remember my covenant, which is between me and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>you and every living creature of all flesh. And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the waters shall never again become a flood to destroy all flesh.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="16">And the rainbow shall be in the cloud, and I will look on it<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to remember the everlasting covenant between God and every<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>living creature of all flesh that is on the earth.’</l><l n="17"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And God said to Noah, ‘This is the sign of the covenant, which I have established<milestone unit="page" n="13r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><supplied reason="lost">between me and all flesh that is on the earth.’</supplied></l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="18">And the sons of Noah who came out<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>from the ship were Shem, and Ham, and Japheth. And Ham was the father of <supplied reason="lost">Canaan</supplied>.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="19">These three are the sons of Noah, and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>all the people of the earth spread <supplied reason="lost">from these</supplied>.</l><l n="20">And Noah began <supplied reason="lost">to be</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>a man working the ground, and he planted a vineyard.</l><l n="21"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>He drank of the wine, and was drunk, and he was uncovered in the middle of<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>his tent.</l><l n="22">And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw <supplied reason="lost">the</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>nakedness of his father, and told his two brothers outside.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="23">And Shem and Japheth took a sheet,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and put it on both their shoulders, and went<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>backward, and covered the nakedness of their own father.<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>And their faces were backward, and they did not see their <supplied reason="lost">own</supplied> father’s nakedness.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="24">And Noah woke up <supplied reason="lost">from</supplied> the dream<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of his drunkenness of wine, and knew what his<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>younger son had done <supplied reason="lost">to him</supplied>.</l><l n="25">And he said,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>‘Canaan is <supplied reason="lost">cursed</supplied>: he shall be a servant of servants to his brothers.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="26">And he said, ‘Praised be the Lord God <supplied reason="lost">of</supplied> Shem,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and may Canaan be a servant to them.</l><l n="27">May God widen<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Japheth, and the divine Presence of God shall dwell <supplied reason="lost">in</supplied> the tents<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of Shem, and may Canaan be a servant to them.’</l><l n="28">And<milestone unit="page" n="13v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years.</l><l n="29"><milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he died.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
