<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 26</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Leviticus 26</supplied><ref n="1"
                                target="#Lev-026-fn1_trl" type="noteAnchor" /></title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="1">If you walk by my statutes,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and if you keep my commandments and do them:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="2">Then I will give you your rains in their time and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             the land will give its crop, and the tree of the field will give its
                            fruit.</l>
                        <l n="3">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             And your threshing shall reach to the gathering |time|, and the
                            gathering shall reach
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             to the sowing |time|: and you will eat your bread to the full, and you
                            will dwell
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             in your land safely.</l>
                        <l n="4"><addSpan spanTo="#Lev-026-add001_trl" />2nd<anchor type="addSpan"
                                xml:id="Lev-026-add001_trl" /> And you will chase
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             your enemies, and they will fall before you by the sword.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="5"><addSpan spanTo="#Lev-026-add002_trl" />1st<anchor type="addSpan"
                                xml:id="Lev-026-add002_trl" /> And I will give peace in the land,
                            and you shall lie down, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             there will be no one making you afraid, and I will cut off evil wild
                            animals
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             out of the land, and a sword will not pass through your land.<anchor
                                type="commented" xml:id="Lev-026-seg001_trl" /><ref n="2"
                                target="#Lev-026-fn2_trl" type="noteAnchor" /></l>
                        <l n="6">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             five of you will chase a hundred, and a hundred of you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             will chase ten thousand, and your enemies will fall before you by the
                            sword.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="7">And I will turn to you, and I will make you spread, and
                            <milestone unit="page" n="203v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             I will multiply you, and I will establish my covenant with you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="8">And you will eat the old getting older, and you will take out the
                            old
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             before the new.</l>
                        <l n="9">And I will set my dwelling
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             place of my divine Presence among you, and my will won’t abhor you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="10">And I will walk among you, and I will be a God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             to you, and you will be a people to me.</l>
                        <l n="11">I
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             am the Lord your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             from being servants to them, and I have broken the beams of your yoke,
                            and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             I made you walk after I had made you keep your head proud.</l>
                        <l n="12">But if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             you do not listen to my word and not do all these commandments,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="13">And if you despise my statutes,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             or if your soul abhors my judgments, so as not to do
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             all my commandments, to break my covenant:</l>
                        <l n="14">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             I, too, I will do this to you: I will even appoint over you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             terror, cold disease and fever
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             that make eyes dim and cause suffering of heart,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             and you will sow your seed in vain, for your enemies will eat it.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="15">And I will set my wrath against you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             and you will die before your enemies, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             your enemies will reign over you, and you will flee even if there is
                            none who pursues
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             you.</l>
                        <l n="16">And if you do not listen to me even after these, then
                            <milestone unit="page" n="204r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             I will discipline you seven times more for your sins.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="17">And I will break the greatness of your power, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             I will make your heavens as iron, and your earth
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             as copper.</l>
                        <l n="18">And your strength will come to its end in vain, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             your land will not give its crop, and the tree of the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             will not give its fruits.</l>
                        <l n="19">And if you walk with me
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             unwittingly, and you will not be willing to listen to my word,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             I will bring seven times more punishments on you, according to your
                            sins.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="20">And I will send the wild animals of the fields on you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             and they will bereave you, and they will deplete your cattle,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             and they will make you few in number, and your roads will be
                            desolated.</l>
                        <l n="21">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             if you are not disciplined before me by these things, and if you walk
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             with me unwittingly,</l>
                        <l n="22">Then I will also walk
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             with you unwittingly, and will punish you, I too,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             seven times for your sins.</l>
                        <l n="23">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             I will bring a sword over you that shall bring the vengeance of my
                            covenant. And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             if you are gathered to your cities, I will send the pestilence among
                            you, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             you shall be given to the hand of the enemy.</l>
                        <l n="24">And when I break
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             the strength of your bread, then ten women shall bake
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             your bread in one oven, and they shall give back your bread by weight,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             and you will eat and not be full.</l>
                        <l n="25">And if,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="204v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             with this, you do not listen to me, and you will walk with me
                            unwittingly,</l>
                        <l n="26">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             Then I will walk with you with the fury of destiny, and I will
                            discipline you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             I also, seven times for your sins.</l>
                        <l n="27">And you will eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             the flesh of your sons, and you will eat the flesh of your
                            daughters.</l>
                        <l n="28">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             And I will destroy your hills, and I will cut off your sunny
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             images, and I will cast your carcasses on the carcasses
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             of your vanities, and my soul will abhor you.</l>
                        <l n="29">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             I will make your cities desolate, and I will bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             your sanctuaries to desolation, and I will not accept your pleasing
                            aroma.</l>
                        <l n="30">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             And I will desolate the land, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             your enemies who dwell in it will be devastated at it.</l>
                        <l n="31">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             I will scatter you among the kingdoms, and I will draw out a sword
                            after you,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             and your land will become desolate, and your cities will become
                            deserted.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                        <l n="32">Then the land shall cease its Sabbaths,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            <seg type="commented" corresp="#Lev-026-seg002_trl" />that is the
                            remission, in all the days of desolation, and you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             will be in your enemies’ land. Then, because of the desolation,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             the land will keep the Sabbath and will cease the remissions that are
                            called Sabbaths,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             which were not kept in all the days of kingdom, as it is written
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             in the Torah.<anchor type="commented" xml:id="Lev-026-seg002_trl"
                                 /><ref n="3" target="#Lev-026-fn3_trl" type="noteAnchor" /></l>
                        <l n="33">All the days of desolation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             it will keep the Sabbath, the |amount| that it did not keep on your
                            Sabbaths when you lived
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             on it.</l>
                        <l n="34">And those among you who remain:
                            <milestone unit="page" n="205r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             I will bring fear in their hearts in the lands of their enemies,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and the sound of a falling leaf will chase them, and they will flee
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             like the flight from a sword, and they will fall, and there will be no
                            one pursuing.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="35">And they will stumble, each over his brother, as in front of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             a sword, and there is no one pursuing, and you will have no
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             stopover before your enemies.</l>
                        <l n="36">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             you will perish among the kingdoms, and the land of your enemies will
                            consume you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="37">And those of you who remain will rot
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             for their iniquity in your enemies’ lands, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             also for the iniquities of their fathers — <seg type="commented"
                                corresp="#Lev-026-seg003_trl" />because there are such
                                iniquities<anchor type="commented" xml:id="Lev-026-seg003_trl"
                                 /><ref n="4" target="#Lev-026-fn4_trl" type="noteAnchor" /> —
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             with them they will rot.</l>
                        <l n="38">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             And they will confess their iniquity and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             iniquity of their fathers for their trespass which they trespassed
                            against me, and also that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             they have walked with me unwittingly.</l>
                        <l n="39">And I, I also,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             will walk with them unwittingly, and I will bring them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             into the land of their enemies. And then their
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             uncircumcised hearts will despond, and then they will fulfil
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             their own iniquity.</l>
                        <l n="40">And I will remember
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             my covenant that I made with Jacob, and also my covenant
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             that I made with Isaac, and I will also remember my covenant that I
                            made
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             with Abraham, and I will remember the land.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="205v" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="41">And the land will be left by them and it will fulfil its Sabbaths
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             while it is desolate from them, and they will accept their own
                            iniquities:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             because they despised my judgments, and because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             their soul abhorred my statutes.</l>
                        <l n="42">And I will even do to them this too:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             when they are in the land of their enemies, I will not leave
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             them completely in exile, and I will not abhor them, to destroy them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and to break my covenant with them, because I am the Lord their
                            God.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="43">And I will remember for them the covenant of the first ones,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             whom I brought out from the land of Egypt in the sight of the kingdoms,
                            to be
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             God to them. I am the Lord.”’</l>
                        <l n="44">These are the statutes and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             judgments and teachings, which the Lord gave between him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             and the children of Israel on Mount Sinai by the prophecy
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Lev026-P205v-L13_trl" n="13"
                                next="ADub.III.73.003.027.trl.xml#Lev027-P205v-L13_trl" />
                             of Moses.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="Lev-026-fn1_trl" type="footnote">K: Lev 26:1–2 is copied as
                            Lev 25:56–57; a scribal error.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Lev-026-fn2_trl" type="footnote">The order of these two verses
                            was corrected by the copyist.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Lev-026-fn3_trl" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to
                            Lev 26:34.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Lev-026-fn4_trl" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to
                            Lev 26:39.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
