<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 47</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 47</title><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="1">And Joseph came and told Pharaoh, and said,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>‘My father and my brothers, and their flocks, and their cattle,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and all that they have, came out of the land of Canaan. And,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>lo, they are in the land of Goshen.’</l><l n="2">And he took some<milestone unit="page" n="80r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of his brothers, five men, and presented them<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>before Pharaoh.</l><l n="3">And Pharaoh said<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to Jacob’s brothers, ‘What is your work?’ And they said to Pharaoh,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>‘Your servants are shepherds, and our fathers, too.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="4">And they said to Pharaoh, ‘We came to live in the land<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>because your servants have no pasture for their flocks because<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>the famine became stronger in the land of Canaan. And now may your servants dwell<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>in the land of Goshen.’</l><l n="5">And Pharaoh said<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to Joseph, ‘Your father and your brothers have come to you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="6">The land of Egypt is before you.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Settle your father and your brothers in the better place of the land.<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>They shall dwell in the land of Goshen. And if you know,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>or if there is any able men among them, then you shall make them<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>livestock superiors over those that are mine.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="7">And Joseph brought in Jacob his father, and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>stood him before Pharaoh. And Jacob blessed<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Pharaoh.</l><l n="8">And Pharaoh said to Jacob, ‘How many<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>are the days of the years of your life?’</l><l n="9">And Jacob said<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to Pharaoh, ‘The days of the years of my life are a hundred and thirty years.<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>The days of the years of my life have been few and bad, and have not attained<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>to the days of the years of the life of my fathers, in the days of their life.’</l><milestone unit="page" n="80v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="10">And Jacob offered peace to Pharaoh, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>went out from before Pharaoh.</l><l n="11">And Joseph settled<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>his father and his brothers, and gave them a possession<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>in the land of Egypt, in the better place of the land, in the land<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded.</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And Joseph nourished his father, and his brothers, and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>all the people of his father’s house, with bread,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>according to the food of the little ones.</l><l n="13">And there was no bread in all<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the land, for the famine became very much stronger, so that the all the people of<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>the land of Egypt and of the land of Canaan went insane by reason of the famine.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="14">And Joseph gathered up all the silver<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>that was found in the land of Egypt and in the land of Canaan<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>for the grain which they bought. And Joseph brought<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the money to Pharaoh’s house.</l><l n="15"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And when the silver came to an end from the land of Egypt and from the land<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of Canaan, all the Egyptians came to Joseph, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>‘Give us bread! And why should we die before you? Because<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the silver came to an end.’</l><l n="16">And Joseph said, ‘Give your livestock,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and I will give you bread for your livestock if the silver is gone.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="17">And they brought their livestock to Joseph,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and Joseph gave them bread for the horses, and for the multitude of<milestone unit="page" n="81r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>sheep, and for the multitude of cattle, and for the donkeys.<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And he led them out with bread for all their livestock<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>in that year.</l><l n="18">And that year was ended, and<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>they came to him the second year, and said to him, ‘We will not hide it<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>from my lord that in truth the silver has come to an end, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>my lord has the multitude of |our| livestock as well. There is nothing left before my lord,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>but our bodies, and our lands.</l><l n="19">Why shall we die<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>before your eyes, both we and our land? Buy us and<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>our land for bread, and we and our land will be servants to Pharaoh.<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And give us seed, that we may live and not die, that the land<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>may not be ruined.</l><l n="20">And Joseph bought all the land<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of Egypt for Pharaoh, because the Egyptians sold every man his field,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>because the famine prevailed over them. So the land became<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Pharaoh’s.</l><l n="21">And the people: he ordered them to go<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to cities, from one edge of Egypt’s borders even to its |other| edge.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="22">Only the land of the priests he did not buy,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>because the priests had a portion assigned them of Pharaoh, and did eat<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>their portion which Pharaoh gave them. On account of this<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>they did not sell their land.</l><l n="23">And<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Joseph said to the people, ‘Lo, I have bought you<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and your land for Pharaoh today. Lo, here is seed for you, and<milestone unit="page" n="81v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>you shall sow the land.</l><l n="24">And it shall be, in the harvest,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>that you shall give the fifth part to Pharaoh, and four<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>parts shall be your own, for field seed, and for your food,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and for them in your houses, and for food for your little ones.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="25">And they said, ‘You have revived us. Let us find favour<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>in the eyes of my lord, and we will be Pharaoh’s servants.’</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And Joseph made it a statute to this day over the land<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of Egypt, that Pharaoh should have up to the fifth part. Only the land<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of the priests did not become Pharaoh’s.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="27">And Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt, in the land<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of Goshen. And they had possessions in it. And they spread,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and multiplied very much.<milestone unit="line" n="13"/><emph>Parashat Vayechi</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="28">And Jacob lived<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>in the land of Egypt seventeen years. So the days<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of Jacob, the days of his life, were a hundred and forty-seven years.</l><l n="29"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And Israel’s days to die drew close. And he called<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his son Joseph, and said to him, ‘If, now, I have found<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>favour in your eyes, I pray you, <supplied reason="lost">put now your hand under my thigh, and do kindness and truth with me, I pray you,</supplied> do not bury me in Egypt.</l><milestone unit="page" n="82r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="30">But let me lie by my fathers. And carry<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>me out of Egypt, and bury me in their cemetery.’ And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he said, ‘I will do according to your words.’</l><l n="31">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>he said, ‘Swear to me.’ And he swore to him. And Israel bowed himself<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>at the head of the bed.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
