<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 3</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Genesis 3</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And the serpent was more crafty than any wild animal of <supplied reason="lost">the</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>field which the Lord God had created, and he said <supplied reason="lost">to</supplied> the woman, ‘Has God<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>said, you shall not eat of all fruits of the trees of the <supplied reason="lost">garden</supplied>?’</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="2">And the woman said to the serpent, ‘Of the fruit of <supplied reason="lost">the</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>trees of the garden we may eat.</l><l n="3">But of the fruit of <supplied reason="lost">the</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>tree which is in the midst of the garden, God has said, “You shall not eat<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of it, and you shall not touch it, lest you die.”’</l><l n="4">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the serpent said to the woman, ‘You will surely not die.</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>For God knows that in the day you eat thereof, then<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>your eyes will be opened, and you will be like angels, knowing good<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and evil.’</l><l n="6">And the woman saw that the tree is good<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>for food and desirable to the eyes, and that<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the tree is desirable <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>to bring about understanding<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>, and she took of its fruit, and ate, <supplied reason="lost">and</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>gave also to her husband with her, and he ate.</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And the eyes of them both were opened and they knew <supplied reason="lost">that they were</supplied><milestone unit="page" n="5v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><supplied reason="lost">naked</supplied>. And they sewed fig leaves |together|, and made<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>themselves aprons.</l><l n="8">And they heard the<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>voice of the Lord God walking in the garden in the windy time<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of the day, and the man and his wife hid themselves from before<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the Lord God among the trees of the garden.</l><l n="9"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And the Lord God called to Adam, and said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>‘Where are you?’</l><l n="10">And the man said, ‘I heard your voice<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>in the garden, and I was afraid, because I was naked, and I hid myself.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="11">And God said, ‘Who explained to you that<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>you were naked? Have you eaten of the tree of which I commanded you<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>not to eat?’</l><l n="12">And the man said, ‘The<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>woman whom you gave to be on my side: she gave me of the fruits of the<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>tree, and I ate’.</l><l n="13">And the Lord God said<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to the woman, ‘What is this that you have done?’ And the woman said, ‘The serpent deceived<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>me, and I ate.’</l><l n="14">And the Lord God said<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to the serpent, ‘Because you have done this, you are cursed above all<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>livestock, and above every wild animal of the field, you will go on your belly,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and you will eat dust all the days of your life.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="15">And I will put enmity between you and the woman,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and between your seed and her seed. He<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>will strike your head, and you will bite his heel.’</l><l n="16"><milestone unit="page" n="6r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>To the woman He said, ‘I will surely multiply your suffering <supplied reason="lost">and</supplied><milestone unit="line" n="2"/>in suffering you will give birth to children. And your desire <supplied reason="lost">will be</supplied> for your husband,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and he will rule over you.’</l><l n="17">And to the man he said,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>‘Because you have listened to the voice of your wife, and have eaten of the fruits of the tree<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of which I commanded you, saying, “You shall not eat of it,”<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>cursed is the ground because of you. You will eat its crops with suffering<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>all the days of your life.</l><l n="18">And it will bring forth to you thorns and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>nettle, and you will eat the plants<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of the field.</l><l n="19">You will eat bread by the sweat of your nose,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>until you return to the ground, because you were taken from it; because<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>you are dust, and you will return to dust.’</l><l n="20">And the<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>man called his wife’s name Eve, because she was the mother of all living.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="21">And the Lord God made for the man and for his wife<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>shirts of skin, and he clothed them.</l><l n="22">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the Lord God said, ‘Lo, the man has become as one of us,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to know good and evil. And now, lest he put forth his hand,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>forever’:</l><l n="23">And the Lord God drove him out<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>from the garden of Eden to work the ground from which he was taken.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="24">And he drove out the man, and he placed<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the cherubim at the east of the garden, and<milestone unit="page" n="6v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the blade of a revolving sword to guard the<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>way to the tree of life.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Lit. ‘to understand’.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
