<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Deuteronomy 22</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Deuteronomy <supplied reason="lost">22</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="1">And you shall not make unseen<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>your brother’s cattle or his sheep that go astray,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and shall not close your eyes from them: you shall certainly bring them back<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to your brother.</l><l n="2">And if your brother is not near<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to you, or if you do not know him, then you shall gather it to the midst of your<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>house, and it shall be with you until your brother seeks after it, and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>you shall give it back to him.</l><l n="3">And you shall do that with his donkey, and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>you shall do that with his clothing, and you shall do that with any lost thing<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of your brother’s which that will be lost by him and you find it:<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>you cannot close your eyes.</l><l n="4">You shall not make unseen<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>your brother’s donkey or his cattle fallen down<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>by the way, and you shall not close your eyes from them. You shall surely lift |them| up<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>with him.</l><l n="5">There shall not be a man’s item on a woman,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and a man shall not put on a woman’s garment,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>because all that do so are an abomination to the Lord your God.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="6">If a bird’s nest happens to be before you in the way in any<milestone unit="page" n="317r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>tree or on the ground, whether they are young ones or eggs,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and the mother sitting on the young or<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>on the eggs, you shall not take the mother with the children:</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="7">You shall surely let the mother go and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>take the children for yourself, so that it will be good for you, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>that you may prolong your days.</l><l n="8">When you build a new house,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>then you shall make a handle for your attic, that you may not set blood in your house<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>if any falling man falls from there.</l><l n="9">You shall not sow<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>your vineyard with two kinds |of seed|: lest the fruit <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>which you have sown</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and the produce of your vineyard be not good.</l><l n="10">You shall not plough with a bull<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and a donkey together.</l><l n="11">You shall not wear <emph>shaatnez</emph>:<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>wool and linen together.</l><l n="12">You shall make strings<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>on the four corners of your quilt with which<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>you cover yourself.</l><l n="13">If any man takes a wife and<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>comes to her and despises her,</l><l n="14">And puts<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>words of slander on her and brings out bad<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>fame on her and says, “I took this woman,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and I came to her, and did not find her virginity,”</l><l n="15"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>Then the father of the girl and her mother shall take and bring out<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the girl’s virginity to the elders of the city<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>in court of justice.</l><l n="16">And the girl’s father shall say<milestone unit="page" n="317v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to the elders, “I gave my daughter to this man<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>for a wife, and he despises her,</l><l n="17">And, lo, he put<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>words of slander on her, saying, “I did not find your daughter’s<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>virginity,” but this is my daughter’s virginity,” and he shall spread out<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the bedsheet before the elders of the city.</l><l n="18"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And the elders of that city shall take that man<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and punish him.</l><l n="19">And they shall fine<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>him a hundred silvers, and they shall give them to the father<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of the girl, because he has brought bad fame on a virgin of Israel.<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And she shall be his for a wife: he shall not be able to drive her out<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>all the days of his life.</l><l n="20">But if<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>this thing is true, if they do not find her virginity<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>in the girl,</l><l n="21">Then they shall bring out the girl<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to the door of her father’s house, and the people<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of her city shall stone her with stones, so that she dies, because she has done a repulsive<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>thing in Israel, to prostitute herself in her father’s house. And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>you shall drive the evil away from your midst.</l><l n="22">If a man is found<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>lying with a woman married to a husband, then<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>both of them shall die, both the man that lay<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>with the woman, and the woman, too. And you shall drive the evil away<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>from Israel.</l><l n="23">If there is a virgin girl that is betrothed<milestone unit="page" n="318r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>to a husband, and a man finds her in the city, and lies with her,</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="24">Then you shall bring them both out<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to the court of justice of that city, and you shall stone them with stones<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>so that they die: the girl, because she cried not<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in the city, and the man, because<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>he has violated his fellow’s wife. And you shall drive the<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>evil away from the your midst.</l><l n="25">But if a man finds in the field<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>a betrothed girl, and the man seizes<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>her and lies with her, then<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>only the man who lay with her shall die.</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>But you shall not do a thing to the girl. The girl does not have |a sin deserving| a punishment<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of death, because, just as a man would rise against his fellow<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and murder him and his soul: this matter is like that,</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="27">Because he found her in the field; though<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the betrothed girl cried, there was no one to save her.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="28">If a man finds a virgin girl who is not betrothed, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>he seizes her and lies with her, and they are found,</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="29">Then the man who lay with her shall give<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to the girl’s father fifty silver, and she shall be his wife.<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Because he has violated her, he shall not be able to drive her out<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>all the days of his life.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
