<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Leviticus 17</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Leviticus 17</title><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="1">And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l><l n="2"><milestone unit="line" n="19"/>‘Speak to Aaron and to his children and to all the children of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and say to them: “This is the word which the Lord has commanded,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>saying,</l><l n="3">“Any man of the house of Israel who slaughters<milestone unit="page" n="188r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>a cattle or a lamb or a goat in the camp, or who slaughters<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>|it| outside the camp,</l><l n="4">And if he does not bring it to the door of the tent of meeting<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to bring forward an offering to the Lord before the tabernacle of the Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>bloodshed will be counted to that man, as if he shed the blood of a man,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and that man will be cut off from among his people.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="5">So that the children of Israel may bring<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>their sacrifices which they offer over the surface of the<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>fields, and that they may bring them to the Lord, to the door<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of the tent of meeting, to the priest, and sacrifice them for peace offerings<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to the Lord.</l><l n="6">And the priest shall sprinkle the<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>blood on the altar of the Lord at the door of the tent<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of meeting and bring forward the fat for a pleasing aroma to the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="7">And they shall no more sacrifice their sacrifices to other<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>devils, after whom they went astray.<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>This shall be a statute forever to them throughout their generations.””</l><l n="8">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>you shall say to them: “Any man from the house of Israel or from the strangers who<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>live among them who offer a burnt offering or sacrifice,</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="9">And does not bring it to the door of the tent of meeting to make it<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to the Lord: that man will be cut off from among his people.</l><l n="10"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And if any man from the house of Israel or from the strangers who live<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>among you eats any blood: then I will set my wrath<milestone unit="page" n="188v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>against that soul that eats blood, and I will cut him off<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>from among his people.</l><l n="11">Because the life of the flesh is in the blood,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and I have given it to you on the altar to ask for atonement<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>for your souls, because it is the blood that askes for atonement for the soul.</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>On account of this I have said to the children of Israel: “No soul among you shall eat blood,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>nor shall the stranger that lives among you eat blood.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="13">And any man from the children of Israel or from the strangers<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>who live among you who hunts game, animal or<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>bird that is eaten: he shall pour out the blood thereof and cover it<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>with earth.</l><l n="14">Because the life of all flesh is its blood: it is in the life of it.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And I said to the children of Israel: “You shall not eat the blood of any flesh,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>because the life of all flesh is the blood of it. Every one of those who eat it<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>will be cut off.”</l><l n="15">And any soul that eats that which died, or<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>that which was torn up, whether it be <supplied reason="lost">a native</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> or a stranger, he shall wash his clothes<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and shall wash himself in water and shall be unclean until the evening:<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and he will be clean.</l><l n="16">But if he does not wash them or<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>wash his flesh, then he shall bear his punishment.”’</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: ‘poor’; a scribal error; cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">בָּאֶזְרָח </foreign>‘of a native of your own country’; cf. also Exo 12:19, Exo 12:48, Exo 12:49, and Lev 16:29.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
