<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 12</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Deuteronomy 1<supplied reason="lost">2</supplied><ref n="1"
                                target="#Deut-012-fn1_trl" type="noteAnchor" /></title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Deut012-P301r-L17_trl" n="17"
                            prev="ADub.III.73.005.011.trl.xml#Deut011-P301r-L17_trl" />
                        <l n="1">These are the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             statutes and judgments which you shall be watchful to do in the land
                            which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             the Lord God of your fathers gave you, to inherit it, all the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             days that you live on the earth.</l>
                        <l n="2">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             You shall surely destroy all the places in which
                            <milestone unit="page" n="301v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             the kingdoms served their gods: on the high mountains
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and on the rocks and under every
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             greening tree which you shall inherit.</l>
                        <l n="3">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             And you shall destroy their altars and break their pillars
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             and burn their idol poles in fire,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             and you shall chop down the carved idols and destroy the name
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             of them out of that place.</l>
                        <l n="4">You shall not do so to the altars
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             of the Lord your God.</l>
                        <l n="5">But to the place which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             the Lord your God shall choose from all your tribes to put
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             his name there: you shall seek his dwelling place and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             there you shall come.</l>
                        <l n="6">And there you shall bring your burnt offerings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             and your sacrifices and your tithes and the heave offerings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             of your hand and your vows and your freewill offerings
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             and the firstborn of your herds and of your flocks.</l>
                        <l n="7">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             And there you shall eat before the Lord your God, <seg type="commented"
                                corresp="#Deut-012-seg001_trl" />each man that which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             he is allowed to eat,<anchor type="commented"
                                xml:id="Deut-012-seg001_trl" /><ref n="2" target="#Deut-012-fn2_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> and you shall rejoice in all that you reach
                            your hand out to,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             you and your households, in which the Lord your God will bless you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="8">You shall not do like everything that we are doing here today,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             each one, everything that seems right in his eyes.</l>
                        <l n="9">Because
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             up to know you have not come to the rest and to the share which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             the Lord your God is giving you.</l>
                        <l n="10">But when you will cross
                            <milestone unit="page" n="302r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             the Jordan and dwell in the land which the Lord your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             is giving you as a share, and he will give you rest from all your
                            enemies
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             all around, so that you dwell in safety,</l>
                        <l n="11">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             Then there shall be a place which the Lord your God shall choose to
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             cause his name to dwell there: There shall you bring all that I
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             command you: your burnt offerings and your sacrifices, your tithes
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             and the heave offering of your hand, and all your choice vows which you
                            vow
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             to the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="12">And you will rejoice before the Lord your God,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             you and your sons and your daughters, and your servants and your
                            maidservants,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             and the Levite that is in your cities, since he has no portion and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             share with you.</l>
                        <l n="13">Take heed to yourself, lest you offer
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             your burnt offerings in every place that you see.</l>
                        <l n="14">Because only
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             in the place which the Lord shall choose in one of your tribes: there
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             you shall offer your burnt offerings, and there you shall do all that I
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             command you.</l>
                        <l n="15">Only, every time when your soul desires you shall sacrifice
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             and eat meat according to the blessing of the Lord your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             which he has given you in all your cities. The unclean man and the
                            clean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             man shall eat it: like the deer and the fawn.</l>
                        <l n="16">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             Only, you shall not eat the blood. You shall pour it like water on the
                            earth.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                        <l n="17">You may not eat within your cities the tithe
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             of your grain or of your must or of your olive oil or the firstborn
                            <milestone unit="page" n="302v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             of your herds or of your flock, or all your vows which you vow
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             or your freewill offerings or the heave offering of your hand.</l>
                        <l n="18">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             But you must eat them before the Lord your God, <seg type="commented"
                                corresp="#Deut-012-seg002_trl" />each man that which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             he is allowed to eat,<anchor type="commented"
                                xml:id="Deut-012-seg002_trl" /><ref n="3" target="#Deut-012-fn3_trl"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> in the place which the Lord your God shall
                            choose,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             you and your son and your daughter, and your servant and your
                            maidservant, and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             Levite that is in your cities. And you shall rejoice before the Lord
                            your God
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             in all that you reach your hands out to.</l>
                        <l n="19">Take heed to yourself,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             lest you leave the Levite, all your days
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                             on the earth.</l>
                        <l n="20">When the Lord your God will widen
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             your border as he spoke to you, and you will say,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             “Let me eat meat,” because every time your soul desires to eat meat,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             you shall eat meat.</l>
                        <l n="21">If
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             the place which the Lord your God has chosen to put his name
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             there is too far from you, then you shall sacrifice of your herd and of
                            your flock
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             which the Lord has given you, as I have commanded you, and you shall
                            eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             in your cities every time your soul desires it.</l>
                        <l n="22">Just: as
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             the deer and the fawn are eaten, so you shall eat
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             it: the unclean and the clean shall eat of them alike.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="23">Just: be strong not to eat the blood, because the blood:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             it is the life, and you shall not eat the life with the meat.</l>
                        <l n="24">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                             You shall not eat it, you shall pour it like water on the earth.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="303r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="25">You shall not eat it, so it will be good for you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             and for your children after you, when you do what
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             seems right in the eyes of the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="26">Only,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                             your holy things which you have and your vows, you shall take, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                             you shall go to the place which the Lord shall choose.</l>
                        <l n="27">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                             you shall offer your burnt offerings, the meat and the blood, on the
                            altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                             of the Lord your God. And the blood of your sacrifices shall be poured
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                             out on the altar of the Lord your God, and you shall eat the meat.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="28">Keep and hear all these words
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                             which I command you, so it may be good
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                             for you and for your children after you forever
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                             when you do what seems good and seems right
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                             in the eyes of the Lord your God.</l>
                        <l n="29">Because when the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                             Lord your God will cut off the nations that you are coming there
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                             to inherit them from before you, and you will inherit them and dwell
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                             in their land,</l>
                        <l n="30">Take heed to yourself
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                             that you are not snared by following them, after they are destroyed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                             from before you, lest you inquire after their gods,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                             saying, “How did these kingdoms serve
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                             their gods? And I will do likewise — I, too.”</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="31">You shall not do so to the service of the Lord your God, because
                            <milestone unit="page" n="303v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                             they did every abominable thing to the Lord which he despises for their
                            gods,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                             because they would also burn their sons and their daughters
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                             in the fire to
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Deut012-P303v-L4_trl" n="4"
                                next="ADub.III.73.005.013.trl.xml#Deut013-P303v-L4_trl" />
                             their gods. </l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="Deut-012-fn1_trl" type="footnote">K: erroneously indicated as
                            Deuteronomy 11.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Deut-012-fn2_trl" type="footnote">An interpretative addition
                            to Deu 12:7.</note>
                        <note xml:id="Deut-012-fn3_trl" type="footnote">An interpretative addition
                            to Deu 12:18.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
