<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 24</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 2<supplied reason="lost">4</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And Abraham grew old,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>he was well along in days. And the Lord had blessed Abraham in all<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>things.</l><l n="2">And Abraham said to his own servant, the elder<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of his household that ruled over all that he had,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>‘Put now your hand under my thigh.</l><l n="3">And<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>let me make you swear by the power of the Lord, the God of the skies,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and the God of the earth, that you shall not take a wife to my son<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I dwell.</l><l n="4"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>But you shall go to my land and to my kindred, and take<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>a wife to my son Isaac.’</l><l n="5">And the servant said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>‘Maybe the woman will not be willing to follow me to this land.<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Must I then bring your son again to the land from where you came?’</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="6">And Abraham said to him, ‘Beware<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>lest you bring my son back.</l><l n="7">The Lord God<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of heaven, who took me from my father’s house and from the land<milestone unit="page" n="33v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of my kindred, and who spoke to me, and swore to me,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>saying, ‘I will give this land to your offspring,’<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he will send his angel before you, and you shall take a wife<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>for my son from there.</l><l n="8">But if the woman is not willing to<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>follow you, then you shall be free from this oath of mine. Only<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>do not bring my son back.’</l><l n="9">And the servant put his hand<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>under the thigh of his lord Abraham, and swore to him<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>about this matter.</l><l n="10">And the servant took ten camels of the camels<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of his lord, and went away, and all the goods of his master were in his hand.<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And he arose, and went to Mesopotamia, to the city of Nahor.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="11">And he made his camels kneel down outside the city<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>by a well of water at evening time, at the<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>time when women who draw water go out.</l><l n="12">And he said,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>‘Oh Lord, God of my lord Abraham, <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>now</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> meet me<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>today, and show kindness to my master Abraham.</l><l n="13">Lo,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>I stand here by the well of water; and the daughters of the men of the city<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>come out to draw water:</l><l n="14">And let the girl to whom<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>I shall say, “Tilt your bucket, that I may drink,”, and if she says,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>“Drink, and I will water your camels, too,” — let her be designated for your servant<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Isaac. And I will know by this that you have shown kindness to my lord.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="15">And it was before he had finished speaking, and, lo,<milestone unit="page" n="34r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Rebekah came out, who was born to Bethuel, son of Milcah, the wife of<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>Nahor, Abraham’s brother, and her bucket was on her shoulder.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="16">And the girl was very fair in appearance,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>a virgin, and no man had known her. And she went down to the<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>spring and filled her bucket and went up.</l><l n="17">And the servant ran<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>to meet her, and said, ‘Let me taste<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>a little water of your bucket.’</l><l n="18">And she said, ‘Drink,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>my lord.’ And she hurried, and lowered her bucket on her hand, and<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>gave him drink.</l><l n="19">And she finished giving him drink, and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>she said, ‘I will draw water for your camels, too, until they finish<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>drinking.’</l><l n="20">And she hurried and emptied her bucket<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>into the trough, and ran again to the well to draw water, and drew<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>for all his camels.</l><l n="21">And the man wondered,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>gazing at her, and kept silent to learn whether the Lord had prospered<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>his journey or not.</l><l n="22">And it was, when the camels finished<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>drinking, that the man took a golden earring of a <emph>gög</emph><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>weight, and put two bracelets on her hands<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of ten measures of gold,</l><l n="23">after<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>he had said, ‘Tell me now, whose daughter are you? Is there<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>room in your father’s house for us to spend the night?’</l><l n="24"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And she said to him, ‘I am the daughter of Bethuel, son of Milcah,<milestone unit="page" n="34v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>whom she bore to Nahor.’</l><l n="25">And she said moreover to him,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘We have both lot of hay and fodder with us, and even room to spend the night.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="26">And the man bowed down, and worshiped the Lord.</l><l n="27"><milestone unit="line" n="4"/>And he said, ‘Blessed be the Lord God of my lord Abraham,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>who has not forsaken his mercy and his truth toward my lord. I was<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>in the way, the Lord led me to the house of my master’s brother.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="28">And the girl ran, and told her mother’s house<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>these words.</l><l n="29">And Rebekah had a brother,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and his name was Laban, and Laban ran out to the man,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to the well.</l><l n="30">And it was, when Laban saw<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>the earring and bracelets on the hands<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of his sister, and when he heard the words of<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Rebekah, his sister, saying, ‘Thus spoke the man to me,’<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>that he came to the man. And, lo, he stood by the camels<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>at the spring.</l><l n="31">And Laban said, ‘Come in,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>blessed of the Lord. Why do you stand outside? For I have prepared<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the house, as well as I have prepared room for the camels.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="32">And the man came into the room, and Laban ordered to take of the saddles<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of the camels, and gave hay and fodder for the camels, and water<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>to wash his feet, and the men’s feet that were with him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="33">And food was set before him to eat. But he said,<milestone unit="page" n="35r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>‘I will not eat, until I have said my words.’ And he said,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘Speak on.’</l><l n="34">And he said, ‘I am Abraham’s servant.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="35">And the Lord has blessed my lord greatly, and<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>he has become wealthy. And he has given him flocks, and cattle, and silver, and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>gold, and servants, and maidservants, and camels, and donkeys.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="36">And Sarah, my lord’s wife, bore a son to my lord<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>after she grew old, and he has given him all that was his.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="37">And my master made me swear, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>“You shall not take a wife for my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, in whose<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>land I dwell,</l><l n="38">You shall do nothing else but<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>go to my father’s house, and to my family, and take a wife<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to my son.”</l><l n="39">And I said to my lord, “Maybe the<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>woman will not follow me.”</l><l n="40">And he said to me, “The Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>before whom I have walked, will send his angel with you,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and prosper your way, and you will take a wife for my son of my family,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and of my father’s house.</l><l n="41">Then, you will be free<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>from this curse of mine if you come to my family, and if they do not give<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>|her| to you, you will be free from my curse.”</l><l n="42">And I came<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>today to the spring, and said, “Oh Lord God of my lord<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Abraham, will you prosper my way which I go?</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="43">Lo, I stand by the well of water, and let there be<milestone unit="page" n="35v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>a girl who comes out to draw. And if I say “Give me now a little water<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of your bucket to drink,”</l><l n="44">and if she says to me,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>“Drink, and I will draw for your camels also,” she is<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the woman whom the Lord has designated for my lord’s son.</l><l n="45"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Before I had finished speaking in my heart, lo,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Rebekah came out with her bucket on her shoulder, and she went down<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to the spring, and drew. And I said to her, “Give me a drink,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>now.”</l><l n="46">And she hurried, and let down<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>her bucket from on her, and said, “Drink, and I will give your camels<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>drink, too.” So I drank, and she made the camels drink, too.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="47">And I asked her, and said, “Whose daughter<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>are you?” And she said, “The daughter of Bethuel, Nahor’s son, whom<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Milcah bore to him.” And I put the ring on her nose,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and the bracelets on her arms.</l><l n="48"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And I bowed down, and worshiped the Lord, and blessed<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the Lord God of my lord Abraham, who had led me<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>in the right way to take my lord’s brother’s daughter<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>for his son.</l><l n="49">And now, will you deal kindly and truly<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>with my lord? Tell me. And if not, tell me,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>that I may turn to right or to left.’</l><l n="50">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>Laban and Bethuel answered, and they said, ‘The word has come from the Lord.<milestone unit="page" n="36r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>We cannot speak bad or good to you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="51">Lo, Rebekah is before you, take her, and go, and let her be<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>a wife to your lord’s son, as the Lord has spoken.’</l><l n="52"><milestone unit="line" n="4"/>And it was, when Abraham’s servant heard their words,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>that he bowed to the ground before the Lord.</l><l n="53">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the servant brought out silver vessels, and gold vessels, and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>garments, and gave them to Rebekah, and he gave excellent gifts to her brother<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and to her mother.</l><l n="54">And they ate and drank,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>he and the men that were with him, and spent the night.<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And they rose up in the morning, and he said, ‘Send me away, may I go<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>to my lord.’</l><l n="55">And her brother and her mother said,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>‘Let the girl abide with us <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg010"/<anchor xml:id="del001"/>a year, or ten months.<delSpan spanTo="#del002"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg010"/<anchor xml:id="del002"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>After that, she will go.’</l><l n="56">And the servant said to them,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>‘Do not delay me, since the Lord has prospered my way. Send me away<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>that I may go to my master.’</l><l n="57">And they said, ‘We will call the girl<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and ask her from her own mouth.’</l><l n="58">And they called Rebekah<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and said to her, ‘Will you go with this man?’ And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>she said, ‘I will go.’</l><l n="59">And they sent away Rebekah<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>their sister, and her nurse, and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Abraham’s servant, and his men.</l><l n="60">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>they blessed Rebekah, and said to her, ‘Our sister,<milestone unit="page" n="36v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>may you become thousands of ten thousands, and may your offspring inherit<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the gate of his enemies!’</l><l n="61">And Rebekah arose,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and her maids, and they rode on the camels,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and followed the man, and the servant took<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Rebekah, and went his way.</l><l n="62">And Isaac came from a trip,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>because he had gone to Beer-Lahai-Roi, and he was dwelling in the land<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of the south.</l><l n="63">And Isaac went out to stroll<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>in the evening among the trees in the field. And<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>he raised his eyes, and saw, and, lo, the camels were coming.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="64">And Rebekah raised her eyes, and she saw<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Isaac, and she fell from the camel.</l><l n="65"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And she said to the servant, ‘Who is that man, <supplied reason="lost">†the one alone</supplied><ref target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor"/>, who walks<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>in the field to meet us?’ And the servant said, ‘It is my lord.’<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>So Rebekah took her veil and covered herself.</l><l n="66"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And the servant told Isaac all the things that he had done.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="67">And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah’s tent.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And he took Rebekah, and she became his<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>wife, and he loved her. And Isaac was consoled<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>after his mother.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Unidentified unit of weight.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">A mistranslation, cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">יָמִים אֹו עָשֹׂור </foreign>‘[a few] days, at least ten’. Repeated in TKow.01, H, C, and R. Translated correctly in V.</note><note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">An uncertain inerpretation of <emph>tigi</emph>.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
