<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 30</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Numbers 30</title><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And Moses told the children of Israel<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>all that the Lord commanded Moses.<milestone unit="line" n="9"/><emph>Parashat Matot</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="2">And Moses spoke<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>to the superiors of the tribes of the children<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of Israel, saying, ‘This is the word which the Lord has commanded.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="3">A man who vows a vow to the Lord or<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>swears an oath to bind his soul with a bond:<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>he shall not disregard his word, he shall do according to all that comes out of his mouth.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="4">And a woman who vows a vow to the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and binds |herself by| a bond in her father’s house in her youth,</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="5">And her father hears her vow<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and her bond by which she has bound her soul, and<milestone unit="page" n="266r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>her father keeps quiet to her, then all her vows will stand, and every<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>bond by which she has bound her soul will stand.</l><l n="6">But<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>if her father forbids her on the day he heard all her vows<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and all her bonds by which she has bound her soul,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>it will not stand. And the Lord will forgive her sin because her father forbade<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>it her.</l><l n="7">And if she marries a husband,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and her vows are on her or<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the utterance of her lips by which she bound her soul,</l><l n="8"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And her husband heard it and kept quiet to her on the day that he heard it,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>then her vows will stand, and her bonds by which she bound<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>her soul will stand.</l><l n="9">But if<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>her husband forbade her on the day that he heard it and broke<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>her vow which is on her and the utterance of her lips<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>by which she bound her soul, then the Lord will forgive<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>her.</l><l n="10">And a vow of a widow and of her that is divorced, everything<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>by which she has bound her soul, shall stand against her.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="11">And if she vowed in her husband’s house<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>or bound her soul by a bond with an oath,</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="12">And her husband heard it and kept quiet to her,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>did not forbid her, then all her vows will stand, and every bond<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>by which she bound her soul will stand.</l><l n="13">But<milestone unit="page" n="266v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>if her husband has truly broken them on the day he heard them,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>then all the came out of her lips concerning her vows and concerning her bond of her soul<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>will not stand. Her husband has broken them, and the Lord will forgive<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>her sin.</l><l n="14">Every vow and every binding oath to afflict<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the soul: her husband establishes it or her husband breaks<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>it.</l><l n="15">But if her husband altogether keeps quiet to her<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>from day to day, then he establishes all her vows<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>or all her bonds which are on her.<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>He establishes them, because he kept quiet to her on the day he heard them.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="16">But if he truly breaks them after that he has heard them,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>then he will bear the punishment of the women.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="17">These are the statutes which the Lord commanded<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Moses, between a man and his wife, between the father<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and his daughter while she is in her youth within her father’s house.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
