<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 15</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 15</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-19-2" n="19" prev="ADub.III.73.003.014.trl.xml#line-19-1" />
                        <l n="1">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            the Lord spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">‘Speak to the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            of Israel, and say to them, “When any man has a discharge out of his flesh,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="184r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            his discharge: it is unclean.</l>
                        <l n="3">And this shall be his uncleanness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            in his discharge: if, in his discharge, there be a <supplied
                                reason="lost">†fluid</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"
                             /> |running| from his flesh or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            his flesh is closed from his discharge, it is his uncleanness.</l>
                        <l n="4">Every
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            bed on which he lies that has the discharge shall be unclean, and any
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            item on which he sits shall be unclean.</l>
                        <l n="5">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            And a man who touches his bed shall wash his clothes and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            wash his body in water, and he shall be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="6">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            And one who sits on any item on which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            the one who has the discharge has sat shall wash his clothes and shall
                            wash his body in water, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            he shall be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="7"><emph>And the one who touches the flesh of the one who has the
                                discharge shall wash his clothes and wash himself in water, and he
                                shall be unclean until the evening.</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"
                             /></l>
                        <l n="8">And if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the one who has the discharge spits on him that is clean, then he shall
                            wash his clothes and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            wash himself in water, and he shall be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="9">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            And any saddle on which the one who has the discharge rides
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            shall be unclean.</l>
                        <l n="10">And anyone who touches anything that was
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            under him shall be unclean until the evening. And the one who bears
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            those things shall wash his clothes <supplied reason="lost">and shall
                                wash himself in water</supplied> and he shall be unclean until the
                            evening.</l>
                        <l n="11">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            And anyone whom the one who has the discharge touches, and has not
                            washed his hands in water,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            he shall wash his clothes and wash himself in water, and he shall be unclean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="12">And the earthen vessel that the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            one who has the discharge touches shall be broken, and every wooden
                            vessel shall be rinsed in water.</l>
                        <l n="13">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            And if the one who has a discharge is cleansed of his discharge, then he
                            shall count to himself seven days
                            <milestone unit="page" n="184v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            from the time of his cleansing and wash his clothes and wash his body in
                            running water,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and he will be clean.</l>
                        <l n="14">And on the eighth day he shall take for him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and he shall come before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            the Lord to the door of the tent of meeting and give them to the
                            priest.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="15">And the priest shall do them: one a sin offering and one a burnt offering,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and the priest shall ask for atonement for him before the Lord for his
                            discharge.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="16">And if a drop of a man’s semen comes out from him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            he shall wash his body in water and be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                        <l n="17">And any garment and any leather on which is
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            a drop of semen shall be washed with water and be unclean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="18">And if a man lies with a woman
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            — an intercourse of seed — they shall wash their bodies in water and be unclean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="19">And a woman who has a discharge: if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            her discharge from her body is blood, she shall be in her menstruation
                            seven days: and anyone
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            who touches her shall be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="20">And everything
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            on which the woman lies during her menstruation
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            shall be unclean and everything on which she sits shall be unclean.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="21">And anyone who touches her bed shall wash
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            his clothes and wash his body in water and be unclean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="22">And anyone who touches any item that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            she sat on shall wash his clothes and wash his body in water
                            <milestone unit="page" n="185r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            and be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="23">And if
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            it is on her bed or on anything on which the woman
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            sits when he touches it, he shall be unclean
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="24">And if any man lies
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            with her at all, and the blood of the women’s menstruation is on him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            he shall be unclean seven days, and all the beds on which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the man lies shall be unclean.</l>
                        <l n="25">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            And if a woman has an emission of blood many days other than the time
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of her menstruation or if it runs close to the time of her menstruation: all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            the days of the discharge of her uncleanness shall be as the days of her menstruation.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            She shall be unclean.</l>
                        <l n="26">Every bed on which she <delSpan spanTo="#del001" />sits<anchor
                                xml:id="del001" />
                            <addSpan spanTo="#add002" /><emph>lies</emph><anchor xml:id="add002" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            all the days of her discharge shall be to her as the bed of her menstruation.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            And any item that she sits on shall be unclean,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            like the uncleanness of her menstruation.</l>
                        <l n="27">And anyone who touches
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            them shall be unclean and shall wash his clothes and shall wash his body
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            in water and shall be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <l n="28">But
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            if she is cleansed of her discharge, then she shall count to herself
                            seven days, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            after that she will be clean.</l>
                        <l n="29">And on the eighth day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            she shall take to her two turtledoves or two young pigeons and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            bring them to the priest, to the door of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="30">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            And the priest shall make one a sin offering and one a burnt offering,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="185v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            and the priest shall ask for atonement for her before the Lord for the discharge
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            of her uncleanness.</l>
                        <l n="31">And you shall separate the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            of Israel from their uncleanness, so as they do not die because of their uncleanness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            when they defile my tabernacle that is among them.”’</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="32">This is the teaching of the one who has a discharge and of him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            from whom a drop of semen goes out, so as to become unclean by it,</l>
                        <l n="33">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            And of her that is sick in her menstruation, and of the one who has a
                            discharge, a discharge of a man,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and of a woman, and of the one who lies with an unclean woman.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An uncertain translation of
                                <emph>siliǵaj</emph>.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
