<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 32</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Numbers 32</title><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="1">And a great multitude of livestock was<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>for the children of Reuben and the children of Gad.<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And they saw the land of Jazer and the land of Gilead,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and, lo, the land was even a place for cattle.</l><l n="2">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>children of Gad and the children of Reuben came and<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>spoke to Moses and to Eleazar, the priest, and to the princes<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of the congregation, saying,</l><l n="3">Ataroth,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and Dibon, and Jazer, and Nimrah, and Heshbon, and Elealeh,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and Shebam, and Nebo, and Beon:</l><l n="4">‘The land<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the inhabitants of which the Lord defeated before the congregation of Israel<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>is a land for cattle, and your servants have cattle.’</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And they said, ‘If we have found favour in your sight,<milestone unit="page" n="270r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>let this land be given to your servants for a possession,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and do not have us cross over Jordan.’</l><l n="6">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Moses said to the children of Gad and to the children of Reuben,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>‘Will your brethren go to war, and will you sit here?</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="7">And why do you hold back the heart of the children of Israel<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>from crossing to the land which the Lord has given them?</l><l n="8"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Thus did your fathers, when I sent them from Kadesh-Barnea<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to see the land.</l><l n="9">And they went up<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to the river of Eshcol and saw the land<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and they hold back the heart of the children of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>not to go to the land which the Lord had given them.</l><l n="10">And<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the Lord’s anger was kindled on that day, and he swore,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>saying,</l><l n="11">“The man<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>who came out from Egypt, from twenty years old and upward <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/><supplied reason="lost">will not see</supplied><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the land which I swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to Jacob, they have not followed my order completely,</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="12">Except Caleb, son of Jephunneh, the Kenizzite, and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Joshua, son of Nun, for they have wholly followed the order<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of the Lord.”</l><l n="13">And the Lord’s anger was kindled<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>against Israel, and he made them wander in the wilderness forty<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>years, until the end of all the generation who were doing things<milestone unit="page" n="270v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>that seemed bad in the eyes of the Lord.</l><l n="14">And, lo, you<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>have risen in your fathers’ place, an increase of sinful men,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>to increase still more the furious anger of the Lord toward Israel.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="15">Because if you turn away from his order,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>he will go on to leave them yet again in the wilderness, and you will destroy all<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>this people.’</l><l n="16">And they came near to him,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and said, ‘We will build sheepfolds here for our livestock<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and cities for our infants.</l><l n="17">But we<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>will arm ourselves to be diligent to go before the children<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of Israel until we have brought them to their place.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And our infants shall dwell in the fortified cities in front of<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the inhabitants of the land.</l><l n="18">We will not return to our houses<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>until the children of Israel have taken every man his share.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="19">Because we will not take a share with them<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>from the ford of Jordan and beyond, because our share has come to us<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>from the eastward |side| of the ford of Jordan.’</l><l n="20"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And Moses said to them, ‘If you do this thing,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>if you arm yourselves before the Lord for war,</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="21">And pass all of you armed over Jordan<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>before the Lord until he has destroyed his enemies<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>from before him,</l><l n="22">And the land is subdued before<milestone unit="page" n="271r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the Lord: after that you will return, and you will be free<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>from the Lord and from Israel, and this land will be your<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>possession before the Lord.</l><l n="23">But if<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>you will not do so, lo, you will be sinful for the Lord, and know<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>that your sin will meet you.</l><l n="24">Build you<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>cities for your infants, and folds for your sheep, and do that which has come out<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of your mouth.’</l><l n="25">And the children<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of Gad and the children of Reuben spoke to Moses, saying,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>‘Your servants will do as my lord commands.</l><l n="26">Our infants,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>our wives, our hosts<ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/> and all our livestock shall be there<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>in the cities of Gilead.</l><l n="27">But your servants<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>will pass over, every man armed for war, before the Lord to battle,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>as my lord says.’</l><l n="28">So Moses gave command concerning them<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to Eleazar, the priest, and Joshua,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>son of Nun, and the superiors of the fathers of the tribes<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of the children of Israel.</l><l n="29">And Moses said to them,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>‘If the children of Gad and the children of Reuben will pass<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>with you over Jordan, every man armed to battle, before<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the Lord, and the land shall be subdued before you, then you shall give<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>them the land of Gilead for a possession.</l><l n="30">But<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>if they will not pass over with you armed, they shall have possessions<milestone unit="page" n="271v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>among you in the land of Canaan.’</l><l n="31">And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the children of Gad and the children of Reuben answered, saying, ‘What<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the Lord has said to your servants, so will we do.</l><l n="32">We will pass<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>over armed before the Lord to the land of Canaan, and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the possession of our share from |across| the ford of Jordan with us.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="33">And Moses gave to them, to the children of Gad and to the children of Reuben and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to half the tribe of Manasseh, son of Joseph, the kingdom<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of Sihon, king of the Amorites, and the kingdom of Og,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>king of Bashan: the land with its cities within the borders of the cities<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of the land all around.</l><l n="34">And the children<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of Gad built Dibon, and Ataroth, and Aroer,</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="35">And Atroth-Shophan, and Jazer,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>and Jogbehah,</l><l n="36">And Beth-Nimrah, and<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Beth-Haran, fortified cities, and folds for sheep.</l><l n="37">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the children of Reuben built Heshbon, and Elealeh,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and Kiriathaim,</l><l n="38">And Nebo,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and Baalmeon, with their names being changed, and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Sibmah, and gave other names to the cities<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>which they built.</l><l n="39">And the children of Machir, son<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>of Manasseh, went to Gilead and took it, and they destroyed<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the Amorites who were there.</l><l n="40">And Moses gave Gilead to Machir, son of Manasseh, and he dwelt there.</l><l n="41"><supplied reason="lost">And</supplied>
							<emph>Jair, son of Manasseh went and took their small villages</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/>
							<supplied reason="lost">and called them Havoth-Jair</supplied>.</l><l n="42">And Nobah went and took<milestone unit="page" n="272r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><addSpan spanTo="#add002"/><emph>Kenath</emph><anchor xml:id="add002"/>, and its villages, and called it Nobah after his own name.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: <emph>if they see</emph>; a mistranslation repeated in a number of manuscripts resulting from literal translation of the Hebrew conditional clause, cf. Gen 14:23, Num 14:23, Num 14:30, Deu 1:35. | TKow.01: <emph>if they see</emph>. | H: <emph>if they see</emph>. | C: <emph>if they see</emph>. | M: <emph>if they see</emph>. | E: <emph>if they see</emph>. | R: <emph>if they see</emph>.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">Possibly a scribal error (or a mistranslation), cf. Heb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">מִקְנֵנוּ </foreign>‘our flocks’. Cf., however, Num 31:9.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
