<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 49</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 49</title><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="1">And Jacob called<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>his sons, and said, ‘Assemble and let me tell you<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>what will befall you in the last days.</l><l n="2"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Assemble and listen, oh sons of Jacob,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and listen to the words of Israel, your father.</l><l n="3"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Reuben, you are my firstborn, my might, and the beginning of my strength,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the fame of priesthood and the fame of reign.</l><l n="4"><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Recklessness like the flow of water is to be found in you, you will not be famous,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>because you went up to your father’s bed, then you defiled,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>it was cut off |from you|.</l><l n="5">Simeon and Levi<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>are brothers: weapons of wickedness are in their habitations.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>My soul did not come into their secret, into their assembly,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>my spirit did not become united. For in their anger they killed a man,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and they wilfully ruined a stronghold.</l><l n="7">Cursed is<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>their anger, for it is fierce, and their fury, for it is cruel.<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>I will divide them in Jacob, and scatter them in Israel.</l><milestone unit="page" n="84r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="8">Judah: You, your brothers will praise you. Your hand will be<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>on the neck of your enemies, your father’s children will bow down before you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="9">Judah is a lion’s cub: from prey, my son,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>you are gone up. He kneeled down, he lay down as a lion, and as a lioness:<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>who will rouse him?</l><l n="10">Reign will not depart<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>from Judah, or a statute-giver among his families, until<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>the Messiah comes, and to him will be the obedience of the peoples.</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="8"/>He will tie his mule to the vine and his donkey’s colt to a thin branch,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>he will wash his garments in wine and his quilt in the blood of grapes.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="12">The redness of his eyes will be because of the plenty<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of wine, and the whiteness of his teeth will be because of the plenty of milk.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="13">Zebulun will dwell at the haven of the seas, and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>he shall be for a haven for ships, and his border shall be at Sidon.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="14">Issachar is of thick bones, lies down<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>between two <supplied reason="lost">†cowsheds</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>.</l><l n="15">And he saw rest, that it was good,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and the land, that it was pleasant, and he bowed his shoulder to bear<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the burden of reading the Law, and became a tribute-payer,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>instead of a servant.</l><l n="16">Dan will judge his people<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>as one of the tribes of Israel <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>from which Shimshon will come forth,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and will be the judge of Israel<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/>.</l><l n="17">Dan will be like a serpent<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>by the road, like a viper by the path, that bites<milestone unit="page" n="84v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the horse’s heels, and its rider falls backward.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="18">I hope for your salvation, oh Lord.</l><l n="19">Gad,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>a troop gathers over him, but at the last he will gather<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and overcome.</l><l n="20">About Asher: his food will be fat, and he<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>will yield a king’s heavenly food.</l><l n="21">Naphtali<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>is like a fawn <seg type="commented" n="#seg002"/>let loose<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg002"/><ref target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor"/>, who gives pleasant words.</l><l n="22"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Joseph is like a bough at full strength, a spreading bough by a well, thin<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>branches that strutted on a stronghold.</l><l n="23">And<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the archers teased him, and shot at him, and were hostile to him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="24">But his bow dwelt in strength, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>the arms of his hands were made strong by the strength of the mighty God<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of Jacob, from there is the shepherd, the foundation of Israel,</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="25">by the command of God of your father, and he shall help you,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and by the mighty God, and he shall bless you with blessings of heavens<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>from the heavens above, with blessings of the deep that lies beneath,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>with blessings of the breasts and of the womb.</l><l n="26">The blessings<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of your father have prevailed above the blessings of my parents<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>up to the tokens of the everlasting rocks. They shall be on the head of Joseph,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and on the brow of the head of the one separate from his brothers.</l><l n="27"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Benjamin will tear up like a wolf, in the morning he will devour the cattle, and at night<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>he will divide the spoil.’</l><l n="28">All these are the twelve tribes of Israel:<milestone unit="page" n="85r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and this is it what their father spoke to them, and he blessed them.<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>He blessed them each according to his blessing.</l><l n="29">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>he commanded them, and said to them, ‘I will be gathered<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>to my people. Bury me next to my fathers in the cave that is in the field<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of Ephron, the Hittite.</l><l n="30">In the cave that<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>is in the field of Machpelah, which is before Mamre, in the land of Canaan,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>where Abraham bought the field from Ephron, the Hittite,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>for a possession as a sepulchre.</l><l n="31">There they buried<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Abraham and Sarah, his wife, there they buried<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Isaac and Rebekah, his wife, and there I buried<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Leah.</l><l n="32">The purchase of the field and of the cave<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>that is in it was from the children of Heth.’</l><l n="33">And<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Jacob finished commanding his sons, and he gathered<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>his feet into the bed, and rested, and was gathered<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to his people.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: an uncertain translation of <emph>tüzüv</emph>, cf. <emph>jasavun</emph> ‘cowshed’ in C. | TKow.01: <emph>eki tüzüvler arsyna</emph>; the same translation as in K. | H: <emph>eki cekler arasyna</emph> ‘between two borders’. | C: <emph>arasyna ol eki jasavu</emph>[n]<emph>larnyŋ</emph>  ‘between the two cowsheds’. | V: <emph>ol eki t́uźuv́ĺar arasyna</emph>; the same translation as in K. | R: <emph>ol eki t́uźuv́ĺar arasyna</emph>; the same translation as in K.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 49:16.</note><note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">Lit. ‘sent’.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
