<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 15</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Numbers 15</title><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="1">And the Lord spoke<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>to Moses, saying,</l><l n="2">‘Speak to the children of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and say to them, “When you will come to the land of your habitations,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>which I am giving to you,</l><l n="3">And when you will make an offering by fire<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to the Lord, a burnt offering, or a sacrifice in dedicating a vow or in a<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>freewill offering or on your holidays, to make an aroma of acceptance to the Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>of the cattle, or of the flock:</l><l n="4">Then<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the one who brings forward his offering to the Lord shall bring forward fine flour,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the tenth part of an <emph>ephah</emph>, mixed with the fourth part<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of a hin of oil.</l><l n="5">And you shall make wine for a drink offering,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the fourth part of a hin, with the burnt offering or<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>for sacrifice for one lamb.</l><l n="6">Or for a ram, you shall make<milestone unit="page" n="237v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>a grain offering, fine flour, two tenths, mixed with the third<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>part of a hin of oil.</l><l n="7">And wine for a drink offering: you shall bring forward the third<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>part of a hin, an aroma of acceptance to the Lord.</l><l n="8">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>when you offer the young of cattle for a burnt offering or for a sacrifice in dedicating<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>a vow or peace offerings to the Lord:</l><l n="9">Then he shall bring forward<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>with a young of a cattle a grain offering, fine flour, three tenths, mixed<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>with half a hin of oil.</l><l n="10">And you shall bring forward<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>for a drink offering half a hin of wine, an offering by fire, an aroma of acceptance<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>to the Lord.</l><l n="11">Thus shall it be done for one bull or for one<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>ram or for a lamb of the sheep or for a goat.</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>According to the number that you will do, so shall you do to |each| one<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>according to their number.</l><l n="13">All those from this land shall do these things after this manner, to bring forward<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>an offering by fire, an aroma of acceptance to the Lord.</l><l n="14">And if<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>a stranger lives with you — or the one who is among you — throughout your generations,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and offers an offering by fire, an aroma of acceptance to the Lord: as you do,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>so he shall do, too.</l><l n="15">Oh |you|, community, one statute<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>is for you and for the stranger that lives |with you|, a statute<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>throughout your generations: as you are, so shall the stranger be before the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="16">One teaching and one judgement shall be for you and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>for the stranger that lives with you.”’</l><l n="17">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l><l n="18">‘Speak to the children<milestone unit="page" n="238r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of Israel, and say to them, “When you come to the land where<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>I am bringing you:</l><l n="19">And it shall be that before you eat<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>of the bread of the land, you shall dedicate a heave offering to the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="20">You shall dedicate a cake of the first of your dough as a heave offering. Like a heave offering<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of the threshing-floor, so shall you dedicate it.</l><l n="21">Of the first<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of your dough you shall give to the Lord a heave offering throughout your generations.</l><l n="22"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And if you make a mistake and do not do all these commandments,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>which the Lord has spoken to Moses,</l><l n="23">All<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>that the Lord has commanded you by the prophecy of Moses,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>from the day that the Lord commanded Moses and onward throughout your generations,</l><l n="24"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Then it shall be that, if it was done by mistake, out of the |sight of| the superiors of the congregation,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>then the congregation shall do one calf, the young of the cattle,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>for a burnt offering, an aroma of acceptance to the Lord, and its grain offering,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>and its drink offering, according to the |required| manner, and one kid of the goats<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>for a sin offering.</l><l n="25">And <supplied reason="lost">the priest</supplied> shall ask for atonement<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>for all the congregation of the children of Israel, and it shall be forgiven<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>them, because it is a mistake, and they have brought<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>their offering, a sacrifice by fire to the Lord, and their sin offering<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>before the Lord for their mistake.</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And it shall be forgiven for all the congregation of the children of Israel and the stranger<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>who lives among them, because for all the people<milestone unit="page" n="238v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the sin was by mistake.</l><l n="27">And if any soul sins<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>by mistake, then he shall bring forward a one-year-old goat for a sin offering.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="28">And the priest shall ask for atonement for the soul<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>that is mistaken, when he sins by mistake before<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the Lord, to ask for atonement for him, and it will be forgiven him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="29">|For| the native among the children of Israel and for the stranger<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>who lives among them: there shall be one teaching<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>for you, for the one doing sins by mistake.</l><l n="30">But<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the soul that does anything with a strong hand, |whether he is| of the native or of the strangers,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>he despises the word of the Lord, and that soul will be cut off<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>from among his people,</l><l n="31">Because he has despised the word of the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and has broken his commandment. That soul shall utterly be cut off:<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the punishment of his iniquity is on him.”’</l><l n="32">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the children of Israel were in the wilderness, and they found a man<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>that gathered wood on the Sabbath day.</l><l n="33">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>those who found him gathering sticks brought him forward<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>to Moses and Aaron and to all the congregation.</l><l n="34"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>And they put him under guard, because it was not yet declared what<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>death should be done to him.</l><l n="35">And the Lord said to Moses,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>‘The man shall be surely put to death. All the congregation <supplied reason="lost">shall</supplied> stone him with stones<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>outside the camp.’</l><l n="36">And<milestone unit="page" n="239r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>all the congregation brought him outside the camp and stoned him<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>with stones, and he died, as the Lord commanded Moses.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="37">And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l><l n="38"><milestone unit="line" n="4"/>‘Speak to the children of Israel, and you shall say to them that<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>they shall make themselves tassels in the edges of their garments<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>throughout their generations, and that they shall put on the tassel of the edges<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>a thread of blue.</l><l n="39">And it shall be to you that you may look on it<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and see, and remember all the commandments of the Lord and<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>do them, and that you shall not turn after your own heart and your own eyes,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>after which you go astray:</l><l n="40">That<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>you may remember and do all my commandments,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and be holy to your God.</l><l n="41">I am the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to be God to you. I am the Lord your God.’</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
