<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 27</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 27</title><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="1">And it was, when Isaac was old,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and his eyes were too dim for seeing, that he called<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Esau, his older son, and said to him, ‘My son!’ And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>he said to him, ‘Lo, here am I.’</l><l n="2">And he said, ‘Lo,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>I grew old, I do not know the day of my death.</l><l n="3">So<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>now take your weapons, your sword, and bow, and<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>go out to the field, and hunt game for me.</l><l n="4">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>make me delicious food, such as I love, and bring it to me,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and let me eat, that my soul may bless you before I die.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="5">And Rebekah was listening when Isaac spoke<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>to his son Esau. And Esau went to the field to hunt<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>to bring game.</l><l n="6">And Rebekah said to her son Jacob,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>saying, ‘Lo, I heard your father speaking to Esau,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>your brother, saying,</l><l n="7">“Bring me game<milestone unit="page" n="41r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and make me delicious food, so I may eat it and bless you before<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the Lord, before I die.”</l><l n="8">Now therefore,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>my son, obey my voice to do what I am commanding you.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="9">Go now to the flock, and take me from there two<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>good kids of the goats, so that I may make from them delicious<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>food for your father, such as he loves.</l><l n="10">And bring it<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to your father, that he may eat, and that he may bless you<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>before his death.’</l><l n="11">And Jacob said to Rebekah his mother,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>‘Lo, Esau my brother is a hairy man, and I am a smooth man.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="12">Maybe my father will touch me, and I will seem in his eyes<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>as a deceiver, and I will bring a curse on me<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>and not a blessing.’</l><l n="13">And his mother said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>‘Your curse will be on me, my son, <delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg011"/<anchor xml:id="del001"/>because if<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>your father recognizes you, you will say that it was I who commanded you to do this.<delSpan spanTo="#del002"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg011"/<anchor xml:id="del002"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> Only<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>obey my voice, and go take them for me.’</l><l n="14">And he went<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and took and brought them to his mother, and his mother made delicious<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>food, such as his father loved.</l><l n="15">And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Rebekah took the garments of Esau, her older son, the<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>finest of them, which were with her in the house, and she put them on Jacob,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>her younger son.</l><l n="16">And she put the skins of the<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>goat kids on his hands and on the smooth<milestone unit="page" n="41v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>part of his neck.</l><l n="17">And she gave the<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>delicious food and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand of Jacob,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>her son.</l><l n="18">And he came to his father, and said, ‘My father.’<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>And he said, ‘Lo, I am here. Who are you, my son?’</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Jacob said to his father, ‘I am Esau your firstborn. I have done all<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>as you spoke to me. Get up, now, sit and eat of my game,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>so your soul will bless me.’</l><l n="20">And<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Isaac said to his son, ‘What is this? You hurried to find, my son.’ And he said,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>‘Because the Lord your God made me meet it before me.’</l><l n="21">And Isaac said<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to Jacob, ‘Come near, now, let me touch you, my son: is this you,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>my very son Esau, or not.’</l><l n="22">And Jacob went near to Isaac<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>his father, and he touched him, and said, ‘The voice is Jacob’s voice,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>but the hands are the hands of Esau.’</l><l n="23">And he did not recognize him,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>because his hands were hairy, like his brother Esau’s hands,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and he blessed him.</l><l n="24">And he said, ‘Are you my very<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>son Esau?’ And he said, ‘I am.’</l><l n="25">And he said, ‘Bring<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>it near to me, and let me eat of my son’s game, so that<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>my soul will bless you.’ And he brought it near to him, and he ate; and he brought him<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>wine, and he drank.</l><l n="26">And Isaac, his father, said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>‘Come near now, and kiss me, my son.’</l><l n="27">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>he came near, and kissed him, and he smelled the smell of his garments,<milestone unit="page" n="42r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and he blessed him, and said, ‘See, the smell of my son is like the smell<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of a field which the Lord has blessed.</l><l n="28">And may<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>God give you from the dew of the skies, and from the fatness<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of the earth, and plenty of grain and must.</l><l n="29"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Let peoples serve you, and nations bow down to you.<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Be superior over your brothers, and let your mother’s sons bow down to you.<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Cursed be everyone that curses you, and blessed be everyone who blesses you.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="30">And it was, when Isaac had finished blessing<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Jacob, and Jacob had scarcely gone out from before Isaac,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>his father, that Esau his brother came from his hunting.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="31">And he, too, had made delicious food and brought it<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to his father, and said to his father, ‘Let my father get up and eat<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of his son’s game, so your soul will bless me.’</l><l n="32"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And Isaac his father said to him, ‘Who are you?’ And he said, ‘I am<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>your firstborn son Esau.’</l><l n="33">And Isaac trembled very<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>exceedingly, <delSpan spanTo="#del003"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg012"/<anchor xml:id="del003"/>for this thing did not appear to him through a prophecy<delSpan spanTo="#del004"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg012"/<anchor xml:id="del004"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/>,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>and said, ‘Who was it here, he that hunted game and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>brought it to me? And I ate of all that I wanted before you came,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and I even blessed him. He shall be blessed.’</l><l n="34"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>As soon as Esau heard the words of his father, he cried<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>with a great and exceedingly bitter cry, and said to his father, ‘Bless<milestone unit="page" n="42v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>me also, I am your soon, too, oh my father.’</l><l n="35">And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>he said, ‘Your brother Isaac came with deceitfulness, and he took<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>your blessing.’</l><l n="36">And Esau said, ‘Was his name really called<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Jacob? And he cheated me these two times.<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>He took my birthright, and, lo, now he has taken<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>my blessing.’ And he said to his father, ‘Lo, have you not left in secret<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>a blessing for me?’</l><l n="37">And Isaac answered and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>said to Esau, ‘Lo, I have made him your superior, and<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>I have given all his brothers as servants, and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>I have sustained him with grain and must. And what shall I do here for you,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>my son?’</l><l n="38">And Esau said to his father,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>‘Is it one blessing that you had, my father? Bless me also, I am<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>your soon, too, oh my father.’ And Esau raised his voice, and wept.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="39">And Isaac his father answered and said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>‘Lo, your dwelling will be in the fatness of the earth,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and the dew of the skies from above will quench the thirst<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of your land.</l><l n="40">And by your sword you will live on, and<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>you will serve your brother. And it shall be, when you shall gain strength,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>that you shall crush his yoke from your neck.’</l><l n="41"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And Esau became hostile to Jacob because of the blessing<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>with which his father blessed him, and Esau said in his heart,<milestone unit="page" n="43r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>‘When the days of mourning for my father will get closer, I will kill my brother Jacob.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="42">And these words of Esau her older son were told to Rebekah.<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>So she sent and called Jacob,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>her younger son, and said to him, ‘Lo, your brother Esau<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>brags concerning you, to kill you.</l><l n="43"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>So now, oh my son, listen to my voice and get up, flee<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to Laban, my brother, to Haran.</l><l n="44">And<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>live with him some time, until your brother’s fury turns back.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="45">Until your brother’s fury turns back<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>from you and he forgets what you have done to him. And I will send<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and take you from there. Why should I be deprived of the two of you as well<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>in one day? <delSpan spanTo="#del005"/>seg type="commented" n="#seg013"/<anchor xml:id="del005"/>For if he kills you, he<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>will be also killed.’<delSpan spanTo="#del006"/>anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg013"/<anchor xml:id="del006"/><ref target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor"/></l><l n="46">And Rebekah said to Isaac,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>‘I am weary of my life before the daughters of Heth. If<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Jacob takes a wife of the daughters of Heth like these<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>daughters of the land, what for is a life to me?’</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 27:13.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 27:33.</note><note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Gen 27:45.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
