<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 43</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 43</title><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the famine became stronger in the land.</l><l n="2">And it was, when<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>they had finished to eat up the grain which they had brought<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>from Egypt, that their father said to them, ‘Go again, buy<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>us a little grain.’</l><l n="3">And Judah said<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to him, saying, ‘The man certified to us,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>saying, “You shall not see my face, if your brother is not<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>with you.”</l><l n="4">If you are sending our brother<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>with us, we will go down and buy you grain.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="5">And if you are not sending, we will not go down, because the<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>man said to us, “You shall not see my face, if your brother is not<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>with you.”’</l><l n="6">And Israel said, ‘Why have you done<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>me wrong, to tell the man whether you had a brother?’</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="7">And they said, ‘The man asked about us<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and about our kindred, saying, “Is your father still alive?<milestone unit="page" n="73r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Do you have another brother?” And we told him according to these words.<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>Could we have known that he would say, “Bring your brother down”?’</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="8">And Judah said to Israel, his father, ‘Send<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the boy with me, and let us arise and go, and let us live and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>not die, we and you and our infants as well.</l><l n="9">Let me take the responsibility<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>for him. From my hand you shall seek him. If I do not bring him to you,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and if I do not set him before you, then I will sin against you for all the days.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="10">For if we had not delayed, by now we would have returned<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>these two times.’</l><l n="11">And Israel, their father, said to them<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>‘If that is how it is here, do this: Take of the excellent<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>fruits in the land in your vessels, and carry down the man<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>a present: a little balm, and a little honey, spices, and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>mastic, pistachio nuts, and almonds.</l><l n="12">And take <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>double the<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> silver<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>in your hand; and the silver that was brought back<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>in the mouth of your sacks, take it again in your hand. Maybe<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>it was an oversight.</l><l n="13">And take your brother, and arise,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>go back to the man.</l><l n="14">And may the mighty God give you<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>mercy before the man, that he may send your other<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>brother and Benjamin to you. And I: when I was deprived of<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Josef, so were I deprived of Simeon.’</l><l n="15">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the men took that present, and they took <seg type="commented" n="#seg002"/>double the<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg002"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/> silver<milestone unit="page" n="73v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>in their hand and Benjamin. And they rose up and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>went down to Egypt and stood before Joseph.</l><l n="16">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to him who<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>was to the superior of his house, ‘Bring these men<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>to the room, and slaughter and make ready |an animal|,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>because these men will eat with me at noon.’</l><l n="17"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the man did as Joseph told him, and the man brought the<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>men to Joseph’s house.</l><l n="18"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And the men were afraid, because they were brought to Joseph’s house,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and they said, ‘Because of the silver that was returned in our sacks<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>the first time are we brought in, that he may seek a pretext against us, and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg003"/><supplied reason="lost">†tie and close</supplied><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg003"/><ref target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor"/> us, and take us for slaves — and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>our donkeys.</l><l n="19">And they came near to the man<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>that was the superior over Joseph’s house, and they spoke<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>with him at the door of the house.</l><l n="20">And they said,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>‘We pray you, my lord, we came down the first time to buy<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>grain.</l><l n="21">And it was, when <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>we came</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> to the place of overnight stay,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>that we opened our sacks, and, lo, every man’s silver<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>was in the mouth of his sack, our silver in its |full| weight. And we have brought it back<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>in our hand.</l><l n="22">And we have brought other silver<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>down in or hand to buy grain. We do not know who put<milestone unit="page" n="74r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>our silver in our sacks.’</l><l n="23">And he said,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>‘Welfare to you, do not be afraid. Your God and the God of your father<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>has given you treasure in your sacks: Your silver reached<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>me.’ And he brought Simeon out to them.</l><l n="24">And<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the man brought the men to Joseph’s house,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and gave them water, and they washed their feet, and he gave food for their donkeys.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="25">And they made ready the<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>present for Joseph’s coming at noon because they heard<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>that they will eat bread there.</l><l n="26">And Joseph came<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>to the room, and they brought the present for him which<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>was in their hand to the room, and bowed themselves to him to the ground.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="27">And he asked them of their health, and said,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>‘Is your old father of whom you spoke in |good| health? Is he still alive?’</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="28">And they answered, ‘Your servant, our father, is in |good| health. He is still<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>alive.’ And they bowed down, and bowed themselves.</l><l n="29">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>he raised his eyes, and saw his brother Benjamin,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>his mother’s son, and said, ‘Is this your younger brother,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of whom you spoke to me?’ And he said, ‘God be merciful to you,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>my son.’</l><l n="30">And Joseph hurried because his compassion grew warm<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>for his brother. And he came to weep and entered his chamber<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and wept there.</l><l n="31">And he washed his face, and went out,<milestone unit="page" n="74v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and strengthened himself, and said, ‘Put the bread.’</l><l n="32">And<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>they served him separately, and them separately, and for the Egyptians,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>who did eat with him, separately, because the Egyptians could not<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>eat bread with the Hebrews, because that is an abomination<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>to Egypt.</l><l n="33">And they sat before him,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the firstborn according to his birthright, and the younger<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>according to his youth. And the men were amazed<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>looking at one another.</l><l n="34">And he lifted<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>gifts to them from before Josef, but Benjamin’s gift<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>was five times more than the gift of all of them.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And they drank, and got drunk with him.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Lit. ‘second’.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">Lit. ‘second’.</note><note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">An uncertain interpretation of <emph>jalajapma</emph>.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
