<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Exodus 21</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Exodus 21</title><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l><emph>Parashat Mishpatim</emph></l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="1">And these are the judgments<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>which you shall set before them.</l><l n="2">If you<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>buy a Hebrew servant, he shall serve six years and in the seventh<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>he shall go out free, for nothing.</l><l n="3">If he, himself, comes in single,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>he, himself, shall go out in single. If he was a married man,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>then his wife shall go out with him as well.</l><l n="4">If his master gives<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>him a wife, and she bears him sons or daughters, the<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>wife and her children shall be her master’s, and he, himself, shall go out<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>in single.</l><l n="5">But if the servant plainly says,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>“I loved my master, my wife, and my children;<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>I will not go out free:”</l><l n="6">Then his master shall bring him to judges,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and the judge shall bring him to the door or<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the door post, and his master shall pierce his ear with an awl,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and he shall serve him forever, <seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>that is, |until| the year of jubilee<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>.<milestone unit="page" n="120v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And if a man sells his daughter as a servant,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>she shall not go out as the |men|servants go out.</l><l n="8">If<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>she would seem bad in the eyes of her master who has designed her for himself,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and he redeemed her, he shall have no right to sell her to another people<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>in his deceiving of her.</l><l n="9">And if he designates her for his own son,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>he shall deal with her according to the manner of daughters.</l><l n="10">If<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>he takes another for himself, he shall not diminish her food, her clothing, and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>her place.</l><l n="11">And if he does not do these three<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>for her, she shall go out for nothing, without silver.</l><l n="12">One who strikes a man,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and if he dies, he shall be surely put to death.</l><l n="13">But if he<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>does not hunt, but God makes the opportunity in his hand: I will set<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>a place for you where he may flee.</l><l n="14">But if a man plots against<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>another to kill him by cunning, you shall take him from my altar<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to die.</l><l n="15">And one who strikes his father<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>or his mother shall be put to death.</l><l n="16">And one who steals<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>a man and sells him, or if he is found in his hand,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>shall be surely put to death.</l><l n="17">And one who curses his father or<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>his mother shall be surely put to death.</l><l n="18">And if men quarrel,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and one strikes another with a stone, or with his fist,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and he does not die, but falls to his bed:</l><l n="19">If<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>he rises, and walks <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>outdoors</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> leaning against his staff, the one who struck him shall be guiltless.<milestone unit="page" n="121r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Only he shall pay the compensation for his loss, and shall have him<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>healed.</l><l n="20">And if a man strikes his servant or his<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>maidservant with a staff, and he dies under his hand, he shall be surely<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>avenged.</l><l n="21">Just: if he stands for a day or two,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>he shall not be avenged, for he is his silver.</l><l n="22">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>if men fight, and they hit a pregnant woman, and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>her children go out, and there would be no death, he shall be punished<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>according as the woman’s husband will lay on him. But<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>if they shall not be able to bargain, give this issue to the judges to judge.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="23">But if there is death, then you shall give<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>life for life,</l><l n="24">Eye for eye, tooth for tooth,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>hand for hand, foot for foot,</l><l n="25"><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>Burning wound for burning wound, open wound for open wound,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>bruise for bruise.</l><l n="26">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>if a man strikes the eye of his servant or the eye of his maidservant<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and destroy it, he shall let him go free for his eye.</l><l n="27"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And if he causes his manservant’s tooth or his maidservant’s tooth to fall out,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>he shall let him go free for his tooth.</l><l n="28">If a bull gores<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>a man or a woman and they die,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the bull shall be stoned with stones, and its flesh shall not be eaten,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and the owner of the bull shall be guiltless.</l><l n="29">And if the<milestone unit="page" n="121v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>bull has been goring for long, and this is testified<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to its owner, and he does not watch it, and it kills a man<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>or a woman, the bull shall be stoned with stones, and<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>its owner shall be put to death as well.</l><l n="30">If a ransom<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>is laid on him, he shall give for the redemption of his life whatever<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>is laid on him.</l><l n="31">Whether it gores a son<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>or it gores a daughter, according to this judgment shall it be done<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to it.</l><l n="32">If the bull gores a |man|servant or<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>a maidservant, he shall give to its master thirty mithqals of silver, and the<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>bull shall be stoned with stones.</l><l n="33">And if a man opens<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>a well, or if a man digs a well and does not cover it, and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>an bull or a donkey fall in it,</l><l n="34">The owner of the well<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>shall pay. He shall give back silver to its owner, and the dead one<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>shall be his.</l><l n="35">And if a man’s bull <supplied reason="lost">hits</supplied><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>another’s bull, and if it dies, they shall sell the<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>live bull, and divide in half the silver<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>for it, and they shall divide in half the dead one as well.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="36">Or: if it is known that it is a goring bull for long,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and its owner does not watch it,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>he shall pay a bull for the bull, and the dead one shall be<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>his.</l><l n="37">If a man steals a bull or a sheep and slaughters it<milestone unit="page" n="122r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>or sells it, he shall pay him five oxen<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>for a bull, and four sheep for a sheep.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Exo 21:6, cf. TKow.01: ‘the meaning of which is “until the jubilee”’.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">K: <emph>assists in birth</emph>; a scribal error. | TKow.01: <emph>hits</emph>. | H: <emph>gores</emph>. | C: <emph>gores</emph>.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
