<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Leviticus 3</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Leviticus 3</title><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="1">And if his offering is a sacrifice of a peace offering,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>if he offers it from the cattle,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>whether male or female, he shall bring it forward unblemished before the Lord.</l><milestone unit="page" n="160r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="2">And he shall reach out his hand over the head of his offering<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and slaughter it at the door of the tent of meeting, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall sprinkle the blood on the altar<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>all around.</l><l n="3">And he shall bring forward from<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering by fire to the Lord: the fat that<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>covers the stomach, and all the fat that is<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>on the stomach,</l><l n="4">And the two kidneys,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and the fat that is on them, which is at the loins,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and the extra of it that is above the liver:<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>he shall take it away with the kidneys.</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And Aaron’s sons shall burn it on the altar<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>next to the burnt offering, which is on the wood that is<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>on the fire, an offering by fire, an aroma of acceptance to the Lord.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And if his offering for a sacrifice of peace offering to the Lord is from the flock,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>male or female, he shall offer it unblemished.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="7">If he brings forward a lamb for his offering,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>he shall bring it forward before the Lord.</l><l n="8">And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>he shall reach out his hand over the head of his offering and slaughter it<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>before the tent of meeting, and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>its blood on the altar all around.</l><l n="9"><milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And he shall bring forward from the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering by fire to the Lord:<milestone unit="page" n="160v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>its fat, and the entire |fat| tail — he shall take it away from opposite the <supplied reason="lost">†backbone</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> –<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>and the fat that covers the stomach, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>all the fat that is on the stomach,</l><l n="10">And the<milestone unit="line" n="4"/><addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>two</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>at the loins, and the extra fat above the liver:<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>he shall take it away with the kidneys.</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And the priest shall burn it on the altar: bread, an offering by fire<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to the Lord.</l><l n="12">And if his offering is a goat, then<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>he shall bring it forward before the Lord.</l><l n="13">And he shall reach out<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>his hand over the head of it and slaughter it before the tent<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of meeting, and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle its blood<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>on the altar all around.</l><l n="14">And he shall offer<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>from it his offering, an offering by fire to the Lord: the fat<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>that covers the stomach, and all the fat<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>that is on the stomach,</l><l n="15">And the two kidneys,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>and the fat that is on them, which is at the loins, and the<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>extra fat above the liver: he shall take it away with the kidneys.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="16">And the priest shall burn them<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>on the altar: bread, an offering by fire, an aroma of acceptance. All fat is the Lord’s.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="17">It shall be an eternal statute throughout your generations, in all your dwelling<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>places: you shall not eat any fat and any blood.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">An uncertain interpretation of <emph>qysylyr orun</emph>. Probably a mistranslation of BHeb. <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">הֶעָצֶה </foreign>‘the spine’ (a hapax legomenon, Lev 3:9); lit. ‘the place which is squeezed’. The Hebrew word could have been confused with the Heb. root <foreign xml:lang="he" style="unicode-bidi: embed;">עסה </foreign>‘to squeeze, to press’.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
