<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 4</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 4</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-21-2" n="21" prev="ADub.III.73.003.003.trl.xml#line-21-1" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="page" n="161r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            to Moses, saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">‘Speak to the children of Israel,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            saying, “A soul who sins by mistake by doing
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            any of the commandments of the Lord that are not to be done, and does
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            any one of them:</l>
                        <l n="3">If the anointed priest, which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            is the High Priest, is guilty according to the sin of the people,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            he shall bring forward for his sin, which he has sinned, a calf,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            unblemished young of cattle, to the Lord for a sin offering.</l>
                        <l n="4">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            he shall bring the calf to the door of the tent of meeting before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            the Lord and shall reach out his hand over the calf’s head
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and slaughter the calf before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="5">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            And the anointed priest shall take of the calf’s blood and bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            it to the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="6">And the priest shall dip
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            his finger in the blood and sprinkle some of the blood seven times
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            before the Lord, before the veil of the Holy.</l>
                        <l n="7">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            And the priest shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            of sweet incense before the Lord, which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            is in the tent of meeting. And he shall pour all the blood of the calf
                            of the sin offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            at the base of the altar, of the altar of the burnt offering, which is
                            at the door
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="8">And he shall take off all the fat of the calf
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            of the sin offering from it: all the fat that covers the stomach
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            and all the fat that is on the stomach,</l>
                        <l n="9">And the
                            <milestone unit="page" n="161v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            two kidneys, and the fat that is on them,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            which is at the loins, and the extra of it that is
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            above the liver: he shall take it away with the kidneys,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="10">As it is taken off from the bull of the sacrifice of peace offerings.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            And the priest shall burn them on the altar of the burnt offering,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="11">And the skin of the calf, and all its
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            flesh, with its head, and with its knees, and its entrails, and its
                            dung.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="12">And he shall he carry forth the whole calf
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            outside the camp to a clean place, at the place where the ashes are
                            poured out,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and burn it on the wood with fire.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            It shall it be burned at the place where the ashes are poured out.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="13">And if the whole congregation of Israel makes a mistake, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            the matter is hidden from the superiors of the assembly, and they do one
                            of any
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of the commandments of the Lord that are not to be done and are
                            guilty,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="14">And the sin over which they have sinned is known,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            the assembly shall bring forward a calf, the young of cattle for a sin offering,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and bring it before the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="15">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            the elders of the congregation shall reach out their hands over the head
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of the calf before the Lord and he shall slaughter the calf before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="16">And the anointed priest shall bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            some of the calf’s blood to the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="17">And the priest shall dip
                            <milestone unit="page" n="162r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            his finger in the blood and sprinkle it seven times
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            before the Lord, before the veil of the Holy.</l>
                        <l n="18">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            And he shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            is before the Lord, that is in the tent of meeting, and shall pour all
                            of the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            at the base of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="19">And he shall separate all its fat from it,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            and burn it on the altar.</l>
                        <l n="20">And he shall do to the calf
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            as he did to the calf of the sin offering, which is his own. So shall he do
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            to it. And the priest shall ask for atonement for them, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            their sin will be forgiven.</l>
                        <l n="21">And he shall carry the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            calf outside the camp and burn it as
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            he burned the first calf. It is a sin offering of the assembly.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="22">When a prince sins and does one of any
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of the commandments of the Lord his God that are not to be done,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            by mistake and is guilty,</l>
                        <l n="23">Or
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            if his sin which he has sinned is made known to him, then he shall bring
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            his offering, a kid of the goats, an unblemished male.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                        <l n="24">And he shall reach out his hand over the head of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            kid and slaughter it in the place where he slaughters the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            burnt offering before the Lord. It is a sin offering.</l>
                        <l n="25">And the priest shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it on the horns
                            <milestone unit="page" n="162v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            of the altar of burnt offering and shall pour out its blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            at the base of the altar of burnt offering.</l>
                        <l n="26">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            he shall burn all its fat on the altar, as the fat of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            sacrifice of peace offerings. And the priest shall ask for atonement
                            over him from his sin,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and it shall be forgiven for him.</l>
                        <l n="27">An if a soul of the people of the land sins by
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            mistake by doing one of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            commandments of the Lord that are not to be done and is guilty,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                        <l n="28">Or if his sin which he has sinned is made known to him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            then he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            an unblemished female, for his sin which he has sinned.</l>
                        <l n="29">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            And he shall reach out his hand over the head of the sin offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            and slaughter the sin offering in the place he slaughters
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            the burnt offering.</l>
                        <l n="30">And the priest shall take some of the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            with his finger and put it on the horns
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            of the altar of burnt offering and shall pour all of its the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            at the base of the altar.</l>
                        <l n="31">And he shall take away all its fat,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            as the fat is taken away from the sacrifice
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of peace offerings, and the priest shall burn it on the altar for a
                            pleasing aroma
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            to the Lord. And the priest shall ask for atonement for him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and it shall be forgiven him.</l>
                        <l n="32">And if he brings a lamb
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            as his offering for a sin offering, he shall bring it an unblemished
                            female.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="163r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="33">And he shall reach out his hand over the head of the sin offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            and slaughter it for a sin offering in the place where he slaughters the
                            burnt offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="34">And the priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering
                            with his finger and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering and shall pour all of
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            its blood at the base of the altar.</l>
                        <l n="35">And he shall take away all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            its fat, as the fat of the lamb is taken away from the sacrifice of the
                            peace offerings,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            and the priest shall burn them on the altar, next to the offerings made
                            by fire
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            to the Lord. And the priest shall ask for atonement for his sin
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-9-1" n="9" next="ADub.III.73.003.005.trl.xml#line-9-2" />
                            which he has sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
