<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Leviticus 14</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Leviticus 14</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l><emph>Parashat Metzora</emph></l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="1">And the Lord spoke to Moses,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            saying,</l>
                        <l n="2">‘This shall be the teaching
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of the leper in the day of his cleansing: And he shall be brought to the
                            priest:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="3">And the priest shall go out of the camp, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            the priest shall see, and, lo, if the disease of leprosy has been healed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            from the leper,</l>
                        <l n="4">The priest shall command, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            one shall take for him that is to be cleansed from leprosy: two field birds,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            clean, and cedar wood and scarlet silk and aspergillum.</l>
                        <l n="5">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            And the priest shall command and he shall slaughter one of the birds
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            in an earthen vessel under running water.</l>
                        <l n="6">The
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            living bird: he shall take it and the cedar wood and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            scarlet silk and the aspergillum, and shall dip them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was slaughtered
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            under the running water.</l>
                        <l n="7">And the priest shall sprinkle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            on the one being purified from the leprosy seven times,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird go
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            over the surface of the field.</l>
                        <l n="8">And the one being purified shall wash
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            his clothes and shave off all his hair and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            wash his body in water, and he will be pure. And after that he shall come
                            <milestone unit="page" n="181r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            into the camp. And shall dwell outside of his tent seven days.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                        <l n="9">And it shall be, on the seventh day: he shall shave off all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            the hair of his head and his beard and the eyebrows
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            of his eyes, even all his hair he shall shave off, and he shall wash
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            his clothes, he shall wash his body in water,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and he shall be clean.</l>
                        <l n="10">And on the eighth day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            he shall take two unblemished |male| lambs, and one unblemished
                            one-year-old female lamb,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and three tenths |of a measure| of fine flour for a grain offering,
                            mixed with oil,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and one log of oil.</l>
                        <l n="11">And the priest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            who is purifying shall set the man being purified, and them as well,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            before the Lord, at the door of the tent of meeting.</l>
                        <l n="12">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            the priest shall take one lamb and bring it forward for a guilt
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            offering, and the log of oil, and elevate them for a wave offering
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="13">And he shall slaughter the lamb
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            in the place where he shall slaughter the sin offering and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            burnt offering, in the holy place, because the guilt offering is like
                            the sin offering,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            it is the priest’s. It is the holy of holies.</l>
                        <l n="14">And he shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            some of the blood of the guilt offering, and the priest shall put it on the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            soft place of the ear on the right <addSpan spanTo="#add001"
                                 /><emph>side</emph><anchor xml:id="add001" /> of the one being
                            purified and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            on the thumb of his right hand and on the great toe
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            of his right foot.</l>
                        <l n="15">And
                            <milestone unit="page" n="181v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            the priest shall take some of the log of oil, and <supplied
                                reason="lost">pour</supplied><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor" />
                            it on the palm
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            of his left hand.</l>
                        <l n="16">And the priest shall dip the finger
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            of his right hand in the oil that is on his left palm and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            shall sprinkle some of the oil with his finger seven times before the
                            Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                        <l n="17">And shall the priest put the rest of the oil that is on his palm
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            on the soft place of the right ear
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            of the one being purified and on the thumb of his right
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            hand and on the great toe of his right foot, over the blood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of the guilt offering.</l>
                        <l n="18">And he shall put
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            what is left of the oil that is on the priest’s palm on the head
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            of the one being purified. And the priest shall ask for atonement for him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="19">And the priest shall make the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            sin offering and ask for atonement for the one being purified
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            from his uncleanness. And afterward he shall slaughter the burnt
                            offering.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                        <l n="20">And the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            grain offering on the altar. And the priest shall ask for atonement for him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            and he will be clean.</l>
                        <l n="21">But if the one being purified is poor,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            and his hand cannot attain |enough|, then he shall take one lamb
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            of the guilt offering for a waved offering, to ask for atonement for
                            himself, and one tenth
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            |of a measure| of fine flour mixed with oil for a grain offering and a
                            log of oil,</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="22">And two turtledoves or two young pigeons,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="182r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            whichever his hand can attain. And one shall be a sin offering and one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            a burnt offering.</l>
                        <l n="23">And he shall bring them on the eighth day
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            for his cleansing to the priest, to the door of the tent of meeting,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="24">And the priest shall take the lamb
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            of the guilt offering and the log of oil, and the priest shall elevate
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            them for a wave offering before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="25">And he shall slaughter
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            the lamb of the guilt offering, and the priest shall take
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            some of the blood of the guilt offering and put it on the soft part
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            of the right ear of the one being purified and on the thumb
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            of his right hand and on the great toe
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            of his right foot.</l>
                        <l n="26">And the priest shall pour the oil
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            on his left palm.</l>
                        <l n="27">And the priest shall sprinkle
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            with his <supplied reason="lost">right</supplied><ref target="#fn2"
                                type="noteAnchor" /> finger some of the oil that is on the palm
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of his left hand seven times before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="28">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the priest shall put some of the oil that is on his palm on the soft place
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            of the right ear of the one being purified and on the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            thumb of his right hand and on the great toe
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            of his right foot, over the place of the blood of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            guilt offering.</l>
                        <l n="29">And he shall put what is left of the oil that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            is on the priest’s palm on the head
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            of the one being purified, to ask for atonement for him before the
                            Lord.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="182v" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="30">And he shall make one of the turtledoves or of the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            young pigeons, whichever his hand can attain.</l>
                        <l n="31">Whichever
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            his hand will attain: one a sin offering and one
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            a burnt offering, with the grain offering. And the priest shall ask for
                            atonement for the one being purified
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            before the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="32">This is the teaching of him
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            in whom is the disease of leprosy, whose hand cannot attain
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            for his cleansing.’</l>
                        <l n="33">And the Lord spoke to Moses
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and to Aaron, saying,</l>
                        <l n="34">‘When you come to the land of Canaan,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            which I am giving to you for a possession, and I will put the disease
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            of leprosy in a house at the land of your possession.</l>
                        <l n="35">And the owner of the house,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the one whose house it is, shall come and tell the priest, saying,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            “It appears like a disease to me in the house.”</l>
                        <l n="36">And the priest shall command
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            that they gather the house before
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            the priest comes to see the disease, so that all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            that is in the house does not become unclean. And, after that, the
                            priest shall come
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            to see the house.</l>
                        <l n="37">And the priest shall look
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            on the disease, and, lo, if the disease is <addSpan spanTo="#add002"
                                 /><emph>in the</emph>
                            <emph>walls</emph>
                            <emph>of the house</emph><anchor xml:id="add002" /> with layers
                            appearing green
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            or appearing red, and they appear to be deeper
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            than |the surface of| the wall:</l>
                        <l n="38">Then the priest shall go out from the middle of the house
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            to the door of the house, and he shall shut the house up seven
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            days.</l>
                        <l n="39">And the priest shall go back on the seventh day and
                            <milestone unit="page" n="183r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            shall look, and, lo, if the disease is spread in the walls
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            of the house:</l>
                        <l n="40">Then the priest shall command that they take away
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            the stones in which the disease is, and they shall cast them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            to an unclean place outside the city.</l>
                        <l n="41">And
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            he shall scrape the house inside all around, and they shall pour
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            out the dust that they scrape off outside the city to an unclean
                            place.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="42">And they shall take other stones and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            bring them in place of the stones, and he shall take other dust,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and shall smear the house.</l>
                        <l n="43">And if the disease comes back
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            and spreads in the house after taking away the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            stones and after scraping the house and after smearing it:</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="44">The priest shall come and look, and, lo,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            the disease has spread in the house, it is a terminal leprosy in the house.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            It shall be unclean.</l>
                        <l n="45">And he shall demolish the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            house, its stones, and the wood of it, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            all the dust of the house, and he shall carry them out of the city to
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            an unclean place.</l>
                        <l n="46">And he that comes into the house all
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            the days that it is shut up shall be unclean until the evening.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                        <l n="47">And he that lies in the house shall wash his clothes,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and he that eats in the house shall wash his clothes.</l>
                        <l n="48">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            And if the priest shall come in and look on it, and, lo,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="183v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            the disease has not spread in the house after the house was smeared,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the disease is
                            healed.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                        <l n="49">And to cleanse the house he shall take two birds and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            cedar wood and scarlet silk and aspergillum.</l>
                        <l n="50">And he shall slaughter
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            one of the birds over an earthen vessel over running water.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                        <l n="51">And he shall take the cedar wood and the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            aspergillum and the scarlet silk and the living bird,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            and dip them in the blood of the slaughtered bird and in the running
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            water, and he shall sprinkle it at the house seven times.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                        <l n="52">And he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            and with the running water and with the living bird and with the cedar wood
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            and with the aspergillum and with the scarlet silk.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                        <l n="53">And he shall let go the living bird out of the city
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            over the surface of the fields, and ask for atonement for the house.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            And it will be clean.’</l>
                        <l n="54">This is the teaching for every disease
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            of leprosy, and for a scab,</l>
                        <l n="55">And for the leprosy
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            of a garment and of a house,</l>
                        <l n="56">And for a sore, and for a swelling, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            for a spot,</l>
                        <l n="57">To teach when it is unclean and
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="Lev014-P183v-L19_trl" n="19" next="ADub.III.73.003.015.trl.xml#Lev015-P183v-L19_trl" />
                            when it is clean. This is the teaching of leprosy.</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app>
                        <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">K: <emph>put</emph>; a scribal error. |
                            TKow.01: unvocalized text. | H: <emph>pour</emph>. | C:
                                <emph>pour</emph>.</note>
                        <note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">K: deest; a scribal error.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
