<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Deuteronomy 29</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Deuteronomy 29</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="19"/><l n="1">And Moses called to all<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Israel, and said to them, ‘You have seen<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>all that the Lord did before your eyes in the land<milestone unit="page" n="330r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of Egypt to Pharaoh and to all his servants and to all his land,</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="2">The great tests which your eyes have seen,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the signs and those great tokens.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="3">But the Lord has not given you a mind<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>to know and eyes to see and ears to hear<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>until this day.</l><l n="4">And I have led you<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>forty years in the wilderness, your clothes have not worn away<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>on you, and your shoes have not worn away on your foot,</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="5">You have not eaten bread, and you have not drunk wine, and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>you have not drunk strong drink, that you may know that I am the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>your God.</l><l n="6">And you came to this place.<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And Sihon, king of Heshbon, and Og, king<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of Bashan, came out against us, and we smote them.</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>And we took their land and gave it as inheritance<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to the Reubenites and to the Gadites and to the half<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>tribe of Manasseh.</l><l n="8">And you shall keep the<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>words of this covenant and do them, that you<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>may prosper in all that you do.<milestone unit="line" n="19"/><emph>Parashat Nitzavim</emph></l><milestone unit="page" n="330v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="9">You are standing today,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>all of you, before the Lord your God — your superiors,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the superiors of your tribes, your elders and your overseers,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>all the men of Israel,</l><l n="10">Your infants, your wives and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>your stranger who is in your camp, from one who cuts<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>your wood to one who draws of your water —</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>For you to cross and enter into the covenant of the Lord your God and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>into his curse, which the Lord your God makes with you today,</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="12">In order to establish you today for him<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>as a people, and he will be a God to you as<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>he has said to you and as he has sworn to your fathers: to Abraham,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to Isaac, and to Jacob.</l><l n="13">It is not<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>with you alone that I am making<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>this covenant and this curse,</l><l n="14"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>But with the one who is here with us,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>stands today before the Lord our God, and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>also with the one who is not here with us today.</l><l n="15"><milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Because you know that we stayed in the land of Egypt<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and that we passed among the kingdoms that<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>you passed.</l><l n="16">And you have seen their abominations<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and their vanities, of wood and stone,<milestone unit="page" n="331r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of silver and gold, which were with them.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="17">Lest there be among you a man or woman or<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>family or tribe whose heart turns away<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>today from the service of the Lord our God to go and serve<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the gods of their kingdoms; lest<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>there be among you a root spreading poison and wormwood:</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="18">And it shall be, when he hears the words<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of this curse, that he will bless himself<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>in his heart, saying, “I will have peace, though<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>I will walk in the obstinacy of my heart, so as to drive away<milestone unit="line" n="11"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>the righteous and the wicked<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/>:</l><l n="19">The Lord will not be willing<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>to forgive his sin, because then<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the anger of the Lord and his jealousy will burn against that man,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>be it one man, be it a family,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and he will lie on him all the curses that are written<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>in this book, and the Lord will wipe out his name<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>from under heaven.</l><l n="20">And if<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>it is a tribe, the Lord will separate him, for bad,<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>from of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>covenant that is written in this Law, in the book.</l><l n="21">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the next generation will say — your children that will rise up<milestone unit="page" n="331v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>after you and the foreigner that will come from a far land, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>they will see the punishments of that land and its illnesses<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>with which the Lord has made it ill,</l><l n="22">Sulphur<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>and salt, all the land will be a burnt, it will not be sown, and<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>it will give no produce, and no plant will grow there,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>like the ruining of Sodom and Gomorrah, Admah and Zeboim<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>which the Lord ruined with his anger and with his fury —</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="23">And all the kingdoms will say, “Why<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>has the Lord done thus to this land? What is this burning of this great<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>anger?”</l><l n="24">And they will say,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>“It is because they have left the covenant of the Lord, God<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them out from of the land<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of Egypt.</l><l n="25">And they went and served<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>other gods and worshiped them, gods<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>whom they had not known and whom God has not given to them as an inheritance.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="26">And the anger of the Lord was kindled<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>against this land to bring on it all the<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>curses that are written in this book.</l><l n="27">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the Lord cast them out from their land in anger and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/><delSpan spanTo="#del001"/>great<anchor xml:id="del001"/> fury <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>and great enragement</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> and threw them into exile into another land,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>as it is this day.”</l><l n="28">The secret things<milestone unit="page" n="332r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>belong to the Lord our God, and the revealed |things| are an obligation to be done,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>for us and for our children forever, to do<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>all the words of this law.</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Interpretative translation.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
