<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 2</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Numbers 2</title><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="1">And the Lord spoke to Moses and to Aaron,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>saying,</l><l n="2">‘Every man, the children of Israel, shall camp by his own standard with the signs<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>by their father’s house: they shall camp opposite,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>all around the tent of meeting.</l><l n="3">And the<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>ones camping toward the rising of the sun: eastward is the standard of the camp of Judah<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>by their armies. And the superior over the army is Nahshon,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>son of Amminadab.</l><l n="4">And his army, and those that were numbered<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of them, are seventy-four thousand and six hundred.</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>And the ones camping next to him is the tribe of Issachar. And the prince<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of the children of Issachar is Nethanel, son of Zuar.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And his army, and those that were numbered of them, are fifty-four thousand and<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>four hundred.</l><l n="7">And next to him: the tribe of Zebulun. And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the prince of the children of Zebulun is Eliab the son of Helon.</l><l n="8"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>And his army, and those that were numbered of them, are fifty-seven thousand and four<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>hundred.</l><l n="9">All those numbered in the camp of Judah were a hundred and<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>eighty thousand and six thousand and four hundred, by their armies.<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>They shall set out in the first line.</l><l n="10">The standard of the camp of Reuben<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>is southward, by their armies. And the prince of the children of Reuben<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>is Elizur, son of Shedeur.</l><l n="11">And his army,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and those that are numbered of them, are forty-six thousand and five hundred.</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="page" n="211r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And the ones camping by him is the tribe of Simeon. And the prince<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of the children of Simeon is Shelumiel, son of Zurishaddai.</l><l n="13"><milestone unit="line" n="3"/>And his army, and those that were numbered of them, are fifty-nine thousand and three<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>hundred.</l><l n="14">And the tribe of Gad. And the prince of the children of Gad<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>is Eliasaph, son of Deuel.</l><l n="15">And his army, and those that were numbered<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of them, are forty-five thousand and six hundred and fifty.</l><l n="16">All<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>those numbered in the camp of Reuben are a hundred thousand and fifty-one thousand<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>and four hundred and fifty, by their armies. And they shall set out in the second line.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="17">And the tent of meeting, the camp of the Levites, shall set out<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>in the midst of the camps. As they camp,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>so shall they set out, every man in his place by their standards.</l><l n="18"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>The standard of the camp of Ephraim by their armies is westward. And<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>the prince of the children of Ephraim is Elishama, son of Ammihud.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="19">And his army, and those numbered of them, are forty thousand<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and five hundred.</l><l n="20">And next to him is the tribe of Manasseh. And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the prince of the children of Manasseh is Gamaliel, son of Pedahzur.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="21">And his army, and those numbered of them, are thirty-two<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>thousand and two hundred.</l><l n="22">And the tribe of Benjamin. And the prince<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of the children of Benjamin is Abidan, son of Gideoni.</l><l n="23"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And his army, and those numbered of them, are thirty-five thousand and four<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>hundred.</l><l n="24">All those numbered of the camp of Ephraim are a hundred thousand and<milestone unit="page" n="211v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>eight thousand and a hundred, by their armies. And they shall set out in the third line.</l><milestone unit="line" n="2"/><l n="25">The standard of the camp of Dan is northward, by their armies.<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>And the prince of the sons of Dan is Ahiezer, son of Ammishaddai.</l><l n="26"><milestone unit="line" n="4"/>And his army, and those numbered of them, are sixty-two thousand and seven<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>hundred.</l><l n="27">And the ones camping by him is the tribe of Asher.<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>And the prince of the sons of Asher is Pagiel, son of Ocran.</l><l n="28"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And his army, and those numbered of them, are forty-one thousand and five hundred.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="29">And the tribe of Naphtali. And the prince of the sons of Naphtali<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>is Ahira, son of Enan.</l><l n="30">And his army, and those numbered<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of them, are fifty-three thousand and four hundred.</l><l n="31">All those numbered<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of the camp of Dan are a hundred thousand and fifty-seven thousand and six hundred. They shall set out last<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>by their standards.’</l><l n="32">These are those numbered<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>of the sons of Israel by the house of their fathers. All those numbered of the camps<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>by their armies are six times a hundred thousand and three thousand and five<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>hundred and fifty.</l><l n="33">And the Levites were not numbered among<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the sons of Israel, as the Lord commanded Moses.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="34">And the sons of Israel did according to all that the Lord commanded<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>Moses: so they camped, and so they set out, every man<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>by their families, by the house of their fathers.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
