<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Deuteronomy 27</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title><supplied reason="lost">Deuteronomy 27</supplied></title><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="1">And Moses and the elders of Israel commanded<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the people, saying, ‘Keep all the commandments<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>which I command you this day.</l><l n="2">And it shall be,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>on the day when you shall cross Jordan to the land which the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>your God is giving you, that you shall set yourselves up great stones<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>and grease them with quicklime.</l><l n="3">And you shall write<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>on them all the words of this Law,<milestone unit="page" n="324r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>after you had crossed, that you may come to the land which the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>your God is giving you, a land flowing |with| milk and honey, as<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>the Lord God of your fathers has promised you.</l><l n="4">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>it shall be, when you cross the Jordan, that you shall set up these<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>stones which I command you today<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>in Mount Ebal, and you shall grease them with quicksilver.</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>And you shall build there an altar to the Lord your God, an altar of stones.<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>You shall not elevate iron over them.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>You shall build the altar of the Lord your God of whole stones, and<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>you shall offer burnt offerings on it to the Lord your God.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="7">And you shall sacrifice the sacrifice of peace offerings, and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>you shall eat there, and you shall rejoice before the Lord your God.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="8">And you shall write on the stones<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>all the words of this Law, to declare it well.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="9">And Moses and the priests,<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the Levites, spoke to all Israel, saying, ‘Take heed and listen, oh<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Israel: this day you have become a people to the Lord your God.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="10">And you shall listen to the voice of the Lord your God<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>and do his commandments and his statutes<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>which I command you this day.’</l><l n="11">And Moses commanded<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the people the same day, saying,</l><l n="12"><milestone unit="page" n="324v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>‘These shall stand on Mount Gerizim to bless the people<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>after you had crossed the Jordan:<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Simeon and Levi and Judah and Issachar and Joseph and Benjamin.</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="13">And these shall stand for the curse on Mount Ebal:<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Reuben, Gad and Asher and Zebulun, Dan and Naphtali.</l><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><l n="14">And the Levites shall begin and say<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to all the men of Israel with a loud voice:</l><l n="15">“Cursed<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>is the man who makes any carved god or molten god,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>an abomination to the Lord your God, the work of the hands of a craftsman,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>and puts it in a secret place.” And all the people shall answer<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>and say, “Amen.”</l><l n="16">“Cursed is the one who defiles<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>his father or his mother.” And all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="17">“Cursed is the one who moves his neighbour’s border.” And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><l n="18">“Cursed is the one<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>who misleads the blind on the way.” And all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="19">“Cursed is the one who rejects the justice of a stranger,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>an orphan and a widow.” And all the people shall say, “Amen.”<milestone unit="line" n="18"/></l><l n="21"><addSpan spanTo="#add001"/>2nd<anchor xml:id="add001"/> “Cursed is the one who lies with any kind of animal.” And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><l n="20"><addSpan spanTo="#add002"/>1st<anchor xml:id="add002"/> “Cursed is the one who lies<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>with his father’s wife, because he has uncovered his father’s nakedness.” And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>all the people shall say, “Amen.”<ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/></l><l n="22">“Cursed is the one who lies<milestone unit="page" n="325r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>with his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of his mother.” And all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><l n="23">“Cursed<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>is the one who lies with his mother-in-law.” And all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="24">“Cursed is the one who smites his neighbour secretly.”<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><l n="25"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>“Cursed is the one who takes a bribe to slay a soul<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to spill innocent blood.” And all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="26">“Cursed is the one who does not strengthen<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the words of this Law to do them.” And<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>all the people shall say, “Amen.”</l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">The order of these two verses was corrected by the copyist.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
