<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Genesis 26</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Genesis 26</title><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="1">And there was a famine in the land, other than the first<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>famine that was in the times of Abraham. And Isaac went<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>to Abimelech, king of the Philistines, to Gerar.</l><l n="2">And<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the divine Presence of the Lord appeared to him, and said,<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>‘Do not go down to Egypt. Dwell in the land which I shall tell you of.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="3">Live in this land, and my help will be<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>with you, and I will bless you, for I will give<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>all these lands to you, and to your offspring, and I will establish<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the oath which I swore to Abraham, your father.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="4">And I will multiply your offspring like the stars<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of the skies, and I will give to your offspring<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>all these lands, and in your offspring<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>shall all the kingdoms of the earth be blessed.</l><l n="5">Because<milestone unit="page" n="39r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Abraham obeyed my voice and kept my guard, my commandments,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>my statutes, and my laws.’</l><l n="6">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Isaac dwelt in Gerar.</l><l n="7">And the men<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of the place asked him about his wife, and he said, ‘She is my sister,’ because<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>he was afraid to say, ‘She is my wife,’ saying, ‘Or else the people of the place will kill<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>me for Rebekah, because she is fair in appearance.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="8">And it was, when his days were dragging on,<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>that Abimelech, king of the Philistines, looked through a window,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and saw, and, lo, Isaac was playing with Rebekah, his wife.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="9">And Abimelech called Isaac, and said,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>‘Lo, she is in truth your wife. Why did you say, “She is my sister?”’<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And Isaac said to him, ‘Because I said, “Or else I will die<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>over her.”’</l><l n="10">And Abimelech said, ‘What is this you have done<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>to us? One of the people has almost lain with your wife,<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>and you would have brought guilt on us.’</l><l n="11"><milestone unit="line" n="16"/>And Abimelech ordered all his people, saying, ‘He<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>who touches this man or his wife shall surely<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>be put to death.’</l><l n="12">Then Isaac sowed in that land, and achieved<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>a hundredfold in the same year. And the Lord blessed him.</l><l n="13"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>And the man became great, and advanced, and grew until<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>he became very esteemed and wealthy.</l><l n="14"><milestone unit="page" n="39v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>And he had plenty of sheep, and plenty of cattle, and<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>many servants. And the Philistines envied him.</l><l n="15">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>all the wells which his father’s servants had dug in the times<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>of Abraham his father: the Philistines had covered them, and they filled<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>them with earth.</l><l n="16">And Abimelech said<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>to Isaac, ‘Go away from us, because you have become much mightier than we.’</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="17">And Isaac went away from there, and stopped by the river of<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Gerar, and he dwelt there.</l><l n="18">And Isaac went back<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>and dug the wells of water that they had dug in the times<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of Abraham his father and which the Philistines had covered after<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Abraham died, and he called them by names, like the names that his father had called<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>them.</l><l n="19">And Isaac’s servants<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>dug in the valley, and found there a well of springing water.</l><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><l n="20">And the herdsmen of Gerar quarrelled<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>with Isaac’s herdsmen, saying, ‘The water is ours.’ So he called<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the name of the well Esek, because they argued with him.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="21">And they dug another well, and quarrelled also over that,<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>and he called the name of it Sitnah.</l><l n="22">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>he moved from there, and dug another well, and they did not quarrel<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>over that. So he called the name of it Rehoboth, and he said,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>‘Because now the Lord has widened for us, and we will spread in the land.’</l><milestone unit="page" n="40r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="23">And he went up from there to Beersheba.</l><l n="24">And the<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>divine Presence of the Lord appeared to him at night, and said, ‘I am<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>your father Abraham’s God. Do not fear, because my help<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>is with you, and I will bless you, and multiply your<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>offspring for my servant Abraham’s sake’.</l><l n="25">And he built<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>an altar there, and called upon the name of the Lord, and pitched<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>his tent there. And Isaac’s servants dug a well there.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="26">And Abimelech went to him from Gerar, and Ahuzzath,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>one of his friends, and Phicol, the superior of his army.</l><l n="27">And<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Isaac said to them, ‘Why have you come to me? You<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>have despised me, and you have sent me away from beside you?’</l><l n="28"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>And they said, ‘We have surely seen that the Lord’s help was<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>with you, and we said, “Let there be now an oath of curse<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>between us, even between us and you, and let us make a covenant<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>with you:</l><l n="29">In case you do harm toward us. Because<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>we have not touched you to do bad to you, and because we have done<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>only good to you and have sent you away in peace. You are now<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the blessed of the Lord.”’</l><l n="30">And he made them a feast, and<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>they ate and drank.</l><l n="31">And they rose up early<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>in the morning, and swore one to his brother, and Isaac sent them away,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and they went away from him in peace.</l><l n="32">And<milestone unit="page" n="40v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>it was in that day, and Isaac’s servants came and told<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>him about the waters that they had dug, and said to him,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>‘We have found water.’</l><l n="33">And he called it Shibah. On account of this<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the name of the city is Beer-Sheba to this day.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="34">And Esau was forty years old, and he took a wife,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>Judith, daughter of Beeri, the Hittite, and Basemath, daughter<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of Elon, the Hittite.</l><l n="35">And they were those who made life bitter<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>for Isaac and Rebekah.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
