<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Leviticus 27</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Leviticus 27</title><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="1">And the Lord spoke to Moses,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>saying,</l><l n="2">‘Speak to the children of Israel, and say<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to them, “When a man will separate a special vow by your valuation of persons for the Lord,</l><l n="3"><milestone unit="line" n="16"/>Then your valuation shall be: A male from twenty years old even up to sixty years old:<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>your valuation shall be fifty mithqals of silver, by the mithqal<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of the Holy.</l><l n="4">And if it is a female, then your valuation shall be<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>thirty mithqals.</l><l n="5">And if it is from five years |old| even up to twenty years |old|,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>then your valuation shall be: |for| a male twenty mithqals, and for a female<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>ten mithqals.</l><l n="6">And if it is from a month old up to five years |old|,<milestone unit="page" n="206r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>then your valuation shall be |for| the male five mithqals of silver and for a female<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>three mithqals of silver.</l><l n="7">And if it is from sixty years old<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and above: if it is a male, then your valuation shall be fifteen<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>mithqals, and for the female ten mithqals.</l><l n="8">But if he is poorer<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>than your valuation, then one shall stand him before the priest, and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the priest shall value him. According to what the power of the hand<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>of the one that vowed can attain shall the priest value him.</l><l n="9">And if<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>it is such an animal from which offering is brought forward to the Lord, all<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>that is given of it to the Lord shall be holy.</l><l n="10">He shall not exchange it or<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>change it, good for bad or bad for good.<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>And if he shall at all exchange animal for animal, then<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>it and the one exchanged shall be holy.</l><l n="11">And if<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>it is any <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>unclean</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> animal from which sacrifice is not brought forward to the Lord,<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>then one shall stand the animal before the priest.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="12">And the priest shall value it, between good and<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>bad: according to your valuation, oh priest, so shall it be.</l><l n="13">And<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>if its owner will at all redeem it, then he shall add a fifth<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>part of it to your valuation.</l><l n="14">And a man who<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>consecrates his house |to be| holy to the Lord, then the priest shall value it,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>between good and bad: as the priest values,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>it so shall it stand.</l><l n="15">And if the one who consecrates<milestone unit="page" n="206v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>it redeems his own house, then he shall add the fifth part of the silver<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>of your valuation to it, and it shall be his.</l><l n="16">And if<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>a man hallows to the Lord some part of a field of his possession,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>then your valuation shall be according to its seed: the sown seed of<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>a homer of barley for fifty mithqals of silver.</l><l n="17">If<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>he consecrates his field from the year of jubilee, it shall stand, oh priest, according to your valuation.</l><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><l n="18">But if he consecrates<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>his field after the jubilee, then the priest shall calculate<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the silver for him according to the years that remain,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>until the year of the jubilee, and it shall be reduced from your valuation.</l><l n="19">And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>if the one who consecrates the field will indeed redeem it,<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>then he shall add the fifth part of the silver of your valuation<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>to it, and it shall stand as his.</l><l n="20">And if<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>he does not redeem the field, and if he sells the field<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>to another man, it shall not be redeemed anymore.</l><l n="21">And<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>when the field goes out in the jubilee, it |shall be| holy to the Lord, like a devoted field;<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>his possession shall be the priest’s.</l><l n="22">And<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>if a man hallows a field which he has bought, that is not from the fields<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of his possession, to the Lord,</l><l n="23">Then<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>the priest shall calculate for him the amount of your valuation, up to the year of the jubilee,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and he shall give your valuation in that day, a holy |thing| to the Lord.</l><milestone unit="page" n="207r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="24">In the year of the jubilee the field shall return to him from whom it was bought,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>to whom the possession of the land belongs.</l><l n="25">And<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>all your valuations shall be by the mithqal of the Holy: twenty <emph>gög</emph><ref target="#fn1" type="noteAnchor"/> shall be<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the mithqal.</l><l n="26">Just: the firstborn of the animals: if a firstborn is born to the Lord<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>no man shall consecrate it. Whether an ox, or sheep:<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>it is the Lord’s.</l><l n="27">And if a firstborn is born<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>to an unclean animal, then he shall redeem it according to your valuation, and shall add<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>a fifth part to it. And if it is not redeemed, then,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>oh priest, it shall be sold according to your valuation.</l><l n="28">Just: any devoted thing<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>that a man shall devote to the Lord of all that he has — from human<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>or animal or from a field of his possession — shall not be sold<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>nor redeemed: every devoted thing is a holy of holies to the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><l n="29">Anyone devoted who is devoted from humans shall not be redeemed.<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>He shall surely be put to death.</l><l n="30">And all the tithe of the land, from of the seed<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of the land, from the fruit of the tree: to is the Lord’s. It is holy<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>to the Lord.</l><l n="31">And if a man will at all redeem<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>any of his tithes, he shall add to it the fifth part of it.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="32">And all the tithe of the cattle or of the flock, everything that<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>passes under the rod, the tenth shall be holy to the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="33">He shall not inspect whether it be good or bad. And he shall not exchange<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>it: and if he exchanges it at all, then both it and the one exchanged<milestone unit="page" n="207v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>for it shall be holy. It shall not be redeemed.”’</l><l n="34">These are the commandments<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>which the Lord commanded Moses to teach to the children of Israel.<milestone unit="line" n="3"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg001"/>And the Lord commanded these commandments to Moses<anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg001"/><ref target="#fn2" type="noteAnchor"/> on Mount Sinai.<milestone unit="line" n="4"/><emph>And praise be to the great and awesome God with whom light dwells, and with his help –</emph><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><emph>may He be blessed whose name is He Who Dwells Between the Cherubim – the peshatim of the Book of Leviticus are completed.</emph><milestone unit="line" n="6"/><emph>In the name of Him who gives rest to wanderers and vagabonds and strengthens the hand of the poor</emph><milestone unit="line" n="7"/><emph>and seats them in His only home I will start to write the peshat of the book of Pentateuch – of the Book of Numbers.</emph><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg002"/><emph>The day of birth of my beloved young son Zecharia: the 6th day of the parashat Ki Tavo, </emph><seg type="commented" n="#seg003"/><emph>the 22nd</emph>
							<emph>of the</emph>
							<emph>month Elul</emph><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>|of the|<emph> year 549 by the abbreviated counting</emph><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg003"/><ref target="#fn3" type="noteAnchor"/><emph>, may God let him grow up for the Torah, for the commandments and for good deeds. Amen, and may it be God’s will!</emph><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg002"/><ref target="#fn4" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><seg type="commented" n="#seg004"/><emph>The day of birth of my beloved daughter, the young girl Malka </emph><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/><emph>, the 5th day of the parashat Nitzavim, </emph><seg type="commented" n="#seg005"/><emph>the 26th of the month</emph><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><emph>Elul </emph>|of the|<emph> year 552 by the abbreviated counting.</emph><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg005"/><ref target="#fn5" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><ref target="#fn6" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="line" n="13"/><emph>The day of birth of my beloved daughter, the young girl Esther </emph><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/><emph>, the 7th day of the parashat</emph><milestone unit="line" n="14"/><emph>Shoftim, </emph><seg type="commented" n="#seg006"/><emph>the 7th of the month Elul </emph>|of the|<emph> year 555 by the abbreviated counting.</emph><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg006"/><ref target="#fn7" type="noteAnchor"/><anchor type="commented" xml:id="seg004"/><ref target="#fn8" type="noteAnchor"/><milestone unit="page" n="208r"/></l></ab></div></div><div type="apparatus"><listApp><app><note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote">Unidentified unit of weight.</note><note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote">An interpretative addition to Lev 27:34.</note><note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote">I.e., <emph>13 September 1789</emph>.</note><note xml:id="fn4" type="footnote">Inserted by another hand in Hebrew.</note><note xml:id="fn5" type="footnote">I.e., <emph>13 September 1792</emph>.</note><note xml:id="fn6" type="footnote">A catchword was written in this line.</note><note xml:id="fn7" type="footnote">I.e., <emph>9 August 1795</emph>.</note><note xml:id="fn8" type="footnote">Inserted by yet another hand (except the catchword in line 12) in Hebrew.</note></app></listApp></div></body></text></TEI>
