<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Exodus 23</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Exodus 23</title><milestone unit="line" n="4"/><l n="1"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>You shall not accept a false news. You shall not put your hand with the wicked to be<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>a false witness.</l><l n="2">You shall not follow many to do evil. And<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>you shall not testify about a dispute following many to reject<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>judgment.</l><l n="3">And you shall not worship a poor in his lawsuit.</l><milestone unit="line" n="9"/><l n="4">If you meet your enemy’s bull or his donkey going astray,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>you shall bring it back to him.</l><l n="5">If you see a donkey<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>of your enemy lying under its burden, you shall refrain from the thought<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>that you would not want to help him: you shall help with him.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="13"/>You shall not reject the judgement of your poor in his verdict.</l><l n="7"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>Keep far from a false word, do not kill the guiltless and righteous, because<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>I will not justify the wicked.</l><l n="8">And you shall take no bribe, because the bribe<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>blinds the clear-sighted and distorts the words<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>of the righteous.</l><l n="9">And you shall not oppress a stranger, either.<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>And you know the heart of a stranger, because you were strangers in the land<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of Egypt.</l><l n="10">And six years you shall sow your land and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>gather its produce.</l><l n="11">And the seventh year<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>you shall let it lie fallow and stop working on it, and<milestone unit="page" n="124r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>the poor of your people shall eat, and what they leave the animal of the field shall eat.<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>Thus shall you do to your vineyard, and to your olives.</l><l n="12">Six days<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>you shall do your work, and on the seventh day you shall rest, so that<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>your bull and your donkey may rest, and so that<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>the son of your maidservant and even the stranger may rest.</l><l n="13">And pay attention in all things that<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>I have said to you, and make no mention of the name of other gods.<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>Let it not be heard on your mouth.</l><l n="14">You shall keep a feast<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>to me three times in the year.</l><l n="15">You shall keep the feast of unleavened bread.<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>You shall eat unleavened bread seven days, as I commanded you, in the appointed time<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>of the month <emph>Baš Qusqan</emph>, because then you came out from Egypt. And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>none shall appear before my directions empty.</l><l n="16">And the feast<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of harvest, of the ripening of your work, which you have sown in the field.<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>And the feast of ingathering, which is when the year leaves, when you have gathered<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>what you have done from the field.</l><l n="17">Three times<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>in the year all your males shall appear before the directions of the lord: the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="18">You shall not sacrifice the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>And the fat of my feast shall not stay overnight until the morning.</l><l n="19">You shall bring the first<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of the ripening of your land to the house of the Lord your God.<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>You shall not boil a kid in its mother’s milk.</l><l n="20">Lo, I send<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>an angel before you, to keep you in the way, and to bring you<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>to the place which I have prepared.</l><l n="21">Be watchful in front of him,<milestone unit="page" n="124v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and obey his voice. Do not betray him, because he will not pardon your trespasses,<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>because my name is in him, too.</l><l n="22">Because if you<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>obey his voice, and do all that I speak, then<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>I will be an enemy to your enemies, and an oppressor to your oppressors.</l><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="23">Because my Angel will go before you and<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>will bring you to the Amorites and the Hittites and the Perizzites<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>and the Canaanites the Hivites and the Jebusites, and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>I will cut them off.</l><l n="24">You shall not bow down to their gods, and you shall not serve<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>them, and you shall not do like the things they do, but you shall smash<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>them and break down completely their pillars.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="25">And you will serve the Lord your God, and<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>he will bless your bread and your water, and I will take<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>sickness away from the midst of you.</l><l n="26">There will be no miscarrying or<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>barren woman in your land, I will fulfil your days.</l><milestone unit="line" n="15"/><l n="27">I will send my fear ahead of you, and I will stir<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>all the people to whom you shall come, and I will give<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>all your enemies to you by the back of their head.</l><l n="28">And I will send<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the hornet ahead of you, and it will drive out the Hivite and<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>the Canaanite and the Hittite from before you.</l><l n="29"><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>I will not drive them out from before you in one year, lest the land become desolate,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>and the animals of the field multiply against you.</l><l n="30">Little<milestone unit="page" n="125r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>by little I will drive them out from before you, until you hall spread and inherit<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>the land.</l><l n="31">And I will set your border<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>from the Red Sea even to the sea of the Philistines, and from<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the wilderness to the river, because I will put the inhabitants<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of the land in your hand, and you shall drive them out from before you.</l><l n="32"><milestone unit="line" n="6"/>You shall not make a covenant with them and with their gods.</l><l n="33"><milestone unit="line" n="7"/>They shall not dwell in your land, lest they make you sin against me, because<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>if you serve their gods, it will be a snare to you.’</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
