<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ana="#no" />
                <author ana="#no" />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement>
                        <repository>Private archive</repository>
                        <idno>ADub.III.73</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the
                            Haftarah</summary>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p><lg>
                        <l>Deuteronomy 9</l>
                    </lg></p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
                    <ab><title>Deuteronomy 9</title>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                        <l n="1">Listen, oh Israel: you are passing over Jordan today,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            to come to inherit kingdoms greater
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            and mightier than you, great and fortified cities reaching
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            to the skies.</l>
                        <l n="2">A people great and tall, the children
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            of the Anakim, whom you know, and of whom you have heard: “Who can stand
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            before the children of Anak?!”</l>
                        <l n="3">You shall know today
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            that the Lord your God is the one who crosses before you consuming like fire.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            He will destroy them and he will break them down
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            before you, and you will drive them out and destroy them quickly,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            as the Lord has said to you.</l>
                        <l n="4">Do not speak in your heart,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            after that the Lord your God has pushed them out from before you,
                            <milestone unit="page" n="296r" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            saying, “Because of my righteousness the Lord has brought me in to inherit
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            this land,” but it is because of the wickedness of these
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            kingdoms that the Lord destroys them from before you.</l>
                        <l n="5">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            Not because of your righteousness or because of the uprightness of your heart
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            you are coming to inherit their land, but because the wickedness
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            of these kingdoms the Lord your God is destroying
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            them from before you, and that he may establish the word
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            which the Lord swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            to Jacob.</l>
                        <l n="6">And you shall know that the
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            Lord your God gives you this good land to inherit it not because of your righteousness,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            because you are a stiff-necked people.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="7">Remember and do not forget how you made the Lord your God angry
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            in the wilderness. From the day that you went out from the land
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of Egypt until you came to this place, you have been rebellious against
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            the word of the Lord.</l>
                        <l n="8">And you made the Lord angry at Horeb,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            and the Lord became angry with you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            so as to destroy you.</l>
                        <l n="9">When I went up
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            the mountain to receive the tables of stone, the tablets of the covenant which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            the Lord made with you, then I stayed on the mountain forty days
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and forty nights. I did not eat bread and I did not drink water.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                        <l n="10">And the Lord gave to me two
                            <milestone unit="page" n="296v" />
                            <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                            tablets of stone written with the order of God, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            on them all the words, like those which the Lord spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            with you on the mountain from the midst of the fire in the day of
                            assembly.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                        <l n="11">And it was: at the end of forty days
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            and forty nights the Lord gave me the two tablets of stone,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            the tablets of the covenant.</l>
                        <l n="12">And the Lord said
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            to me, “Arise, go down quickly from here, because your people
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            whom you have brought out from Egypt have lost the way. They have gone
                            aside from the way which
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            I commanded them. They have made them a molten god.”</l>
                        <l n="13">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            And the Lord spoke to me, saying, “I have seen
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            this people, and, lo, it is a stiff-necked people.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                        <l n="14">Hold back from me that I may destroy them and that I may blot out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            their name from under heaven, and let me make
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of you a kingdom mightier and greater than they.”</l>
                        <l n="15">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            So I turned and came down from the mount, and the mount was burning
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            in fire: and the two tablets of the covenant were on my two hands.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                        <l n="16">And I looked, and, lo, you had sinned
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            against the Lord your God. You had made yourselves a molten calf.
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            You had gone aside quickly from the way which the Lord had commanded
                            you.</l>
                        <l n="17">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            And I took the two tablets and cast them
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            out of my two hands and broke them in your sight.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="297r" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="18">And I fell down and besought before the Lord,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            like the first |time|, forty days and forty nights — I did not eat bread,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            and I did not drink water — because of all your sins which you sinned,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            in doing what seems bad in the eyes of the Lord, to
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            make him angry,</l>
                        <l n="19">Because I was afraid of the anger
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            and fury with which the Lord was angry with you
                            <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                            to destroy you. But the Lord hearkened to me at that
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            time as well.</l>
                        <l n="20">And the Lord was very angry with Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            so as to destroy him. And I prayed for Aaron
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            at that time as well.</l>
                        <l n="21">And I took your sin,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            the calf which you had made, and burned it
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            in fire and crushed it to grind it very well until
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            it was as small as dust. And I cast the dust
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            of it into the river that descended from the mountain.</l>
                        <l n="22">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="15" />
                            And at Taberah and at Massah and at Kibroth-Hattaavah
                            <milestone unit="line" n="16" />
                            you were making the Lord angry.</l>
                        <l n="23">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="17" />
                            And when the Lord sent you from Kadesh-Barnea, saying,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="18" />
                            “Go and inherit the land which I have given you,”
                            <milestone unit="line" n="19" />
                            then you rebelled against the command of the Lord your God, and you did
                            not believe him,
                            <milestone unit="line" n="20" />
                            and you did not listen to his voice.</l>
                        <l n="24">You have been rebellious against
                            <milestone unit="line" n="21" />
                            the Lord from the day that I knew you.</l>
                        <milestone unit="page" n="297v" />
                        <milestone unit="line" n="1" />
                        <l n="25">And I fell down and besought before the Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="2" />
                            through the forty days and forty nights that I had fallen down and besought
                            <milestone unit="line" n="3" />
                            because the Lord had said he would destroy you.</l>
                        <l n="26">
                            <milestone unit="line" n="4" />
                            And I prayed to the Lord, and said, “Oh Lord
                            <milestone unit="line" n="5" />
                            God, do not crush your people and your share which you have redeemed
                            <milestone unit="line" n="6" />
                            through your greatness, whom you have brought out from Egypt with a
                            strong hand.</l>
                        <milestone unit="line" n="7" />
                        <l n="27">Remember your servants, Abraham, Isaac, and
                            <milestone unit="line" n="8" />
                            Jacob, do not turn |your eyes| to the hardness of this people
                            <milestone unit="line" n="9" />
                            and to its wickedness and to its sin,</l>
                        <l n="28">Lest
                            <milestone unit="line" n="10" />
                            the peoples of the land from which you brought us out will say:
                            <milestone unit="line" n="11" />
                            “Because of the Lord not being able to bring them to the land of which
                            he spoke
                            <milestone unit="line" n="12" />
                            to them, and because he rejected them. He has brought them out
                            <milestone unit="line" n="13" />
                            to kill them in the wilderness.”</l>
                        <l n="29">And they are
                            <milestone unit="line" n="14" />
                            your people and your share whom you brought out by your great power
                            <milestone unit="line" xml:id="line-15-1" n="15" next="ADub.III.73.005.010.trl.xml#line-15-2" />
                            and by your outstretched arm.”</l>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>
