<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title ana="#no"/><author ana="#no"/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Uppsala University, Department of linguistics and philology</publisher><pubPlace>Uppsala, Sweden</pubPlace><date>2020</date><availability status="restricted"><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><settlement>Warsaw, Poland</settlement><repository>Private archive</repository><idno>ADub.III.73</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary ana="#no">A Karaim translation of the Torah and the Haftarah</summary></msContents></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><lg><l>Numbers 26</l></lg></p></abstract></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="edition"><div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"><ab><title>Numbers 26</title><milestone unit="line" n="5"/><l n="1">And it was after the plague,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>and the Lord spoke to Moses and to Eleazar,<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>son of Aaron, the priest, saying,</l><l n="2">‘Take<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>the sum of all the congregation of the children of Israel,<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>from twenty years old and upward, by the house of their fathers, everyone going out to the army<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>in Israel.’</l><l n="3">And Moses and Eleazar,<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>the priest, spoke with them in the steppes of Moab by Jordan<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>of Jericho, saying,</l><l n="4">‘From twenty years old and upward,’<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>as the Lord commanded Moses and the children<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>of Israel, who went out from the land of Egypt.</l><l n="5"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>Reuben, the firstborn of Israel; the children of Reuben: Of Hanoch:<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>his family — the Hanochites. Of Pallu: his family — the Palluites.</l><l n="6"><milestone unit="line" n="17"/>Of Hezron: his family — the Hezronites. Of Carmi: his family — the Carmites.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="7">These are the families of the tribe of Reubenites, and<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>they that were numbered of them: forty-three thousand and seven hundred and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>thirty.</l><l n="8">And the son of Pallu: Eliab.</l><l n="9">And<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>the sons of Eliab: Nemuel, and Dathan, and Abiram. These are the Dathan<milestone unit="page" n="258r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>and Abiram, the representatives of the congregation, who quarrelled<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>with Moses and with Aaron in the congregation of Korah,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>when they quarrelled before the Lord,</l><l n="10">And<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>the earth opened its mouth, and swallowed them up,<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>and consumed Korah, when that congregation died,<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>when the fire consumed two hundred-fifty men: and they became<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>a sign.</l><l n="11">But the children of Korah died not.</l><milestone unit="line" n="8"/><l n="12">The sons of Simeon by their families: Of Nemuel:<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>his family — the Nemuelites. Of Jamin: his family — the Jaminites. Of Jachin:<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>his family — the Jachinites.</l><l n="13">Of Zerah: his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Zerahites. Of Shaul: his family — the Shaulites.</l><l n="14">These are<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>the families of the Simeon: twenty-two thousand and two<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>hundred.</l><l n="15">The children of Gad by their families: Of Zephon:<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>his family — the Zephonites. Of Haggi: his family — the Haggites. Of Shuni:<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>his family — the Shunites.</l><l n="16">Of Ozni: his family — the Oznites.<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>Of Eri: his family — the Erites.</l><l n="17">Of Arod: his family —<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the Arodites. Of Areli: his family — the Arelites.</l><l n="18">These<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>are the families of the children of Gad by those that were numbered of them: forty<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>thousand and five hundred.</l><l n="19">The sons of Judah: Er and<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Onan. And Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan.</l><milestone unit="line" n="21"/><l n="20">And the sons of Judah by their families were:<milestone unit="page" n="258v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>Of Shelah: his family — the Shelanites. Of Perez: his family — the Perezites. Of Zerah:<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>his family — the Zerahites.</l><l n="21">And the sons of Perez were:<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Of Hezron: his family — the Hezronites. Of Hamul: his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>Hamulites.</l><l n="22">These are the families of Judah by those that were numbered:<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>seventy-six thousand and five hundred.</l><l n="23">The sons<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>of Issachar by their families: Of Tola: his family — the Tolaites. Of Puvah:<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>his family — the Punites.</l><l n="24">Of Jashub: his family — the Jashubites. Of Shimron:<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>his family — the Shimronites.</l><l n="25">These are the families<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>of Issachar by those that were numbered: sixty-four thousand and three<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>hundred.</l><l n="26">The sons of Zebulun by their families: Of Sered: his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Seredites. Of Elon: his family — the Elonites. Of Jahleel: his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>Jahleelites.</l><l n="27">These are the families of the tribe of Zebulun<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>by those that were numbered: sixty thousand and five hundred.</l><l n="28"><milestone unit="line" n="14"/>The sons of Joseph by their families: Manasseh and Ephraim.</l><l n="29"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>The sons of Manasseh: Of Machir: his family — the Machirites. And Machir<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>begat Gilead. Of Gilead: his family — the Gileadites.</l><milestone unit="line" n="17"/><l n="30">These are the sons of Gilead: Of Iezer: his family —<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>the Iezerites. Of Helek: his family — the Helekites.</l><l n="31">And<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of Asriel: his family — the Asrielites. And of Shechem: his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Shechemites.</l><l n="32">And of Shemida: his family — the Shemidaites.<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>And of Hepher: his family — the Hepherites.</l><l n="33">And Zelophehad,<milestone unit="page" n="259r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>son of Hepher, had no sons, but only daughters.<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And the names of the daughters of Zelophehad: Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah,<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>and Tirzah.</l><l n="34">These are the families of Manasseh, and<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>those that were numbered of them: fifty-two thousand and seven hundred.</l><l n="35"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>These are the sons of Ephraim by their families: Of Shuthelah:<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>his family — the Shuthelahites. Of Becher: his family — the Becherites. Of Tahan:<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>his family — the Tahanites.</l><l n="36">And these are the sons<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>of Shuthelah: Of Eran: his family — the Eranites.</l><l n="37">These are<milestone unit="line" n="9"/>the families of the sons of Ephraim by those that were numbered: thirty-<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>-two thousand and five hundred. These are the sons of Joseph by their families.</l><milestone unit="line" n="11"/><l n="38">The sons of Benjamin by their families: Of Bela:<milestone unit="line" n="12"/>his family — the Belaites. Of Ashbel: his family — the Ashbelites. Of Ahiram:<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>his family — the Ahiramites.</l><l n="39">Of Shephupham:<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>his family — the Shuphamites. Of Hupham: his family — the Huphamites.</l><l n="40">And<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>the sons of Bela were Ard and Naaman: of Ard: his family —<milestone unit="line" n="16"/>the Ardites. Of Naaman: his family — the Naamites.</l><l n="41">These are<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the sons of Benjamin by their families, and they that were numbered of them:<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>forty-five thousand and six hundred.</l><l n="42">These are the sons<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>of Dan by their families: Of Shuham: his family — the Shuhamites. These<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>are the families of Dan by their families.</l><l n="43">All the families<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>of the Shuhamites, by those that were numbered: sixty-four thousand and<milestone unit="page" n="259v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>four hundred.</l><l n="44">The children of Asher by their families: Of Imna:<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>his family — the Imnites. Of Ishvi: his family — the Ishvites. Of Beriah:<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>his family — the Beriites.</l><l n="45">Of the sons of Beriah: of Heber:<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>his family — the Heberites. Of Malchiel: his family — the Malchielites.</l><l n="46"><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>And the name of the daughter of Asher: Serah.</l><l n="47">These are<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the families of the sons of Asher by those that were numbered: fifty-three thousand and<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>four hundred.</l><l n="48">The sons of Naphtali by their families: Of Jahzeel:<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>his family — the Jahzeelites. Of Guni: his family — the Gunites.</l><l n="49"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>Of Jezer: his family — the Jezerites. Of Shillem: his family — the Shillemites.</l><milestone unit="line" n="10"/><l n="50">These are the families of Naphtali by their families, and<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>they that were numbered of them: forty-five thousand and four hundred.</l><l n="51"><milestone unit="line" n="12"/>These were the numbered of the children of Israel, six times a hundred<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>thousand and also a thousand seven hundred and thirty.</l><l n="52">And<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</l><l n="53"><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>‘The land shall be distributed to these as a portion with the number of names.</l><l n="54"><milestone unit="line" n="16"/>To many you shall give more portions, and to few less portions shall be given.<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>To each man his portion shall be given according to those that were numbered.</l><milestone unit="line" n="18"/><l n="55">Just: the land shall be divided by lot.<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>By the names of the tribes of their fathers they shall inherit.</l><milestone unit="line" n="20"/><l n="56">The portions of it shall be distributed according to the lot,<milestone unit="line" n="21"/>between many and few.’</l><l n="57">And these are they that were numbered<milestone unit="page" n="260r"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/>of the Levites by their families: Of Gershon: his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>Gershonites. Of Kohath: his family — the Kohathites. Of Merari: his family — the Merarites.</l><milestone unit="line" n="3"/><l n="58">These are the families of the Levites: his family — the Libnites,<milestone unit="line" n="4"/>his family — the Hebronites, his family — the Mahlites, his family — the Mushites, his family — the<milestone unit="line" n="5"/>Korathites. And Kohath begat Amram.</l><l n="59">And<milestone unit="line" n="6"/>the name of Amram’s wife was Jochebed, daughter of Levi, whom |her mother| bore to Levi<milestone unit="line" n="7"/>in Egypt. And she bore to Amram Aaron and<milestone unit="line" n="8"/>Moses and Miriam, their sister.</l><l n="60"><milestone unit="line" n="9"/>And to Aaron was born Nadab, and Abihu,<milestone unit="line" n="10"/>Eleazar, and Ithamar.</l><l n="61">And<milestone unit="line" n="11"/>Nadab and Abihu died when they brought forward strange fire before the Lord.</l><milestone unit="line" n="12"/><l n="62">And those that were numbered of them were twenty-<milestone unit="line" n="13"/>-three thousand, all males from a month old and upward, because they were not numbered<milestone unit="line" n="14"/>among the children of Israel, because there was no portion given<milestone unit="line" n="15"/>them among the children of Israel.</l><milestone unit="line" n="16"/><l n="63">These are they that were numbered by Moses and Eleazar,<milestone unit="line" n="17"/>the priest, who numbered the children of Israel in the steppes<milestone unit="line" n="18"/>of Moab by the Jordan of Jericho.</l><l n="64">And among these there was not<milestone unit="line" n="19"/>a man of them whom Moses and Aaron, the priest, numbered,<milestone unit="line" n="20"/>when they numbered the children of Israel in the wilderness of Sinai.</l><milestone unit="page" n="260v"/><milestone unit="line" n="1"/><l n="65">For the Lord had said of them, ‘They will surely die in the wilderness.’<milestone unit="line" n="2"/>And there was <addSpan spanTo="#add001"/><emph>not a man</emph><anchor xml:id="add001"/> was left of them, except Caleb, son of Jephunneh, and<milestone unit="line" n="3"/>Joshua, son of Nun.</l></ab></div></div></body></text></TEI>
